<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brotherly persvvasion to vnitie, and vniformitie in iudgement, and practise touching the receiued, and present ecclesiasticall gouernment, and the authorised rites and ceremonies of the Church of England. VVritten by Thomas Sparke Doctor in Diuinitie. And seene, allowed, and commended by publike authoritie to be printed</title>
            <author>Sparke, Thomas, 1548-1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 259 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23019.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102433</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838218</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838218</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2585</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12700)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2585)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1085:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brotherly persvvasion to vnitie, and vniformitie in iudgement, and practise touching the receiued, and present ecclesiasticall gouernment, and the authorised rites and ceremonies of the Church of England. VVritten by Thomas Sparke Doctor in Diuinitie. And seene, allowed, and commended by publike authoritie to be printed</title>
                  <author>Sparke, Thomas, 1548-1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 83, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes for Roger Iackson, and are to be sold at his shop in Fleet-street neere to the great Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A perswasion to vniformity vnto his Christian brethren.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 23020 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2585:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2585:1"/>
            <p>A BROTHERLY PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SWASION TO VNITIE, AND VNIFORMITIE IN IVDGEMENT, AND PRACTISE TOVCHING THE RECEIVED and preſent Eccleſiaſticall gouernment, and the authoriſed <hi>rites and ceremonies of the Church of England.</hi> VVritten by <hi>Thomas Sparke</hi> Doctor in Diuinitie. And ſeene, allowed, and commanded by publike <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to be printed.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 12.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If it be poſsible, as much as in you is, haue peace with all men.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>COR. 11.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If any luſt to be contentious, we haue no ſuch cuſtoms, nor the Churches of God.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of a pair of compasses, associated with Nicholas Okes (McKerrow 334)</figDesc>
               <p>LABORE ET CONSTANTIA</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes</hi> for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Fleet-ſtreet neere to the great Conduit. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:2585:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of the British royal family, encircled by the Order of the Garter, crowned</figDesc>
                  <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2585:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, IAMES BY THE GRACE OF GOD, OF GREAT BRITAINE, France and Ireland King, and ouer all perſons, and in all cauſes as well Eccleſiaſticall as ciuill, in theſe his dominions, next and immediatly vnder God, Supreme Gouernor, and defender of the ancient, Catholike and Apoſtolike Faith.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Igh and mightie Monarch, and my moſt dread &amp; gratious Soueraigne, being one of them, that by your moſt Honorable Councels letters, in your Maie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſties name, were called to be before your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, at the conference at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> and receiuing there ſuch ſatisfaction as I did by your excellent Maieſties owne moſt readie and apt anſwers to the doubts and obiections there and then propoſed: as I could not but then greatly reioyce in my heart, and praiſe and magnifie the Lord for the ſame, ſo euer ſince, though to the better ſatisfying of all others, I haue not onely in my practiſe accordingly yeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vniuerſall conformitie, but priuately by word and writing alſo haue laboured to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb facs="tcp:2585:3"/>all whom I haue met with, to do likewiſe: yet ſeeing and obſeruing ſo many ſtil to refuſe, I could not but think it my bounden dutie to God and his Church firſt, &amp; then to your highneſſe, by writing ſome ſhort Treatiſe to doe the beſt that I could, to further your moſt gracious &amp; chriſtian purpoſe, reſolution, &amp; determination in the ſaid confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which was (as I conceiued it) by your moſt princely moderation, &amp; reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, firſt of al in our home controuerſies amongſt our ſelues about our Churches Liturgie or Hierarchie, ſo to knit vs all together in vnitie, &amp; verity, as that al our forces hereafter might more ſtrongly be bent &amp; employed againſt our common aduerſaries, ſo the better alſo after to draw them to conformity with vs in the exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and profeſsion of our true and pure religion. And therfore now wel nigh two yeares ago, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing writ this Treatiſe, and finding that the priuat vſe therof, though it hath done good with ſom, yet to that purpoſe could reach but to a few, it hauing in this time comd &amp; bene in the view of ſome of the moſt reuerend Biſh. &amp; ſo hauing
<pb facs="tcp:2585:3"/>alſo got allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by authority to be printed, &amp; hereupon hauing bene by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and many others which haue ſene &amp; read the ſame, much vrged to publiſh it, I am bound thus to dedicate it to your Maieſty, &amp; ſo to offer it to the ſight of all, who ſhalbe pleaſed to read it. And the rather I thought iuſtly I might ſo do, for that the ground of moſt of that I haue ſaid therin to the ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my brethren, ariſes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpeeches, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, &amp; determinations that your highnes ſelf gaue in the forſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference. But indeed I muſt needs confeſſe, I durſt not yet thus far haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured, but vpon comfortable reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of your Mai. vouchſafing the next morning after the ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference to ſend for me, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to giue me that moſt gratious cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; moſt princely kind words that you the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of a book that your highnes vnderſtood I had writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; bin in ſome trouble for in her Ma. time that laſt was, touching ſuccesſion. Pardon me ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt gracious ſoueraign if to teſtify in ſome
<pb facs="tcp:2585:4"/>meaſure my loyalty and thankefulnes for the ſame, I venture now againe into your highneſse preſence, with ſo ſmall a preſent as this. For you being pleaſed to accept the ſame, &amp; to giue it paſſage thus vnder your moſt roial patronage and protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the end aforeſaid, vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it wil &amp; may much the ſooner get liking and entertainment withall, &amp; ſo alſo giue the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſatisfaction and contentment to all them wherſoeuer it finds the ſame. Thus therefore once againe moſt humbly crauing pardon for this my great boldnes, &amp; hoping of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties fauorable acceptance hereof, &amp; moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly vpon the knees of my ſoule begging of the almighty, that your Highnes &amp; your moſt royall iſſue may moſt happily &amp; proſperouſly reign &amp; rule ouer vs, while the Sun &amp; Moon endure, to his moſt gracious protection I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend your Maieſtie now and euer. From Bletchley in Buckinghamſhire. <hi>1607.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties faithfull and humble ſubiect.</hi> Thomas Sparke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2585:4"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Chriſtian <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant (welbeloued in the Lord) that I haue and doe vndergoe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready the hard cenſure of many for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming my ſelfe as I haue to the orders of our Church, and that I am like to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure harder for the writing and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Treatiſe following, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade others ſo to doe likewiſe. And all this the rather, for that eyther through ignorance what my iudgement in former times hath beene of theſe matters now in queſtion, or miſconſtruction of ſome of my former actions, many as it ſeemeth (haue conceiued) that heretofore I haue not beene the ſame man, that now in this my dealing I mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt my ſelfe to be. To ſatisfie therefore all men (if it may be) in this reſpect; firſt they are to vnderſtand that though there be now, vpon occaſion of the manner of this new vrging the rites and ordinances of our Church as they are, ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in outward ſhew, betwixt my former courſes, and this which I now take, that yet that prooues not (circumſtances duely conſidered) any alteration of my minde or iudgement at all touching theſe things: For I alwaies before, as occaſion ſerued me, both in Pulpit, and otherwiſe in priuate conference with many, manifeſted my ſelfe to be of that opinion, that I alwaies thought they were rather to be yealded vnto, being but of the nature they are, and being vrged no otherwiſe then
<pb facs="tcp:2585:5"/>in deed and truth they be, by our Church, then that any mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhould for his refuſing conformity therunto, ſuffer himſelf to be put from the vſe of his gifts, place and miniſtery, for ſuch a neceſſity is laid vpon vs that be in the miniſtery, (I alwaies knew and remembred) to preach the Goſpell, that woe is to vs if we do not ſo: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. And with <hi>Archippus</hi> I euer vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that <hi>Paule</hi> had ſaid to euery one of vs, take heed to thy miniſtery that thou haſt receiued in the Lord, that thou fulfill it. <hi>Coll.</hi> 4.17. And therfore I could neuer think (and ſo my vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſaying hath been alwaies to my friends and felow miniſters talking with me of theſe things) that at the laſt day it would or could be taken for a ſufficient excuſe or reaſon in any of vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the great Iudge of quick &amp; dead, and the chiefe Biſhop of our ſoules, of and for our ſurceaſing therefrom, to ſay and plead we could not be ſuffered to continue and to go on therin vnleſſe we conformed our ſelues in theſe thinges, as this our Church requireth now at our hands. And therefore alſo how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer otherwiſe weake brethren were not wilfully and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly in ſuch things to be offended by vs, yet if after ſo many yeares inſtruction, they would be ſo weake ſtill, as that they would rather wiſh vs to leaue our miniſtery, what miſchiefe or inconuenience ſoeuer therby ſhould grow, eyther to them, or to our ſelues and ours, and to the whole Church by our ſo doing, then to yeald to the vſe of theſe things, I could neuer yet perſwade my ſelfe that we were bound, to preuent the not offending of ſuch, by ſuffering our ſelues to be run vpon theſe ſo daungerous rocks. But indeed I alwaies rather thought, that that was to redeeme the not offending of them in ſuch things, at a farre higher and coſtlier rate and price, then eyther wee were bound to giue for it, or it were worth: and therefore that in this caſe, the onely thing that remained for vs to doe, was, holding on ſtill our miniſtery, better to inſtruct them, and to
<pb facs="tcp:2585:5"/>pray for them that God would make them wiſer and ſtronger, and ſo to leaue them to him. And the rather haue I beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in this my opinion, becauſe I plainly find, that Maiſter <hi>Cartwright</hi> himſelfe (as deſirous as he was otherwiſe, that they that are in authoritie would haue rather beene pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue ſundrie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) was yet in this caſe of the very ſame iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as any man may ſee he was in his seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part of his seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d reply, chap. the laſt. Then ſecondly, though when I haue beene called by lawfull authoritie to ſome conference about theſe matters (as ſometimes I haue beene; and by the ſame had leaue then freely to ſay my mind touching theſe things) I haue not refuſed in dutifull manner to lay downe my reaſons, why they that were in authoritie (hauing queſtionleſſe thereby power as well to remooue or alter ſuch rites and ceremonies, as to continue them, as that plainely is confeſt they haue, both in our Common Booke it ſelfe, and in the booke of Articles) might well be pleaſed, for the better encouraging of many, both to enter into the miniſterie, and the quieter to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue therein, as alſo thereby the ſooner to breed peace, vnitie and loue amongſt our ſelues, and to remooue offence from the weake and tender conſciences of many, to vſe their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authoritie, rather to remooue, or alter certaine of them, then to continue and vrge them as they were: yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen then alſo (as it is well knowne, as occaſion was offered) I sundrie times plainely proteſted, that for my owne part, thoſe reaſons notwithſtanding, I thought it not fitt, if authoritie would not yeelde therefore ſo to do, but for other reaſons ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of more force thereunto, ſhould chuſe rather to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and ſo to vrge them ſtill, that any man therefore eyther ſhould ſhunne the miniſterie, or ſuffer himſelfe to be depriued thereof. For I neuer thought them, but waied and vnderſtood as they are with vs, eyther of themſelues ſimply vnlawfull,
<pb facs="tcp:2585:6"/>or any way ſo inconuenient, that any ſhould therefore runne vpon eyther of theſe rocks. Much more therefore I haue won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at thoſe men, and greatly alwaies in my minde haue I miſliked them, who for things of no other nature then theſe (about which our domeſticall controuerſies haue beene) haue yet euen therefore growne vnto ſuch a miſlike of the ſtate of our Church, as that they both in pulpit and print, haue thought they might, not onely moſt bitterly ſeeke the diſgrace both of it, and the gouernours thereof, but alſo make (as they haue too to many of them) a plaine and open ſchiſme therin, yea and an vtter rent &amp; breach therfrom. And (I praiſe God for it) the feare thereof from the beginning, and the falling of it out ſo when it did, together with the ſerious conſideration of the nature of the queſtions themſelues, haue ſo alwaies kept me in loue and liking of the preſent gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the orders thereof, that hitherto euer peaceably and quietly, I haue liued vnder, and in the practiſe thereof, and neuer yet could be brought (how well ſoeuer I haue liked of ſome that haue ſeemed zealous &amp; forward in wiſhing as they counted it, reformation of and in certaine things, for their painfulneſſe in their places, and fruitfulneſſe of their labours otherwiſe in their miniſtery) eyther to be preſent at any of their meetings and conſultations to that end, or to yeald them my hand at any time, to any thing concluded therein by them: yea alwaies as I haue ſaid, I haue not onely miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, (to the diſturbance and diſquiet of ſo famous a Church of Chriſt as this of ours is) all thoſe their exceptions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it notwithſtanding, that any ſhould ſeeke eyther in Pulpit or Print, to deface it and diſgrace it, as I ſawe too many did: but alſo what credite ſoeuer at any time God hath giuen mee with any, eſpecially of any great place, I haue vſed it to the beſt of my skill, and credite with them,
<pb facs="tcp:2585:6"/>to breede and to nouriſh in them a good liking of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church-gouernment, and ſo in time and place to bee as they might, Patrons for it, rather then any way to ſuffer themſelues to bee drawne to ioyne with them that ſought the ſubuerſion thereof, and to bring in an other. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that thirdly I may with a ſafe and good conſcience both before GOD and man proteſte, that I neuer yet coulde bee brought by any thing that I haue euer heard or read to that purpoſe theſe foure and thirtie yeares that I haue beene in the Miniſterie (and yet I thinke I haue read moſt, if not all that hath beene ſince written to that ende) eyther to thinke that forme and plott of Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement ſo much admired and magnifyed as the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and onely fit gouernement for Chriſtes Church by a paritie of Miniſters and their Presbiteries, eyther fitting for ſuch a Monarchye as this is, or any way in deede ſo aunſwerable or conformable to the perpetuall gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vſed by GOD for and in his Church, eyther ſince <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Chriſt,</hi> during the Storie, eyther of Newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Olde, as this by <hi>Archbiſhopps, Biſhoppes,</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors</hi> of ours is. And heereupon it hath beene, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great part of my time Biſhoppe <hi>Coopers</hi> Chaplaine, to my good liking, and contentment, I haue not onely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies euer ſince I was Miniſter, liued as an ordinarie Paſtour, euer alſo diſcharging the office of ſuch an one, in my own perſon, in and vnder this gouernment, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at any time once, eyther preſented or conuented, for the omiſſion or tranſgreſſion of any of the orders there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; but alſo for ſundrie yeares was I by the ſaid Biſhoppes gifte Archdeacon of <hi>Stow</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> and ſo had beene ſtill, but that it was ſo farre from mee, that I found I coulde not do that good therein that otherwiſe I
<pb facs="tcp:2585:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>might, and in conſcience tooke my ſelfe bound to haue done. Likewiſe hence it hath beene, that neuer to this day was I ſo much as made priuie too, or acquainted with any petition or ſupplication exhibited to Prince, Parliament, or Conuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation tending to any alteration of this preſent gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And laſtly, certaine it is, that I neuer miniſtred the Communion but I receiued it kneeling, and as for the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſſe I haue long agoe, and verie often worne it, neyther e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer refuſed I the wearing of it, where or when I had one to weare, and when it was eyther by my people, or by the Ordinarie of the place required at my hands, or when I my ſelfe ſaw the vſe of it would open vnto me any wider doore, or procure me any more opportunitie to doe good with any: and when I leaſt vſed it, yet euen then alſo I had a care, when my Text gaue mee any occaſion, ſo to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint my people with the doctrine of Chriſtian liberty, and to teach them the free vſe of ſuch indifferent things, that it ſhould not any way be iuſtly offenſiue to any of them, when at any time for order ſake, vpon occaſion they ſhould ſee mee moſt formally vſe them. And touching ſubſcription if I would or ſhould denie it, ſure I am the Biſhoppe of <hi>Lincolnes</hi> recordes would prooue it, that twice or thrice I haue heretofore vpon occaſion ſubſcribed, in effect euen as now it is required. Finally, I muſt needes ſay (whatſoeuer other men haue fancied of mee) though with <hi>Bucer</hi> in his opinion giuen of our Common Booke, I haue thought certayne things therein ſo ſet downe, as that <hi>Niſi candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de intelligantur,</hi> that is, vnleſſe they bee fauourably vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, they ſeeme to carrie ſome ſhew of contrarietie to the word of God, yet in verie deede, I neuer thought any thing therein, or within the compaſſe of the required ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription ſuch, but that the ſame by ſuch a charitable and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable
<pb facs="tcp:2585:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſtruction, and that alſo but well ſtanding with the profeſſed, and publikely eſtabliſhed doctrine of our Church, and with the beſt and true meaning of the Bookes themſelues whence the obiections to the contrarie did ſeeme to ariſe, might with a good conſcience for the peace and good of the Church be quietly yealded vnto. And in that beſt ſenſe, as I knew charitie did binde vs all to take euery thing, ſo I coulde neuer be perſwaded, but that with a very good liking, and allowance of the ſtate, wee freely might. And therefore that is all that euer I deſired, if to them that were in authoritie, in peaceable manner by conference with or before them, when it ſhould or did pleaſe themſelues to call or admit men thereunto, it could not be perſwaded, for the reaſons and reſpects aforeſaid, that it were beſt to alter thoſe things, whereupon ſome tooke occaſion to ſhunne the miniſterie or to leaue it, that otherwiſe were likely to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for their gifts therein, that yet they would be pleaſed, (as by law alreadie eſtabliſhed I know they might) to allow euery thing within any of the bookes whereunto that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription reacheth, to be conſtrued and taken of euery one, in the beſt ſenſe they could, &amp; for the better and more certaine direction thereunto, to publiſh the ſame as therby allowed ſo to be taken. And ſo to conclude my iudgement alwaies hath beene and is of this preſent Church gouernment, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thereof, if they that be in place of gouernment therein, euery one of them would do but that good in his place, which by the lawes thereof alreadie made he both might an ought, it would be ſo happie and bleſſed euery way as none ſhould iuſtly haue cauſe eyther to complaine of the old, or to ſeek to bring in a new. And before the laſt conference before his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> it is well knowne in the countrey where I dwell, that in a publike meeting of the miniſters
<pb facs="tcp:2585:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>before the commiſſarie and many miniſters, vpon occaſion there giuen mee, I made it publikely knowne that I was, and euer had beene of this iudgement that I haue ſaid, and therefore then further I ſhewe (as elſewhere ſundrie times before others of greater place, and namely to my owne Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan alſo, before the ſaid conference had) how vnwilling I was, eyther there, or elſewhere, to be drawne to ſtand in any oppoſition or contention with the reuerend fathers, about any of theſe matters: For my iudgement is that neuer that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but dutifull ioyning with them is likely any way to be the meanes to procure the Churches good. Being therfore thus perſwaded, and therefore ſo thinking of the lawfulneſſe of my owne courſe, as alſo taking the inconueniences of the other to bee ſo many and great ſundrie waies as I doe, (the times now alſo conſidered wherein wee liue) how can I but in Chriſtian charitie, in this manner doe the beſt that I can, both thus to make my minde knowne in theſe things, and alſo by this inſuing Treatiſe, to ſeeke to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade others to be like minded as I am, and for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons therein ſet downe to yealde to doe as I doe. The beſt and moſt fauourable conſtruction therein, I haue giuen of the things that men vſe to ſticke at, and yet with all I truſt I haue made it appeare that the ſame ſtands verie well with the true meaning of the books themſelues whence the doubts ariſe, and with the publikely receiued doctrine of this our Church: This Treatiſe therefore being ſeene and allowed thus to be printed and publiſhed according to the order in that caſe prouided, may the rather I hope draw men to vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie and conformitie, for that euen thereby they may ſee, that thus both in their practiſe and ſubſcription, they are by publicke and ſufficient authoritie allowed, to take and conſtrue euerie thing in the beſt ſenſe that may bee.
<pb facs="tcp:2585:8"/>And the rather that it might ſo doe, (becauſe amongeſt bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren I thought that the likelieſt way to perſwade) I haue ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died to deliuer my mind in as louing &amp; brotherly a phraſe and manner as I could. Wherefore hoping that all reaſonable men herewith will be ſatisfied, and ſo be content and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling without any preiudice from my perſon, to read and conſider what I haue ſet downe in this Treatiſe following, I bid thee Chriſtian Reader hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily farewell in the Lord. 1606.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing brother vnfainedly, <hi>Thomas Sparke.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2585:9"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Treatiſe <hi>following.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 1.</hi> The preamble or preface thereunto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> The ſum and diuiſion of the whole.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> The mayne propoſition of the whole, and ſeuen groundes thereof.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Of kneeling in the receit of the Communion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> Of conformitie in apparrell, and namely touching the ſurpleſſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> Of the vſe of the ſigne of the croſſe in baptiſme, in general</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Anſwers to obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt the ſame, ſome old, ſome new.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> Anſwers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning ſome men ſpecially touching theſe rites</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> Of the order and practiſe of the book in reading the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Canonicall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> Touching the reading as the booke appointes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> Concerning the interrogatories in Baptiſme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> Anſwers touching diuers other obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt the booke</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> Touching ſubſcription: and certaine obiections againſt the ſame.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> Anſwers to more obiections made againſt the ſame.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> Anſwers to certaine obiections againſt the booke of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 16.</hi> The concluſion, and an exhortation to vnitie.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2585:9"/>
            <head>A PERSVVASION TO VNIFORMITIE VN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Chriſtian brethren: </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Preamble, Chap.</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough I muſt needs confeſſe (well beloued) that none that with any diligence haue read the Eccleſiaſticall ſtories, and the monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the ancient councels and fathers, but that therein they muſt needs ſee and find, that alwayes there haue bene diuerſities of opinions in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, euen in the beſt times ſinſe the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and that amongſt the beſt and moſt famous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians otherwiſe, eſpecially about the outward orders and cuſtomes of the Church: yet no ſmall griefe hath it bene vnto me, to ſee and behold now for theſe 34. yeares (that I haue bene in the miniſterie) the originall, growth, and continuance, of theſe our domeſticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies amongſt our ſelues, about the outward policie and rites of our Church. For whiles men haue ſpent their times and zeale in the purſuit thereof, as of both ſides they haue very much, ſo much time, leaſure and oportunitie hath <hi>Sathan</hi> got, to ſow and water his tares of <hi>Atheiſme, Papiſme,</hi> and of ſects and ſchiſmes amongſt vs. Inſomuch that the ſight and conſideration therereof, hath often made me to thinke and ſay, as occaſion hath ſerued me, to men of both ſides, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did to the Iſraelits, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2. <hi>Why ſmitest thou thy fellow, being thy brother:</hi> and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſayd to the Galathians: <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. <hi>If ye thus bite one another, take heed, yee be not conſumed one of another.</hi> For alwayes it hath bene, and ſtill is my opinion in ſuch caſes: <hi>Conferant fratres, ſed non contendant:</hi> for doubtleſſe in ſuch matters as theſe eſpecially, S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath told vs, <hi>if any liſt to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tious that we haue no ſuch cuſtome, nor the Church of God,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2585:10"/>Foreſeeing yet what further inconuenience might grow of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies in the end, if it were not in time preuented, I haue long and much wiſhed and prayed, that God would raiſe vs ſome one, that both for authoritie, skill and will, were fit to be a moderator therein, and ſo an effectuall compoſer thereof. Wherein (his name be bleſſed for it) at the laſt he hath graunted that my deſire, in ſending vs him to be our ſoueraigne Lord and king whom he hath, who accordingly vpon his firſt entrance into this his kingdome, moſt religiouſly, and chriſtianly hath ſought by a ſolemn conference to end and determine the ſame, by letting both parties therein ſee, wherein they had gone too farre, &amp; what was the <hi>Medium</hi> in which they were both to meete and agree. Wherein his Maieſtie ſo caried himſelf, that verily I thinke I may boldly ſpeake it in the name of all that were then preſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, that neuer any of his place before, in ſuch varietie of queſtions and matters, ſhewed himſelfe more worthie of admiration and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe of all, either for his indifferency in deciding, or for his iudicious kind of examining of euerie thing that then came in queſtion. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that without all doubt, if once whatſoeuer then and there, his Maieſtie reſolued of might take effect, and accordingly be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution (witneſſe but the report of the ſayd conference alreadie with allowance publiſhed in print) great hope there would be, that the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie that thereby his Highneſſe aimed at, would quickly be attained and happily continued. For euen thereby it appeares, that an vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall learned and preaching Miniſtery through his dominions, and that alſo by all good meanes prouiſion ſhould be made for the ſame as ſoone as might be, was then yeelded to be fit and verie neceſſarie: <hi>Pag.</hi> 52. 96. The careleſneſſe and negligence of ſundrie miniſters in this Church alſo was therein by his Maieſtie inueyed againſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: <hi>Pag.</hi> 52. And that ſtricter order ſhould be taken for the due ſanctifying of the <hi>Sabaoth,</hi> was then vniuerſally approued: <hi>Pag.</hi> 45. Likewiſe how and by whom hereafter the cenſures of the Church might be euerie way and in all Eccleſiaſticall courts, moſt fruitfully and ſincerly adminiſtred, then and there was ſo reſolued of, as that if accordingly there be proceeding therein, we ſhall all therefore haue great cauſe to reioyce: <hi>Pag.</hi> 19. 78. 89. 94. And for the better main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the puritie of religion amongſts vs, then and there by his Highneſſe order was taken (which ſince moſt carefully and religiouſly his Maieſtie hath cauſed to be gone about) that as pure and perfect a tranſlation ſhould be made of all the ſcriptures as may be, &amp; that then
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2585:10"/>that onely (both to the ending of all quarrels touching tranſlations, as much as poſſible might be, both amongſt our ſelues, and alſo with our aduerſaries) ſhould after be publiquely vſed in our Churches. <hi>Page.</hi> 46. Then alſo it was to the ſame end agreed that our <hi>Catechiſme</hi> ſhould be perfected: <hi>Page.</hi> 43. which ſince thereupon as we ſee hath beene enlarged &amp; amended. Thirdly to that end likewiſe it was yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto, that there ſhould bee a ſtraiter reſtraint, for the ſelling of Papiſts bookes then before had beene <hi>Page.</hi> 49. And laſtly then alſo it was graunted, that the words in the ſixteenth Article of the booke of articles touching falling from grace of regeneration, ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned, by addition of ſome ſuch words, as wherby plainly it might appeare, that it taught not, that the regenerate and iuſtified either to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally or finally fall at any time from the ſame. <hi>Page.</hi> 30. 41. Further concerning the communion booke, to make the vſe and ſubſcription thereunto the eaſier to be yeelded vnto, it was by his <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> with the aſſent of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> concluded, that to the title of abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold be added (for the better explanation of the meaning thereof) theſe words or remiſſion of ſins. <hi>Page.</hi> 13. And that to the title of confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be annexed theſe, laying on of hands vpon children bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, and able to render an accompt of their faith according to the <hi>Catechiſme</hi> following. <hi>Page.</hi> 36. And that the <hi>Rubricks</hi> touching pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate babtiſme ſhould be ſo altered, as that thereby it might be eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the booke in no caſe of neceſſity, allowes any but a lawfull miniſter to baptiſe any childe. <hi>Page.</hi> 19. 86. And that thoſe words his diſciples ſhold twice be left out in the Goſpells <hi>Page.</hi> 63. al which we ſee in our new communion bookes don. And then alſo certainly (as it is plainly ſet downe. <hi>Page.</hi> 61, of the ſaid booke of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) his <hi>Maieſties</hi> order was, that none of the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> ſhould bee read at all, wherein there was any error, and therefore his highnes willed D <hi>Reynolds</hi> to note thoſe chapters in the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> bookes, wherein ſuch errors were, and to bring the note thereof to the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as it is further teſtified. <hi>Page.</hi> 62. beſides the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; there it was alleadged by the author of the ſaid booke, D <hi>Barlow</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dean of <hi>Cheſter</hi> now Lord B. of Rocheſter when the obiection taken from the reading of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha</hi> was in hand, as a ſufficient anſwere thereunto, and not gainſaid of any that the preface prefixed to the ſecond book of <hi>Homiles</hi> might haue made vs to ſee the needleſneſſe thereof, for that thereby the miniſter is permitted, at his diſcretion for any chapter appointed (by the Communion booke) of the old teſtament to be red, to read a chapter of the new, which he thought more fit, for the edification
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2585:11"/>of his people. And yet his Maieſty moſt wiſely foreſeeing that all theſe notwithſtanding thus amended, it was likely inough that ſome things in the book, or within the compaſſe of the vrged ſubſcription, would ſtill ſeeme vnto ſome ſo harſhly to remaine ſet downe, as that they would ſticke and ſtay thereat, his Highneſſe moſt graciouſly ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vnto vs, that as it was our duties, ſo he wiſhed euery one of vs, to conſtrue and take euerything in the beſt ſenſe that we could, and not in the hardeſt and worſt: for ſo only his intent and pleaſure was, that they ſhould be vrged. And ſo much in the foreſayd booke of Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence alſo to this end is remembred, as that <hi>Pag.</hi> 47. it is ſet downe, that his maieſtie would haue things indifferent, rather interpreted and helpt by a gloſe, then altered. All which things conſidered, if we could and would once learne to bend our wits as well to make the beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of euerie thing hereafter, as ſome haue heretofore, to make the worſt, both the practiſe of the book, &amp; the ſubſcription therunto, and to the reſt, would now be doubtleſſe far eaſier then heretofore it hath, or yet is, vnto many. Indeed the rites &amp; ceremonies preſcribed by that booke, by no meanes would either his Maieſtie or the <hi>Biſhops</hi> be drawne to alter, howſoeuer it was agreed and then conſented vnto, that where they had in certaine places beene long diſuſed, and the men there, otherwiſe were found peaceable, painfull, &amp; fruitfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, a conuenient time ſhould be graunted them (which ſince accordingly hath beene) both to ſatisfie themſelues and their people in that time, for the vſing of them againe. And certainly his Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties anſweres to the reaſons that were then vſed to haue perſwaded him to remoue them (which in effect were all that either before or ſince by any haue beene vrged to that purpoſe) were ſuch, as alſo his owne reaſons for the continuance thereof (being no otherwiſe vrged then they are) as that I am fully perſwaded what his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth therein, he doth it with an vpright and good conſcience in the Lord. For his Highneſſe anſweres to the ſaid obiections, I muſt needs confeſſe, then ſeemed vnto me not onely very apt, acute and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, but alſo euen now in this treatiſe, moſt of the ground of all my anſweres to the ſame obiections, or the like, growes thence. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (as I remember) vrged by his <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> for his reſolution of their continuance, were theſe: that he found them here eſtabliſhed by ſuch a ſtate which the Lord had long and wonderfully bleſt, that being vrged but as they were, they were of that nature of things, wherein both he lawfully might commaund, and wee alſo were bound wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2585:11"/>to obey, and that change vnleſſe very neceſſary, did (as <hi>Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> ſaith <hi>Epiſt:</hi> 118) more hurt by the nouelty, then otherwiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit: and that they were vſed by the primatiue and pureſt churches, &amp; in the ages next the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and that by holy fathers and renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med chriſtians, before popery began, and ſo euer ſince haue beene continued, and that therefore he would not giue the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> that aduantage, as by his now reiecting of them, to ſay that we were ſo giuen to nouelty, as that no auncient thing could pleaſe vs, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid he, by our retaining ſtil of them, they ſhould wel vnderſtand, that neither in doctrine, rite nor ceremonie, we deſpiſe true antiquitie and that indeed, they are they that in both theſe do ſo, and not wee. And doubtleſſe it was euident that all that pains then his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> tooke to knit vs altogether in vnitie, that ſo being ioyned together in one, in vniformity of Iudgment and practiſe in theſe things, as wee were otherwiſe in doctrine, we might all more ſtrongly bend our forces together againſt our common aduerſaries, &amp; he be alſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſtronger to draw them after to conformity of religion with vs. Giue me therfore leaue (good brethren) euen of vnfained loue alſo to you, and of an harty deſire of the peace and good of this our Church, in the beſt manner that I can, by this my brotherly perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to further his Highnes royall and holy deſire herein. Many haue written I confeſſe to this end, both before I writ this and ſince, and that in good ſort, and to very good purpoſe, &amp; yet I truſt there may be alſo good vſe of this of mine, but indeed euen therfore in moſt things I haue beene ſo briefe as I may referring you for the reſt that might haue beene ſaid, to thoſe others in print before this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Containing the ſumme and diuiſion of the whole Treatiſe.</head>
               <p>To enter therefore hereinto, though I muſt needs confeſſe, that ſo farre to iuſtifie by ſubſcription as it is vrged, as we are content by our practiſe to allow, or at the leaſt to tollerate, ſeemeth vnto me in effect all one: yet I cannot deny, but that there is great difference betwixt a miniſters yealding onely ſo farre forth as concerns him and his miniſtry to conformity, and his yealding vniuerſally and ſimplye to the ſubſcription now vrged. For by the former, he yeelds onely a tolleration, or an allowance at the moſt, for the peace ſake and good of the Church, to ſo much of the booke of Common Prayer,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2585:12"/>as by the rules thereof, he himſelfe is bound to vſe and practiſe and by the other he not onely ſo farre alſo iuſtifies the ſame, but all the reſt thereof, as namely the tract of confirmation, the vſe &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe whereof onely belongs to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as alſo the booke of ordination the execution whereof appertains likewiſe onely to them, and the reading of <hi>Homilies</hi> then publiſhed and authoriſed, or to be then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter publiſhed and authoriſed, which long ſince (as I take it) ſo haue bene in the ſecond volume of homilies 1563 which being a preacher and preaching alwaies when they ſhould be read, by the order of the booke it ſelfe, he needs neuer do. As for the reſt within the compaſſe of the ſaid ſubſcription, namely touching his <hi>Maieſties</hi> ſupremacie, &amp; the Articles concerning faith &amp; the ſacraments, I mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, becauſe without gainſaying all of our religion are willing ſo farre to yeald it, howbeit for aſmuch as he that hath once learned with a good con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience for the Churches good and his owne, to yeald to the former will alſo the eaſilier be brought in the ſame reſpects to yeeld to the other, and he that cannot bee brought to the former, will neuer be drawne to the latter: firſt let vs conſider what may be ſaid to induce men to the former, and then after likewiſe how beſt the obiections that ſtay men from the latter, may be anſwered and remoued in both which becauſe I haue to deale with men of wiſedome and learning I will ſtudy to be as briefe as I may.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Conſiſting of the maine propoſition of the whole and of ſeauen grounds of the diſcourſe following.</head>
               <p>That we are bound to yeeld the former, the ſtatute made <hi>Eliza</hi> i: firſt to authoriſe the booke &amp; the vniforme practiſe &amp; vſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſince his <hi>Maieſties</hi> proclamation publiſhed therewith as it is now, to ratefie the ſame, and the Canons aucthoriſed by his high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes as they are in my opinion, make it ſo cleare and euident, that wee can iuſtly make no doubt thereof. All the queſtion therefore I would thinke now is, whether being thus by lawfull acthority commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the nature of the things within the compaſſe of the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the maner of the vrging thereof conſidered, we be bound or no, to yeeld quietly our obedience therunto, wherin my opinion is were not the law that requires this at our hands ſo penall as it is, yet but commaunding it (the things commaunded, being neither in their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2585:12"/>owne nature, either againſt faith or good manners, and therefore but things indifferent, nor yet in the vſe as they are vrged otherwiſe, by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon rules of the word in that caſe ſet downe, touching the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the inferiour, to the ſuperior. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1. &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, &amp;c. wee were quietly and willingly (euen to diſcharge our duety &amp; conſcience towards ſuch, in reſpect of thoſe rules, for our owne good and the Churches, and to maintaine good order &amp; peace in the ſame) to yeeld our obedience &amp; conformity thereunto: yea further ſeemed there to bee ſome inconuenience, and vnexpediency in ſome of the things commaunded, yet being by ſuch lawfull authority, and vnder ſuch penalty vrged as they are, ſo long as by any right and charitable conſtruction of our Churches, and her gouernours intent &amp; meaning therein, they may be ſo taken, as that there is nothing in the word of God ſet downe in the canonicall ſcriptures contrary thereunto, in my poore iudgment, it is the duety of euery modeſt and chriſtian Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to yeeld rather his conformity thereunto, then (hee cannot tell how much to the wrong and preiudice of the Church, himſelfe, and his, vnto all which he ſtands ſo ſtrictly bound as he doth) for his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuering ſtill and refuſing ſo to doe, to ſuffer himſelfe by his ordinary, either to be kept from entring into the miniſtry, or to be depriued of place or miniſtry. Now yet before I can come to anſwere the obiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions againſt this required obedience and conformity, by your gentle patience, let vs a little conſider of a few neceſſary grounds (I hope co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed of vs all) which notwithſtanding duly weyed, may well ſerue, not onely to confirme theſe points, but alſo to open a way to anſwer all that is or can be obiected againſt the ſame.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Firſt therefore (good brethren) I truſt wee all are reſolued, that things neither for their nature, nor vſe commaunded nor forbid by the word of God in the canonicall ſcriptures of the old or new te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, expreſly or by any ſound deduction from thence, are &amp; may lawfully be held for things indifferent. Of this mind I am ſure <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſhewes him ſelfe to haue beene <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118. and <hi>Epiſt</hi> 86 <hi>ad Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanum,</hi> and ſo it is noted in the <hi>Heluetian</hi> confeſſion <hi>Sect.</hi> 17. of the harmony of the confeſſions of the reformed Churches: that <hi>Hierom</hi> writing to <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was alſo of the ſame iudgement: the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appeares moſt flatly to haue beene <hi>Ambroſe</hi> opinion in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> And indeed in all ages, all learned writers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt chriſtians, for any thing that euer I could read to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (and yet for this cauſe I may truly ſay I haue taken ſome paines to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2585:13"/>read and ſearch as many of them as I could come by) are fully with vs in this point.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Now next we know that though chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liberty eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in our freedom from the curſe of the Law, from ſin, &amp; from the wrath of god for the ſame, &amp; in our freedom from the ſeruice of ſin, &amp; from the rites &amp; iudicialls of <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being tyed in all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealths &amp; churches, to the preciſe followng either of one outward ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill policy, or of one &amp; ſelfe ſame forme of rites &amp; ceremonies eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall, yet one parte therof lyeth vndoubtedly alſo, in our freedom &amp; liberty in &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning things indifferent. For of theſe things the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> ſpoke, ſaying I know &amp; am perſwaded, thorough the Lord Ieſus, that there is nothing vncleane of it ſelfe, but to him that iudgeth any thing to be vnclean, to him it is vnclean. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.14, &amp; againe vnto the pure all things are pure. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. And all things are lawfull for mee, though all things are not expedient. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.23. And therefore in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſuch things, it was no ſmall part of his glory as he ſhewes. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19. &amp;c. to become all vnto all, ſo to win the more.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly therefore wee may not deny the chriſtian ſupreme magiſtrate, who by Gods ordinance is to be <hi>Eſai.</hi> 49.23 as a nurſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto his churches vnder him, nor to the Biſhops and others of the Clergy by his authority lawfully aſſembled in a nationall Synod, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in ſuch matters as theſe, for the more orderly gouernment of the Church in their iudgments, to preſcribe ordinances: alwaies prouided that the rites &amp; ceremonies that thereby they impoſe vpon the Churches, be not contrary, but rather conſonant to the generall rules left them in the word, to direct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therein. For elſe to what pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe hath the Apoſtle left that generall rule in this caſe to al churches to the worlds end? 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. Let all things be done honeſtly &amp; by order, this therefore as their very due and right, is with one conſent yeelded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the foreſaid 17 ſection of the harmony of the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; <hi>Caluin</hi> vpon the 11 of the firſt to the <hi>Corinth.</hi> &amp; <hi>Beza</hi> in his 8 e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle (as indeed generally alwaies the learned of all ages &amp; the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall practiſe of Chriſts church alſo haue done) graunt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame: Indeed whiles as yet conſultation is but by them held, what ſhall in this kind be ordayned or continued, or what ſhall not. I find that law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully (ſo it be done orderly &amp; in quiet ſort) they that haue lawful cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereunto, may ſhew the beſt reaſons they can, to direct them therein, to determine &amp; conclude for the beſt: but when once vpon mature deliberation, the concluſion is made &amp; publiſhed howſoeuer
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2585:13"/>then we may not deny the reſt of the church that fredome &amp; liberty, becauſe of thoſe generall rules giuen all chriſtians, try all things, and keepe that which is good. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.21. &amp; try the ſpirits whether they are of god or no, 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.1. to examine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſions by the word, yet doubtles in things of this nature &amp; kind, all muſt alſo remember, that <hi>Paul</hi> hath giuen rule, that neither the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> nor the churches of God, haue any cuſtome to warrant any to be contentious. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. In caſe therefore any conſtitutions at any time by chriſtian Princes, and there nationall Synods in ſuch matters, ſhall chance to be made, which ſome priuate man or men examining by the word of God, are thereby able to proue the ſame to be contrary thereunto (which I cannot deny but may bee poſſible, for the trueth is, as our Church very ſoundly holdeth. <hi>Artic.</hi> 21. generall counſels may erre, &amp; ſometimes haue erred, euen in things appertaining vnto God) yet ſuch are then, but in all peaceable and in dutifull manner, to make knowne thoſe their reaſons, for which they ſo thinke thereof to thoſe that are in authority, &amp; no way otherwiſe by preſſe or in pulpit, to ſeek to trouble or to deface, either the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or the church, in other reſpects co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable, for matters of no greater moment then an aberration or twoe can be, touching the outward orders only therof; ſo leauing in patience the ſucceſſe thereof to God, &amp; to more mature co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration in the next Synod, for ſo much I thinke the foreſaid rule of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> binds vs vnto, and certain it is, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teaches in his ſecond booke againſt <hi>Parmenian, Toleranda quaedam ſunt, quae non ſunt tamen probanda:</hi> &amp; therefore as he there ſaith <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. as a man of right may <hi>quaedam improbare,</hi> ſo <hi>&amp; firmitate debet quaedam supportare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Our fourth ground &amp; principle therefore is, that the Soueraigne magiſtrate and the church, hauing in things indifferent lawfully once enacted their eccleſiaſticall orders, and conſtitutions, howſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore therein men might vſe their freedome and liberty to vſe or not to vſe them, as charity in not offending their weake brother there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by would beſt permit them, all men then are onely ſo to vſe their liberty therein, as that they giue no ſcandale and offence to publike authority, nor ſhew any contempt thereof in wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not conforming them ſelues, according to the order thereby preſcribed therein. For when the councell. <hi>Acts.</hi> 15. had once decreed that the gentiles ſhould abſtaine from things offered to Idolls, ſtrangled, and bloode <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe.</hi> 29, wee reade that <hi>Paule</hi> &amp; <hi>Silas: Acts.</hi> 16. gaue the Churches of the gentiles the ſame to obſerue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2585:14"/>and keepe after, as they trauelled. And hee him ſelfe hauing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and further preſcribing certaine ordinances touching ſuch matters to the <hi>Corinthians. Chap.</hi> 11. commends them for obſeruing them <hi>verſe.</hi> 2. and condemns thoſe that contentiouſly refuſed ſo to do <hi>verſe.</hi> 16. The frequent and vſuall practiſe of the Church, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare both in all eccleſiaſticall ſtories, and in the decrees of auncient famous councels, both in making of canons touching ſuch matters, and in obaying the ſame pregnantly proue, that this is an auncient receiued truth. Yea euen thereby, for the further proofe hereof, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that it hath beene an vſuall thing in the Churches of Chriſt, aſwell to cenſure them for Schiſmaticks, who for a rite or ceremony, not vnlawfull in it ſelfe, neither for nature nor vſe, would make a rent therein, to the breach and diſturbance of the communion &amp; fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thereof, as thoſe for heritikes, that would ſet abroach and wilfully defend errors in doctrine of faith or manners, to the diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eting and infecting of the ſame. And truly not without iuſt cauſe hath it thus done, for as <hi>Caluin</hi> writes <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt. Cap.</hi> 10. <hi>Sect.</hi> 31. what a ſeed of braules and confuſion of things would that bee, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one might be ſuffered, as he liſt to alter things appointed by pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lique order. The conſideration whereof, as <hi>Beza</hi> to his commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on notes in his diſcourſe of his life, cauſed him to ſubmit himſelfe to the order of <hi>Geneua</hi> touching their communion bread, when hee was admitted thither againe, though he then diſſembled not, that he liked other bread better.</p>
               <p n="5">5 But then fiftly we are to take this with vs, that then rites and ceremonies by publique authority commaunded are ſuch, as thus we are bound (though not in reſpect of the things themſelues in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, yet in regard of gods ordinance ſet downe in his word in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, to binde vs in all things not contrary to his reuealed will in the ſcriptures, to obey our ſuperiors) to yeeld vnto, when not onely in their owne nature they are things neither commaunded nor forbid by the word, as is aforeſaid, but alſo are neither for multitude nor coſt too burthenſome to the Church nor are ſuch in reſpect of the vſe wherein they are vrged, wherein any part or peece of Gods proper and immediate worſhip, outward or inward, or any opinion of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, merit or greater perfection, or neceſſitie to inthrall or inſnare the conſcience is lodged: And when they are impoſed as ſuch things ought to be, only for order, decency, and comlineſſe, as mutable &amp; changable vpon iuſt occaſion by like authority, and therefore as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difying
<pb facs="tcp:2585:14"/>onely as ſuch things may, and not iuſtly tending to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of any, for that they are vrged but to the lawful ends laſt named, and <hi>extra caſum ſcandali</hi> and <hi>contemptus,</hi> lay not an Ineuitable neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity vpon the conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the obſeruer. For ſo long neither any thing ſet downe or ment in the ſecond commaundement, nor any elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in the Scriptures againſt adding thereto, or againſt the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiping of God in vaine by the precepts and traditions of men (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſome ſeeme to think otherwiſe) can iuſtly &amp; rightly be drawn againſt ſuch ordinances: for the ſecond commaundement only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes any worſhiping of God, otherwiſe then he hath appointed himſelfe. And ſo likewiſe all the other places againſt additions, and vaine traditions, are onely againſt ſuch wherein any opinion of faith, Gods worſhip, or ſeruice is laid. And the opinion touching the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of the Scriptures, by the godly learned in all ages held and maintained, hath beene and is this, that either expreſly or by right in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, they are ſufficient to determine all truth, concerning faith &amp; gods worſhip neceſſarie to ſaluation: whereas ſtill it hath beene alſo held and yet is, for outward accidentall and changeable rites and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, that the Churches of Chriſt haue libertie to ordaine tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them, as the gouernours thereof ſhall think fitteſt, and ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all, nor alwaies, that they are tyed to one preciſe forme there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Alwaies prouided that in their ordayning the ſame they croſſe not but rather agree as neere as they can as is aforeſaid, to the generall rules left them in the ſame Scriptures, touching the ſame: elſe how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we iuſtifie <hi>Salomons</hi> ſeauen daies feſtiuity at the dedication of the temple 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 8. <hi>Heſters</hi> &amp; <hi>Mardocheus</hi> yearly holy days <hi>Chap.</hi> 9 or of <hi>Iudas Machabaeus</hi> his brethren? <hi>Math.</hi> 4.59 All which yet we allow and all this is ſet downe as one of the points agreed on amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt our ſelues in this Church. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.20 and 34, whereunto none refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe: and <hi>Caluin</hi> vpon the eleuenth of the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> &amp; <hi>Beza</hi> in his foreſaid eight <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> moſt plainly teach the ſame: yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Cartwright</hi> himſelfe, as you may ſee in the 84 Page of the late <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> booke againſt him, confeſſes, that it is not neceſſary that euery rite and ceremony be expreſſed therein, but that it is ſufficient to make the orders of the Church therein lawfull, if they be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the generall rules ſet downe in the Scriptures, concerning ſuch things. They therefore being ſo, if any yet will be offended, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the commaunders or obeyers therein, it is an offence taken, &amp; not giuen, and therefore at their owne perill onely, for both reaſon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2585:15"/>and religion teach, and therefore as an vndoubted truth it is held and alwayes hath bene, and namely of <hi>Caluin,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>Inſtit lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>Sect.</hi> 31.32. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. of the harmonie of the confeſſions: by <hi>August. Epiſt.</hi> 118.119. <hi>&amp;</hi> 86. by <hi>Bucer</hi> to <hi>Alaſco,</hi> by <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to <hi>Hooper,</hi> and by <hi>Bucer</hi> to <hi>Cranmer,</hi> that the Churches of Chriſt haue freedome and libertie according to theſe generall rules to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe orders, rites and ceremonies, and then they hauing ſo done, it is not for priuate men to refuſe, for the maintenance of good order and peace therein, to conforme themſelues thereunto, for that the publicke iudgement of the Church in ſuch matters, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be preferred before the priuate opinion of this man or that, and the Church is not to ſtay from making any conſtitutions in ſuch things, vntill ſhe can be aſſured that all will be pleaſed therewith, for then hardly euer ſhould ſhe make any, and ſo alſo there would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be any end of brawles, iarres, diſcords, and diſſentions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about. He therefore that herein would neither giue offence nor take any, is according to the councell of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in this caſe, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath reported in two of the former places, modeſtly and quietly alwayes to conforme himſelfe according to the order of the Church wherein he liueth.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And yet though hee doe ſo, let not any man thinke, but for all that he may be fully in poſſeſſion of his Chriſtian libertie in ſuch matters, and ſo according to the rule of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> ſtand faſt in that libertie wherewith Chriſt hath made him free, not ſuffering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe any whit to bee entangled againe with the yoke of bondage, <hi>Galathians</hi> 5.1. For we may ſufficiently to that end bee poſſeſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, within our conſciences, though for not offending of a weake brother, much more for not offending the publicke eſtate of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Church, wee neuer outwardly poſſeſſe our ſelues thereof: For the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> that giues vs that rule, and as we haue heard of ſuch things confidently ſayd, that all things were lawfull for him: 1. <hi>Corinthians</hi> 10.23. yet ſayth alſo, if meate did offend his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hee would eate no fleſh whiles the world ſtood, that hee might not offend his brother, 1. <hi>Corinthians</hi> 8.13. For Chriſtian libertie in reſpect of ſuch outward things, lies in our right iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, in that we are alwayes perſwaded that <hi>extra ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ſcandali &amp; contemptus,</hi> both of priuate perſons, and the publicke ſtate wherein wee liue, wee may without ſinne, and hurt to our conſciences vſe our libertie therein. The igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2585:15"/>or forgetfulneſſe but of which point, is the ground and cauſe of manie vnbrotherly quarrels and contentions in the Church, about things of this kind; let vs therefore take this for the ſixt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall point needefull to bee reſolued of, for the better direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelues and others, how to behaue our ſelues in matters of this nature. If any doubt whether <hi>extra caſum ſcandali &amp; contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> one may lawfully without ſin or hurt of conſcience in ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded rites and ceremonies, ſometimes vpon due and iuſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and circumſtances, omit, or intermit the vſing of them, let him conſider that the decree of abſtaining from things offered to idols, ſtrangled, &amp; bloud, mentioned <hi>Act.</hi> 15. notwithſtanding after, the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> in his firſt <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Corinths</hi> (though he vtterly diſalow the breach of that ordinance by any of the church in the idols temple to the offence of any weake brother, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) yet when in reſpect of the circumſtances, there is no ſuch danger of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, <hi>Chap</hi> 10.27. permits them freely to eat thereof, without any ſcruple of conſcience. Neither ought this to ſeeme ſtrange vnto any: for as there is a preciſe keeping of ſuch lawes, and as flat a breaking thereof, ſo is there alſo a middle or meane betwixt both, which is to do <hi>prater legem,</hi> and yet not <hi>contralegem,</hi> becauſe though then the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the law be not ſtrictly obſerued, yet neither the true meaning, nor end of the law is croſſed, by doing otherwiſe then it appoints. Vpon which ground, though the foreſaid decree of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and brethren in the councell of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> was ſet downe, as it appeares there, without limitation of time or place, how long and where it ſhould binde the chriſtian gentiles to the obſeruation therof, yet in due place &amp; time, without ſin or hurt of conſcience, they grew to the diſuſe thereof, and now it is vniuerſally held not to bind at all any, when there is no danger of offence to any weake brother by doing otherwiſe. Wherefore it is to be wiſhed that the Church, and they that are in authoritie therein, would alwayes in the vrging, the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and execution of ſuch their ordinances, not onely haue a care (as queſtionleſſe this of ours hath had) firſt that by all good meanes they whom the obſeruation thereof concernes, might be taught how with a good conſcience they may, and ought to yeeld thereunto (for doubtleſſe the rule of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> whatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. holds not onely of things indifferent left at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, but alſo limited by authoritie, for their vſe one onely way) then alſo that they bee but vrged according to the nature of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2585:16"/>things themſelues, that is, neither as perpetuall and vnchangeable vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon any occaſion, nor as ſimply and abſolutely alwayes to bind the conſcience, as the things commanded by God himſelfe do. Much leſſe would they be vrged more earneſtly then the ordinances and commandements of the Lord himſelfe in his word, leaſt ſo the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes</hi> ſhould iuſtly be incurred, yee tythe mint and anniſſe, and leaue the greater things of the law vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, or ye make the commandements of God of none effect, for the obſeruing of your owne traditions, <hi>Math.</hi> 23.22. and 15.3. for it is all that the verie lawes of God himſelfe do, or can do, ſimply and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely to bind the conſcience, and therefore human lawes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances doubtleſſe bind not ſimply of themſelues, but ſo farre forth onely, as they are made by lawfull authoritie, whereunto the word of God requires ſubiection and obedience, as long as the things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thereby are not contrarie, but rather conſonant to the ſame word of God. Maruellous well therefore ſaith the late <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> in his anſwer to the admonition (as it is to be ſeene <hi>Pag.</hi> 279. of his foreſaid anſwer to <hi>M. Cartwright</hi>) that a chriſtian magiſtrate may ordaine or retaine, any ciuill, politike, or Eccleſieſticall orders and rites, ſo that firſt they be not againſt the word of God, ſecondly, that iuſtification or remiſſion of ſinnes be not attributed vnto them, third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Church be not troubled with the multitude of them, fourthly, that they be not decreed as neceſſarie and not to be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and laſt of all that men be not ſo tied vnto them, but that by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, they may be omitted, ſo that it be without offence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Hereunto I will adde onely one generall rule more, and that is this, the nature of charitie being as it is deſcribed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Certainly where it is indeed, it will make the owner alwayes ſtriue to hope and to iudge the beſt that he can of his priuate neighbours actions and deeds; how much more then ought it to bind all men to conceiue and to conſtrue the beſt of the lawes and orders of the Church of Chriſt wherein they liue? contrarie therefore doubtleſſe it is to Chriſtian charitie (let men therein pretend neuer ſo much zeale) to ſtretch and bend their wits, to make the worſt and hardeſt conſtruction they can of the lawes and ordinances, ſet forth by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full authoritie in the Church whereof they are. Thus queſtionleſſe whiles men do, they giue not vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which is <hi>Caeſars,</hi> as Chriſt hath commanded, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.22. neither do they yeeld vnto
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2585:16"/>their ſuperiours that honour and reuerence, that both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> enioyne all Chriſtians to giue them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by thus doing, they make themſelues like ſuch as <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.10. and <hi>Iude verſ.</hi> 8. deſcribe to be deſpiſers of gouernement, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, ſtanding in their owne conceipts, and fearing not to ſpeake euill of them that are in dignitie. For they cannot but ſee that ſo farre as they by their hard conceipt, and conſtruction diſgrace their lawes and ordinances, ſo farre alſo they deface and diſcredit them that made and vrge them. Remember we therefore that as it is an ancient ſaying, ſo it is alſo in this caſe a verie ſound rule, the words of the lawe may not captiouſly be taken, nor the law it ſelfe ſlandered. For he that in wreſting of the lawes would ſeeme to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, therein vſes to prooue himſelfe commonly to bee no better then a <hi>Sycophant.</hi> Theſe things thus premiſed, and as I hope by vs all yeelded vnto, as certaine truths, I truſt I ſhall be able to iuſtifie as much as I haue ſayd, namely that with a ſafe and good conſcience we may and ought to yeeld conformitie, ſo farre as by publike autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is now required at our hands. Howbeit whiles I go about thìs, vnderſtand, my purpoſe is not to take vpon me particularly and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly to ſeeke to ſatisfie euerie obiection, that I know hath bene or is made, but onely thoſe that I iudge to be moſt materiall, and that alſo as briefly as I can, for that I hope I haue to deale with men of learning and iudgement, who therfore being ſatisfied in the greateſt, will neuer ſticke (I ſhould thinke) at the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of Conformitie, and firſt in kneeling at the receipt of the Communion.</head>
               <p>TO proceed therefore therein, the things of greateſt moment for which I obſerue this vrged conformitie is ſtucke at, are either certaine rites or ceremonies, preſcribed the Cleargie to vſe, by the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice booke or Canons, or certain exceptions made againſt the things thereby appointed in the Churches ſeruice to be read. In the firſt ranke three rites or ceremonies are miſliked, eſpecially kneeling in the receit of the Communion, the preſcribed apparell, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſigne of the croſſe after Baptiſme: Their reaſons of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of the firſt of theſe. I find eſpecially to be three; that it was not vſed by Chriſt, nor his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> at the firſt inſtitution of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2585:17"/>that it came in and firſt was taken vp after the doctrine of reall preſence by tranſubſtantiation, and ſo thereupon adoration of the hoſt crept into the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and now by the Canons it is vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſo ſtrictly, as that neither the miniſter may adminiſter it to any that refuſe to take it kneeling, nor they otherwiſe receiue it without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring the cenſures of the Church. Touching the firſt reaſon, long ago it hath bene ſufficiently anſwered, as you may ſee <hi>Pag.</hi> 596. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the late <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> anſwer to <hi>M. Cartwright,</hi> where hee ſhewes the Authors of the admonition, that were the firſt vrgers of it, that as the Church of Chriſt without any wrong offered to Chriſt, or his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, haue ſince altered the time and the place, and diuerſe other circumſtances in the adminiſtring of this Sacrament, ſo may it alſo the geſture of ſitting, (then vſed for that it was inſtituted after the receit of the paſſeouer, in eating whereof they vſed that geſture) into this of kneeling. And as for the ſecond, it is grounded rather vpon an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, then vpon any ſound ground, for though there I find the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition ſaith it came in by the decree of <hi>Honorius,</hi> yet they quote no author to proue it, which they would not haue failed to do, if they had had any worth the citing: And therfore though they were anſwered by the foreſayd author, that he could find no ſuch decree of <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> for it, yet neither they nor <hi>M. Cartwright</hi> their defender, once ſince go about to proue that euer <hi>Pope Honorius</hi> made any ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree. And there being foure of that name <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſome of them before either tranſubſtantiation or adoration, was heard of in the Church, in fathering ſuch a decree vpon <hi>Honorius</hi> without any adition or proofe, argues the weakneſſe and vncertaintie of their eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. But howſoeuer the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſince theſe groſſe and idolatrous conceits of theirs touching this ſacrament came in, haue vſed it ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly in adoring their hoſt in the eleuation thereof, I cannot find neither in their maſſe booke, or any where elſe, that either Prieſt or people with them, were bound to receiue it kneeling: and we by our publike doctrine hauing abandoned that eleuation and adoration of theirs as we haue, we vſe it onely as in the foreſayd place the ſayd <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> ſhewes to no ſuch end, but for that we thinke it a fit and ſeemely geſture, the Sacrament being as it is a Sacrament of thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, and it being alſo by the order of our Church alwayes deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and receiued with prayer, wherein that geſture is very come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and for that we know that now amongſt vs, there is as great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, if not more, of too baſe a conceit, and of too much contempt of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2585:17"/>ſo excellent a Sacrament, then of any too high an eſtimation there of. And therefore euen, to preuent that the better is it onely that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ſo earneſtly vrges the vſe of this geſture of kneeling, as alſo by vrging it ſo ſeuerely, to put an ende to the offenſiue diuerſitie (if it were poſſible) in the receiuing of this ſacrament of vnitie, ſome ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſome ſtanding, ſome walking, and but ſome keeeling: for that of all theſe kinds of geſtures (theſe times conſidered) this of kneeling is iudged the fitteſt. For it was wiſely foreſeene that ſuch multiplicitie and varietie of geſtures, tending ſo much as they do, not onely to ſet the people forward in that whereunto they are too for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward alreadie, namely in thinking too too irreuerently of ſo high a myſterie, but alſo to the no ſmall occaſioning of the Papiſts more and more to ſtumble both at our doctrine and doings, would not, nor could not, bee reduced to a needefull vniformitie in this caſe, without ſome moderate ſeueritie vſed to that end. Wherefore other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to gather thereupon, as though thereby our Church now meant to make it abſolutely and ſimply neceſſarie to the complement of this ſacrament, is but directly contrarie to our laſt premiſed rule, to make the worſt conſtruction of the Churches order therein that may be; and therefore thus is their third argument founded vpon ſo bad a ground anſwered alſo. Further yet to breed and continue in vs (for the reaſons aforeſayd) the better liking of the Churches order in this behalfe, none can ſay of this geſture of kneeling, as they ſay of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that it is a meere humane inuention, for we find it often practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with allowance and liking of the Scriptures of the godly in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and thankſgiuing to God, and therefore howſoeuer idolaters haue, or do, and will ſtill abuſe it, in and about their idolatrie, I hope for all that we purging it of all ſuch abuſe, none will deny the vſe thereof to be lawfull, and very fit alſo, for true Chriſtians in hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelues before God in their prayers and thankſgiuing. Sure I am that the conſideration of theſe things hath alwayes ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed with me, that without ſcruple of conſcience, I haue euer vſed it my ſelf in the receipt of the Sacrament: and rather am I incouraged to vſe it ſtill, for that I find that not our Church alone, but the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church of <hi>Boeme,</hi> as it appeares in the harmonie of confeſſions, <hi>Sect.</hi> the 14. alſo alloweth and vſeth it. Let this therefore ſuffice touching this rite, and now let vs go on to conſider what is ſayd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and what may be ſayd for the preſcribed apparell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2585:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Of conformitie in the preſcribed apparell.</head>
               <p>ALl the reſt of the preſcribed apparell ſaue only the Surpliſſe, for vs ordinarie Miniſters, as namely the <hi>Gowne, Cloake, Hood, Cap. and Tippet,</hi> are in all mens eyes rather ciuill, ſcholaſticall, and acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall, then meere Eccleſiaſticall, appointed rather only for a decent diſtinction and degree then otherwiſe; neither are they impoſed by law vpon any ſuch penalty as the Surpliſſe, and therefore they muſt needs be without the reach of moſt, if not of all the obiections made againſt the Surpliſſe: Yea the verie ſurpliſſe alſo, in that it is, by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der now appointed, not to be worne of any miniſter that is a graduat, without his hood anſwerable to his degree, ſo farre forth muſt needs ceaſe to be meere Eccleſiaſticall. Somewhat alſo to the ſame end it is that we ſee in Collegiate and Cathedrall Churches, the wearing of it, is not appropriate to miniſters or deacons only, for that many there weare it, as well as theſe, which neither are ſuch, nor neuer meane to be. And as for the <hi>Coape</hi> appointed by the 24 Canon, by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall miniſter to be worne, when he miniſters the Communion in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiat and Cathedrall churches, we need not here trouble our ſelues at all, for there is none that I know, or heare of in ſuch places, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe therein to conforme themſelues. The onely queſtion therefore touching apparell preſcribed vs miniſters, is in effect about the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſſe, ſo that it being once proued, that we may and ought (it being vrged as it is) conforme our ſelues therein, I doubt not but with all it will be ſufficiently cleared, that we may without ſcruple yeeld to the vſe of the other, appointed vs for our ordinarie ciuill vſe; out of the time of our adminiſtration. Many haue bin, and yet are the obiections againſt it, but they are alſo anſwered by the late reuerend <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> in his foreſayd booke, <hi>Pag.</hi> 256. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that he that will take the paines but to read and marke what is there ſayd therunto by him (partialitie of affection laid aſide) cannot but be ſatisfied I would thinke. And there further ſhall you find proued, that diſtinction of apparell was appointed miniſters and vſed by them, before the <hi>Popes</hi> tyrannie; and namely that this of wering a white linnen garment was in vſe in <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Hieromes</hi> time. <hi>Pag.</hi> 291, 259. and that he defends it not (howſoeuer ſome other haue done) for any ſignification it hath, but for decencie, order, and comelineſſe ſake onely, nor as moſt fit and neceſſarie, but as tollerable and quietly to bee yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2585:18"/>vnto, and vſed for obedience ſake to lawfull authority, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding it for the peace, and good of the Church; ſo proouing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaínſt all their ſaid againſt it, either by the admonition, or by Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Cartwright,</hi> as it is vrged, and vſed by our Church, not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto any thing ſet downe in the word, but rather to be conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant euery way, to the rules thereof touching ſuch matters. And doubtles it is but either the ignorance, or wilfull error of men, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe and ſhun it as they doe, for that either it was firſt deuiſed, and brought in by the tyranny of the Biſhop of Rome, or for that it hath beene vſed, or yet is, idolatrouſly by the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church. For firſt it is recorded by <hi>Polidor d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>inuent rerum. Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 12, and by <hi>Iſidor</hi> writing <hi>de Stephano,</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Stephanus</hi> (who was Biſhop of <hi>Rome anno Chri.</hi> 256, which was long before euer popery was) firſt decreed the white lynnen garment, to be vſed of miniſters in their miniſtration: and for further proofe of this point, let any man read <hi>Hieroms</hi> firſt booke againſt the <hi>Pelagians. Cap.</hi> 9. and vpon the 44 of <hi>Ezechiell,</hi> and <hi>Chriſoſt. hom.</hi> 6. <hi>ad populum Antiochaum,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>concil.</hi> 4. <hi>carthaginenſe. Cap.</hi> 41. and he ſhall find a white linnen gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in thoſe times alſo in vſe amongſt the miniſters of the Church, as a diſtinct apparrell to adminiſter in, yea that more is, who ſo reads <hi>Theodorets</hi> 2 booke <hi>Cap.</hi> 27. ſhall finde that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> gaue vnto <hi>Macarius Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> a pretious garment wrought with gold to adminiſter baptiſme in: all which was before popery that wee ſo much condemne. And as for the other reaſon drawne from the abuſe of it in popery, not onely by the teſtimony of <hi>Auguſtine ad Publico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam Epiſt.</hi> 154 but alſo by the moſt cleare teſtimony of ſundry other writers, both ancient and moderne, and by ſundry preſidents and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples out of the ſcripture, in the foreſaid tract, in the defence of the appointed apparrell. <hi>Page.</hi> 272. &amp;c. the ſaid <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> plentifully prooueth, that the good creatures of God neuer ſo much abuſed by Idolaters, purged of that abuſe, may be vſed and that very lawfully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Gods worſhip and ſeruice, and ſo quite ouerthroweth the ground of this argument, for whereas to reuiue it againe, they wold ſhift off all theſe proofes, by ſaying, they hold onely when the things ſo abuſed, after purged and vſed, are things needfull and profitable; that cannot ſerue there turne: for many of the things, if not all men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in thoſe there alleadged teſtimonies, were not ſo needfull, but that Gods ſeruice might haue beene fully done without them, and it is not for priuate men to iudge, ſo well as the publike ſtate, what is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2585:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>profitable and to be vſed to good end. And in very deed the very Latine word <hi>Superpelliceum</hi> vſed to ſignifie a ſurpliſſe (as ſome not vnprobably haue noted) doth ſhew that it was taken vp and vſed by the miniſters in their adminiſtration, in the primatiue and pureſt times of the Church, when the miniſters, and almoſt all that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſt, through the cruell perſecutions raiſed in thoſe times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſuch, were faine to hide themſelues in Caues, woods, and mountaines, and for very pouerty and want of better, to go clothed in <hi>pellibus,</hi> in beaſts ſkynns, euen therefor for ſeemlineſſe and comli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe when they were to execute their miniſtry, to hide &amp; couer thoſe there baſe garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of skyns. And many of the miniſtry now in theſe daies, either thorough pouerty, or by ſome other meanes, ordinarily going ſo raggedly and vndecently apparrelled as they doe, if it were but in that reſpect, there is and may be a profitable and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary vſe in ſome ſenſe of the ſame garment, to couer the deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the other, and to preſerue them, and their miniſtry, from co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt &amp; deriſion, that too eaſily otherwiſe therefore with too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, they might runne into. But to take away quite all force of this their argument, which yet ſeemes to be the chief and principall that any now ſtand vpon in this caſe: firſt I ſay, ſuppoſe a ſurpliſſe for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; forme altogether like ours, were abuſed and yet is as they ſay in in the popiſh Church, yet ours that we now vſe being not <hi>eadem nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero,</hi> but only <hi>eademſpecie,</hi> they can no more make idolathites of ours then the <hi>Corinthians</hi> could of euery ſheep, becauſe ſuch ſome amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them had beene. As therfore they without any ſcruple of conſcience of their owne &amp; others, might eat of any other ſheepe that certainly was known neuer had beene offered to an Idol, though it were neuer ſo like that which had, ſo what reaſon is there, but that we for all this reaſon, of the abuſing of a ſurpliſſe to Idolatry by the Papiſts, may vſe an other ſurpliſſe made vs ſince the baniſhment of popery out of our churches, which we are ſure they neuer abuſed nor yet vſed? ſecondly I further ad that in very deede, it can neuer ſoundly be proued that a ſurpliſſe, as it is preſcribed to vs with long &amp; large ſleeues, hath been at all any of their idolatrous maſſe garments. An <hi>Albe</hi> I find was one of them, but that was with ſtrait ſleeues &amp; diuerſly otherwiſe in their wearing of it differed from ours, as many may ſee. <hi>Lib</hi> 3. <hi>Durandifol.</hi> 25. <hi>de rationali diuinoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> officioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> In deed I cannot deny but that at the firſt by the ſtatute. 1, <hi>Eliza.</hi> miniſters were to vſe in their miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame ornaments that were in vſe in the raigne of <hi>Ed.</hi> the ſixt, &amp; in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2585:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſecond yeare of his raigne, amongſt which this <hi>Albe</hi> was. But her Maieſtie by vertue of the ſaid ſtatute, with the conſent of the <hi>Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> &amp; the high comiſſioners, in the ſeuenth yeare of her raigne (as it appears by the booke of <hi>Aduertiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> then by authority publiſhed) belike of purpoſe to remoue the ſcandall take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the popiſh <hi>Albe</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the ſurpliſſe in this forme &amp; manner that we weare it, to be-vſed in ſtead thereof, hoping that ſeeing <hi>forma dat eſſe rei,</hi> &amp; ſo therby this differed from that popiſh linnen maſſe garment as it doth, that by this change of the forme, people wold alſo cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge their miſlike therof for the former reaſon, into a liking of this, for that now it was not the ſame, neither <hi>numero</hi> nor <hi>ſpecie,</hi> particulerly nor generally, that euer had beene vſed to or about the Idolatry of the maſſe; for though <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deons Ephod</hi> particularly abuſed, was therfore worthy to be defaced, yet that neither cauſed <hi>Samuell</hi> nor <hi>Dauid</hi> to ſhun the wearing of lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen <hi>ephods</hi> eſpecially differing from his otherwiſe in forme, as they did alſo, yea (to conclude this point) ſeeing the Lord in the old teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t preſcribed ſuch diſtinct apparrell for <hi>Aaron</hi> &amp; his ſonnes, and all their ſons to miniſter in, as we read he did, <hi>Ex.</hi> 28. &amp; that not onely to be ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pical (wherin it ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not with the nature of the times of the new te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament to imitate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) but alſo as it is, there expreſly ſet down) <hi>ve.</hi> 40. for glory &amp; comlineſſe: things lawfull to be reſpected euen now in the time of the new, what ſound reaſon can be ſhewed vtterly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar the Churches now ſince Chriſt, from imitating them at all, in appointing any comely apparrell to diſcerne, and diſtinguiſh their miniſters by? To ſay it is an humane tradition, and therefore to be reiected, as long as it is vrged but as it is without any ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous opinion thereunto annexed, onely for comlineſſe, order and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, as we haue heard by the fift principle before ſet downe, it may lawfully be retayned and vſed. But if it be alleadged, that it is offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue to ſome eye, to many weake brethren, firſt anſwer is to be made thereunto, that indeed that were ſufficient to ſtay men from the vſe thereof, if lawfull authority, had ſet downe no order therein, but now that it hath, the caſe is altered, as that according to the fourth premiſed ground, the ordinance of he Church muſt bee the rule that we are to follow therein, for feare of offending the publike e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate thereof whoſe offence wee are rather to ſhunne then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yea the caſe ſo ſtanding with vs, that in reſpect of our mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry &amp; place, wee haue all to ſay with the <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. wo be to vs if we preach not the Goſpell, as <hi>Cartwright</hi> himſelf hath writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2585:20"/>in the ſecond part of his reply page. 264 we are rather by continuance in our miniſtry, by yeelding to the vſe hereof, to ſhun this rock of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring otherwiſe this woe, then the other. For in this caſe all we can do for ſuch, is ſaith he, to ſeeke better to inſtruct them, and to pray for them, but we may not to preuent not offending of them, leaue vndon that which God hath not left free vnto vs, and to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, writeth. <hi>Beza Epiſt.</hi> 8. and 12. But indeed to many are the readieſt to bee offended at our yeelding hereunto (though intruth it bee of conſcience before God, euen for their good) not for that they are weake brethren, but for that they take vs to be weake in yeelding, &amp; themſelues to be ſtrong in miſliking: and generally whoſoeuer they be, if they be at that point, that whatſoeuer is ſaid to ſatisfie them, they yet are ſo farre from beeing willing ſo to be, that they ſeeke &amp; ſearch all the corners of their wits to the contrary, and refuſe no paines by all meanes to nouriſh themſelues ſtill in their weakneſſe or error, it ſurely ſo appearing, that they would yet rather haue vs leaue all to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor them, what miſchiefe ſoeuer grow vnto the Church, them and there neighbors, vs and ours thereby, then for the good of all theſe by vſing hereof, to continue in our places and miniſtery: verily in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, we make a fond choiſe, if we ſo reſpect them, that we neglect all theſe. Whatſoeuer further is or can be ſaid againſt this (becauſe the obiections againſt it, and the ſigne of the croſſe, therein are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) I ſhall haue occaſion to anſwere, in ſeeking to ſatisfie that which is obiected againſt that, and therefore for the ſurpliſſe in the mean time, I will ſay no more. And yet euen hereby it may ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, that neither the chriſtian Magiſtrate, nor the Church are ſo without all word of faith, as ſome think, for their appointing it, but as they doe with vs, for wee haue heard and ſeene that both, by Gods word haue lawfull authority to make lawes and ordinances, and that the ſame followes then for decency and good order, and ſo in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall though not in particuler expreſlie to thoſe ends to preſcribe this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Of conformity in vſing the ſigne of the croſſe in Baptiſme.</head>
               <p>BEing now come to the ſigne of the Croſſe (howſoeuer ſome ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant perſons thinke to the contrary) the vſe of it euen in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, is far ancienter then antichriſtian popery; for <hi>Origen</hi> that liued
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2585:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>and dyed before the firſt three hundred yeares after Chriſt were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>hom.</hi> 8 in <hi>diuerſos locos Euang:</hi> makes expreſſe mention of it, as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſed in Baptiſme, and ſo doth <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his time, in his one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred &amp; eighteenth tract vpon <hi>Iohn,</hi> and euident it is to all of any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the ancient Fathers, that almoſt infinite are the places, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers plentifully haue ſhowed, that haue writ hereof, that might bee cited out of them that floriſhed before 400 yeares after Chriſt were expired, to proue the frequent vſe thereof, not onely in that ſacrament but alſo otherwiſe. In deed I muſt needs confeſſe that very many of their ſpeeches ſeeme to ſound as though they too quickly grew to attribute to much vnto it. But Maiſter <hi>Perkins</hi> in his probleme late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſhed, writing of thoſe their ſayings, is of opinion, that in ſo ſpeaking &amp; thinking thereof as they did, they had alwaies an eye and reuerence therein, to Chriſt and his death vpon the croſſe, &amp; that they put no ſuch affiance in the ſigne, but onely vſed it with reuerence to teſtifie thereby, boldly their faith in him that dyed vpon a croſſe, &amp; to be an admonitory ſigne vnto them, to ſtir the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp ſo, ſtill to belieue. But howſoeuer either ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to quickly, or the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſince, by miſtaking their metaphoricall, and hyperbolicall ſpeeches thereof, haue vſed it ſuperſtitiouſly, and Idolatrouſly, making it a ſigne of it ſelfe not onely ſignificatiue, but alſo operatiue and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of wonderfull things, we therein and therefore condemne them and retain the vſe thereof onely that was moſt ancient &amp; free, either from ſuperſtition or Idolatry, namely to be as a ſigne or token, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther naturally of it ſelfe, nor ſupernaturally otherwiſe, either ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing, or working or effecting any thing, in thoſe vpon whome we confer it, but it is vſed indeed by vs, and that by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in his owne name, and the congregations or Churches wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is miniſter, after he hath baptiſed the child, that it together with his admittance therof, into the outward viſible church, vpon the bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme precedent and finiſhed, may alwaies after be an admonitory token vnto it, neuer to be aſhamed to profeſſe the faith of Chriſt that dyed vpon a croſſe, and manfully to fight vnder his banner againſt the world the fleſh and the Diuell; for after it is fully baptiſed, &amp; to manifeſt the ſame, <hi>Amen</hi> is ſaid, then by the order of our booke, the miniſter ſaith, we receiue this child into the congregation of Chriſts flock, &amp; ſigne it with the ſigne of the croſſe, in token that hereafter it ſhall neuer be aſhamed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the faíth of Chriſt crucified &amp;c. So that not it alone, but it together with the publike admittance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2585:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>into the Church, is made the token vnto it, of that which followeth &amp; further any man may ſe, that neither it alone, nor it togither with that admittance or receiuing therof, are made any otherwiſe to bee a ſigne or token therof vnto the child, then in our intention, &amp; that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is conferred by the miniſter &amp; the Church, &amp; ſo withall they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it into their fellowſhip &amp; company, of hope they haue, that if it liue (as they truſt it will) comming to age and diſcretion, and then ſeeing others baptiſed, it will remember, that likewiſe when it was baptiſed, it was ſo receiued into the Church therupon and ſo ſigned, and that therfore thereby it would take occaſion (accordingly as they that baptiſed it, and ſo ſigned it, thereby ſeemed to hope and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect) not to be aſhamed to confeſſe the faith, wherin it was baptiſed, &amp; to ſhew the fruits and effects therof in continuing Chriſts faithfull ſoldier, &amp; ſeruant to the liues end. No ſigne therfore at all it is made betwixt God and the child, nor betwixt the child and him, but only as a token togither with the outward receipt therof, vpon his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme premiſed, betwixt the miniſter &amp; the people and it, of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hope &amp; expectation they haue, that it will anſwere after in time both in beliefe, and life, that which they then hopd &amp; promiſed in the name therof, as much as lay in them, it ſhould. And it rather appears, that this indeed is the onely and true vſe of it with vs, for that in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate baptiſme, which is only allowed, when the child is in more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to die then otherwiſe, the booke doth not preſcribe the vſe of it, for that belike they in that caſe, fearing rather the preſent death ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoping for the life, vntill it may thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the faith of Chriſt crucified, it was not thought fit they ſhould thus ſigne it in token of their hope and expectation, that it ſhould &amp; would thus, not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to confeſſe &amp;c. for the reaſon aforeſaid, well &amp; iuſtly therefore it is proteſted in the thirtith canon, that as it is vſed with vs, it is no part of the ſubſtance of the ſacrament, &amp; that being after vſed, it doth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ad any thing to the vertue &amp; perfection of baptiſme, nor beeing omitted, doth detract any thing from the effect &amp; ſubſtance of it, for doubtleſſe the childe priuately baptiſed, by the order of the booke without it: though it immediately after die, is therby &amp; by our church taken and held to be fully &amp; effectually baptiſed the very name of the croſſe, as it is ſaid in the beginning of that canon, we find indeed ſo honored by the pen of the <hi>Apostle</hi> S. <hi>Paule,</hi> as that vnder that very word, often in his epiſtles, he comprehends the death of Chriſt with all the fruits &amp; effects thereof, &amp; therfore the ſigne after a ſort bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2585:21"/>the name of the croſſe to remembrance, and expreſſing it, by all likelyhood euen thereupon grew, as there it is further noted, very early, reuerently alſo to be vſed in the primitiue Church, to make thereby outward and open ſhew, to the aſtoniſhment both of <hi>Iew</hi> &amp; <hi>Gentile,</hi> that Chriſtians were not aſhamed to belieue in Chriſt, that dyed vpon a croſſe. For the vſe thereof to that end is ſo ancient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as that the moſt diligent ſtudier and ſearcher of ancient writers cannot ſhew the firſt originall and beginning there of, he may ſhew when firſt hee reads it was vſed, but that will not prooue that it was not vſed before, but rather ſhewes the contrary. Wherupon ſome thinke that it is ſo frequent with the ancient Fathers, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with <hi>Baſil Cap.</hi> 27. <hi>de ſpiritu ſancto</hi> to tearme it an <hi>Apostolike</hi> tradition, for that they thinke it came from them and their times, for that other originall ſenſe, they cannot ſhew thereof. For that indeed as Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> rule <hi>de baptiſmo contra donatiſtas. Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 24, namely that which is vniuerſally obſerued in the Church, and whoſe originall wee cannot ſhew by councells, and which hath alwaies therein beene vſed, that wee are to thinke certainly to bee an <hi>Apoſtolike</hi> tradition. I wonder therefore the author of the late booke publiſhed againſt the croſſe, allowing the vſe &amp; practiſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the primitiue Church to the ſame ende and vſe that is in vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, ſhould diſſallow it in vs, he ſaith it was ciuill in them, but it is eccleſiaſticall amongſt vs, but what reaſon hath he to ſay ſo, ſeeing it was vſed by them in baptiſme, at the firſt to the ſame end that it is amongſt vs? neither will that ſerue that ſome ſay it was then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vpp, and vſed becauſe chriſtians then liued intermingled with vnbeleeuing Iewes and Gentiles, for let the teſtimonies of the Fathers bee examined where they mention the vſe of it, and it will appeare, that they vſed it aſwell when none ſuch were by or neare, as when they were: and if their liuing amongſt ſuch was a warrant to them for the vſe thereof; why is not ours likewiſe, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing amongſt ſo many profane <hi>Atheiſts</hi> as wee doe? Wee vſe it but (as it is ſaid in the foreſaid canon) as a lawfull outward ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remony, and as an honorable badge of our Chriſtian profeſſion: Whereunto <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> writeing vppon the ſecond comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, hauing an eye ſaith, if it bee lawfull for vs to weare the Cognizance of our owne houſe and family, <hi>licet etiam ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no crucis Christianam nostram religionem profiteri:</hi> And this alſo was ſo cleare and manifeſt, that euen <hi>Beza</hi> though elſwhere no great
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2585:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>friend or patron hereof, in this anſwere to <hi>Baldwin,</hi> ſpeaking of ſuch Churches, that ſtill thus to this end do vſe it, writeth plainly, let ſuch as it is meete, vſe their liberty therein, <hi>Bucer</hi> alſo in his cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vpon the firſt communion booke, doth moſt plainly allow it, and wee know <hi>Cranmer</hi> and <hi>Ridley,</hi> and ſundry other learned and famous Martyrs, liued and dyed in the liking and allowance of it, It is not vrged, nor vſed, nor defended by vs, as ſimply neceſſary, or as immutable, For the late <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> euen when and whiles hee ſought moſt and beſt to maintaine and defend the vſe of it, as it is with vs, writes plainly of it. <hi>Page.</hi> 617 of his foreſaid booke: it was vſed of the primitiue Church, and ſtill may bee vſed, and it may be left; but wee chooſe rather to retaine it, and to vſe it as <hi>Paule</hi> did impoſition of hands, and thereby as by an admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory token to put the child in minde of the duety, as hereby the other moued <hi>Timothy</hi> to bee mindfull of his, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. All which laide togither may make it euident, that not onely it is a thing of the owne nature indifferent, becauſe it is ſo, neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded nor forbid in the word of God, but alſo as it is vſed and vrged, for that neither ſo, any way is it contrary to faith or good manners, but may well ſtand with the generall rules of the word left the Church for her direction in ſuch matters. Howbeit I know for all this, many both godly and learned, will hardly bee perſwaded ſo of it: let vs therefor conſider the reaſons they ſeeme to haue yet further againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Containing anſweres to certaine obiections againſt the ſame, ſome new, and ſome olde, generally stood vpon by the refuſers to vſe it.</head>
               <p>FIrſt ſome ſeeme now to miſlike worſe of it, ſince by the ſaid third canon the vſe of it hath beene explained as it is there, then they did before, and that for two reaſons: for that it is there ſaid to be retained for the remembrance of the croſſe of Chriſt, whereof the ſacrament of the bodie, and blood of Chriſt is a sufficient remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, vntill his comming againe. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. and for that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo it is firſt ſaid that the chriſtians in the primitiue Church ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their children therewith, when they were chriſtned, to dedicate them by that badge to his ſeruice, whoſe benefits beſtowed vpon them in baptiſme, the name of the croſſe did repreſent and then afer
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2585:22"/>that, we now following therein the primitiue and apoſtolicall chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and accounting it a lawfull outward ceremonie, thereby alſo as by an honorable badge dedicate our baptized infants to his ſeruice: For this now ſay they muſt needs be taken for the ſenſe and meaning of our Church in the vſe thereof, howſoeuer before we might haue taken it, as I before haue ſet downe. But if ſuch would herein put in practiſe the laſt of the ſeuen rules layd downe for a preamble to this treatiſe, neither theſe reaſons would proue ſo ſtrong as otherwiſe they ſeeme, nor yet hereby would it follow, that they are one whit enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to take it in a worſe, or harder ſenſe then they might before: for firſt in reaſon and charitie, we are all bound to thinke, that whereas by that Canon, as it euidently appeares thereby, the reuerend <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Prelates</hi> aſſembled ſeriouſly and carefully, went about by their explaining the meaning of our Church in the vſe thereof, to draw men to like and allow thereof better then before, that they were not ſo vnconſiderate, as ſo directly to croſſe their owne intent, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it harder and worſe to be like of then it was before. Then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly it is certaine, if theſe their words might be ſo hardly taken, as thereupon now to build ſuch an erronious and ſuperſtitious vſe of this ſigne, as they (that thereupon now take occaſion more to diſlike it then before) perſwade themſelues they iuſtly may; then theſe reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and learned fathers and brethren of ours, ſhould moſt abſurdly contrarie themſelues, euen in the Canon it ſelfe; for growing towards the end therof, as before they had confeſſed, that alwayes our Church ſince the aboliſhing of poperie, hath vſed it with ſuch ſufficient cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and exceptions againſt all popiſh ſuperſtition and error, as in like caſes are fit and conuenient, ſo they conclude that by this their declaration and explanation of the vſe thereof, they haue not onely purged it from all ſuperſtition and errour: but reduced it alſo in the Church of <hi>England</hi> to the primarie inſtitution of it, vpon thoſe true rules of doctrine, concerning things indifferent: and according to the iudgement of all the ancient fathers. With what probabilitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can any man thinke, that ſo many and ſuch men, could in their foreſayd words haue any ſuch hard meaning, as thereby not only to make the ſigne of the croſſe of it ſelfe to ſerue to the very ſame ende that the Supper of the Lord doth, as to keepe in our remembrance his death and paſſion, but alſo ſo plainly to encroach vpon a principall vſe of the other Sacrament, as to be the meanes whereby the child is ſubſtantially and effectually dedicated to Chriſt and his ſeruice?
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2585:23"/>Surely whatſoeuer other men ſay or thinke in this reſpect, chriſtian charitie neither will nor ſhall euer (I hope) ſuffer me to admit of ſo abſurd a conceit of all, or of any of their meanings, that either were the penners, makers, or allowers of that Canon: yea the ſame charity and the dutifull and reuerend eſtimation I haue of them all, leades, yea enforces me, euen by the conſideration of their owne words v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within the ſame Canon, to be fully reſolued, that that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their meaning: but that indeed their meaning plainly and ſimply was onely, by the former to ſignifie, as the name of the croſſe in the phraſe of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> did comprehend or repreſent, the death of Chriſt vvith all the fruits and effects thereof, ſo the ſigne thereof with the helpe of our intention and meditation in the vſing thereof, might be as a token or ſigne admonitorie to put vs in remembrance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: for by the name of the croſſe they ſay expreſly the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in his ſpeech comprehended as much, and that by that name or word was repreſented all the benefits of Chriſts death, and ſo that thereupon the making of the ſigne thereof was ſhortly after taken vp and vſed, thereby to make ſhew and profeſſion of their faith in him that died on a croſſe, which they could not doe; without taking occaſion thereby in ſome ſort (which is not vnlawfull) to remember his deaths and by the latter doubtleſſe they meant only, (as theſe words, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly in the latter place added, ſhew, <hi>as by the words vſed in the booke of common prayer it may appeare</hi>) ſuch a dedication of the child by that badge to the ſeruice of Chriſt, as formerly the booke onely meant and intended; which was no otherwiſe, then I haue ſhewed before: that is, a publike admittance thereof, with the conferring of that ſigne, into the congregation of Chriſts flocke, and ſo into his ſeruice by confeſſion of faith in him, and manfully fighting vnder his banner againſt all the ſpirituall enemies: for immediatly before the act of the baptizing of it, the miniſter prayeth that whoſoeuer there ſhall bee dedicated vnto God by his office and miniſterie (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in baptizing them) may bee endued with heauenly vertues, and euerlaſtingly rewarded through his mercie: and then hauing baptized it or them, in faith and hope that this prayer is heard, and ſo that they are by, and in baptiſme, ſubſtantially and effectually dedicated vnto God, <hi>Amen</hi> is ſayd: after followes the miniſters and peoples admittance of them, and ſigning of them as aforeſayd: which is nothing but an approouing of the former dedication as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2585:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>much as lies in them, and a declaring of their hope and expectation by that which they do, that in time they will ſhew and manifeſt themſelues to be dedicated to his ſeruice indeede, in faithfully ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of him both in beleefe and life: ſo that euen the words and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the booke, whereunto they haue expreſſe conference, in that Canon plainely ſhew, that by them is meant no other dedication of the baptized by that badge, then an approbation by them of the former dedication of them in and by baptiſme, and ſo their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration thereof by that, and the admittance of the baptized, as the booke appointeth. <hi>Appobatiuè</hi> therefore, and <hi>declaratiué,</hi> and <hi>non effectiuè,</hi> are they and the Canon to be vnderſtood: wherein there is no ſuch daunger or alteration of the former good meaning, that might be of this ſigne.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now therefore theſe new obiections thus anſwered, let vs go on to weigh what further either of olde or elſe of late is obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt this ſigne of the Croſſe, in anſwering whereof I ſhall, I hope; yet more lay foorth the weakneſſe of theſe: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t is ſtill, and long hath beene alledged againſt it, that it is made by vs as it is vſed ſignificatiue (and that when wee haue made the beſt conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction thereof wee can) of that which is ſufficiently ſignified by baptiſme before, and that therefore in the vrged vſe it is not indifferent, and ſo not to be yeelded vnto. To this argument it is aunſwered firſt, that it is grounded of that which will not, nor neede not bee graunted, namely that it is not within the power and libertie of the Church of Chriſt, to ordaine rites and ceremonies with ſignification of ſpirituall things, eſpecially of any thing ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified alreadie by either of the Sacraments, for that were, ſay they, to obſcure them, and as it were to bring in new kinde of Sacraments without expreſſe warrant from Chriſt, which is vnlawfull. For where finde they in the word any warrant to debarre the Church of this freedome and libertie, to ordaine rites with any ſuch ſpirituall ſignification? Sure I am <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> a verie godly learned man in an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of his to <hi>Hooper,</hi> plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewes, that he had neuer found any ſuch, for there hee ſaith, how ſhall we debar the Church of God of this libertie, that it cannot ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſome good thing in ſetting forth her rites &amp; ceremonies? eſpecially being ſo done that no maner of Gods honor is attributed vnto them, and that they be in ſight comly, and in number few, and that chriſtian
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2585:24"/>people be not with them ouerburthened, and matters of greater im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance be not omitted? But indeed though this and the reſt of ours be otherwiſe, thus qualified, as <hi>Martir</hi> would haue all ſuch to be, and are not darke and dumbe ceremonies, as the Popiſh ceremonies aboliſhed were, but are ſo ſet forth (as is ſaid in the tract of ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies prefixed before our Communion booke) that euery man may vnderſtand what they meane and to what vſe they ſerue, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently (as there alſo is noted) are the freer from danger of abuſe; yet indeed, that booke no where, nor any publike ordinance of our Church annexeth any ſignification vnto any of them, as I ſaid before, either for that naturally of themſelues, they ſignifie any ſuch thing, or that ſupernaturally any ſuch is tied thereunto: what vſe ſoeuer therefore we make of any of them, by way of ſignification or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, it is either from our owne declared meaning and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the vſe thereof, as in this, or from our voluntarie meditation thereof, as in the reſt, and therefore they neither darken the nature of the Sacraments, nor no way iuſtly can be ſayd or thought to be as new Sacraments. For all Sacraments by Chriſts owne ordinance, not onely ſignifie the ſpirituall things whereof they are Sacraments, but alſo are Gods ordinarie meanes, whereby he doth offer, deliuer, and ſeale the deliuerie thereof, to all the worthie receiuers of the ſame, in all which theſe come ſhort of them. And who knoweth not but the Sacraments haue ſignifications, ſome principall and proper, and ſome leſſe principall and common to them with other things, and that therefore, though the Church may not either in her intention or voluntarie meditation, in the vſe of her owne rites and ceremonies, thereby encroach vpon the principall and proper vſe of Chriſts Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, yet ſhe may without wronging either of Chriſt or his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, reach in her intention and meditation by occaſion of her owne rites and ceremonies, to thoſe that are leſſe principall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. As for example, the Supper of the Lord hath two ends and vſes, the one principall and proper, to be vnto the right receiuers the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the body and bloud of Chriſt, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. and another leſſe principall, ſet downe in the next verſe, namely to knit vs in communion amongſt our ſelues. Now though the Church, neuer that we read of, ventured by any of her rites and ceremonies to ſignifie the former, yet doubtleſſe both by her loue feaſts taken vp in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times, as it appeares euen in that Chapter, and by the vſe of the holy kiſſe, mentioned <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.16. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.20. yea euen im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2585:24"/>before the receipt of the Sacrament, by <hi>Iuſtine Martirs</hi> time, as it appeares in his Apologie vnto <hi>Antoninus Pius,</hi> it was the Churches vſe to reſemble vnto themſelues the latter, and thereby as by admonitorie ſignes and tokens the better to put and keepe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in remembance thereof: what ſhould let therefore, but that the ſacrament of baptiſme principally and properly ſignifying our remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes in the bloud of Chriſt, and our regeneration through his ſpirit, in being thereby ſo ingrafted into his death and reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as that we are dead to ſinne, and raiſed vp to righteouſneſſe, but that the Church of Chriſt may vſe the ſigne of the Croſſe as ſhe doth with vs, as an admonitorie token of our chriſtian hope and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the children of Chriſtians baptized amongſt vs, ſhall and will anſwer the leſſe principall and common end thereof, which is to bring forth the fruits and effects of the former, thereby before beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon them and ſealed vnto them?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hereby alſo we are led to anſwer another maine obiection which they make againſt it, for that whiles it is vſed as it is, it is charged to be an addition to Chriſts Sacrament and ordinance of baptiſme, which is vtterly vnlawfull, or at leaſt an arguing him in ſome ſort of ſome imperfection in the ordaining the maner how it ſhould be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, in that wee neuer read, he or any of his Apoſtles made any mention of the vſe hereof in the adminiſtration of this Sacrament. For euen hereby we ſee alreadie by the lawfull vſe of the loue feaſts, and the holy kiſſe, together with the receit of the other Sacrament in the primitiue and apoſtolike Churches, neither of which were any more mentioned by Chriſt in the inſtitution of that Sacrament, then this was in this other, that euerie ſuch rite and ceremonie taken vp by the Church and vſed, when and where the Sacraments are miniſtred, though they be alſo ſuch as ſerue to betoken and ſignifie vnto the people ſome thing alſo ſignified by the Sacraments themſelues, as theſe did, are not ſtraight to be accounted either vnlawfull additions thereunto, or things arguing Chriſt of imperfection, in not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring them in the firſt inſtitution: They themſelues that vrge this obiection moſt, do allow diuerſe things in the adminiſtration here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and in the other Sacrament alſo, as here either of godfathers, or godmothers, or of the parents, or of ſome in their roome, and that to anſwer certaine queſtions, as alſo in the other of miniſtring it in the morning, in the publike aſſemblies and to women, none of which are expreſſed in the firſt inſtitution of either, and yet they will not grant
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2585:25"/>either of theſe things to folllow thereupon. But the full anſwere to this obiection is this, that the truth is indeede, that Chriſt hath left the inſtitution of the Sacraments full and perfect for all the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and vnchaungeable things thereunto appertaining, expreſly ſet downe by the direction of his ſpirite in the Scriptures, wherein he is to bee followed without addition or detraction, yea or any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof at all; and that he left vnto his Church the further orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the circumſtances, and further what was fit according to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of times, perſons and places, for the moſt orderly, decent, and comely adminiſtration thereof, prouided alwayes, that therein ſhe keepe her ſelfe in a courſe not contrarie, but conſonant to rules ſet downe in the ſame Scriptures for her direction herein: for thus the practiſe of his true Church euer ſince hath taught vs to vnderſtand him therein. Vnlawfull addition to any of Chriſts Sacraments there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is only that, that either participates therewith in all, or at the leaſt in the chiefe and proper ends and vſes thereof, or is added for complement thereof, as neceſſarie and ſo vnchangeable, whereas our Church in the laſt named tract of her ceremonies proteſteth of this and of all the reſt, that they are retained only for diſcipline and order, and may vpon iuſt cauſes be altered and changed, &amp; therefore are not to be eſteemed equall with Gods law, and we haue heard that the 30. Canon particularly of this proteſteth, that the vſing of it is neither to adde any vertue or perfection to the Sacrament, nor the omitting of it detracts any thing from the effect and ſubſtance of it: And therfore not only priuate baptiſme, as we haue heard, is by our ſeruice booke iudged perfect and effectuall without it, but we ſee that our Church accounteth many thouſands that haue bin, and yet are baptized with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it ſufficiently baptized: ſo that euen thereby it is euident, that it is vſed not as a neceſſarie ſupply to perfect baptiſme, though it be called the ſigne of the Croſſe in baptiſme, but that it is vrged, only vpon the miniſter, to vſe it as is appointed, as a comly &amp; decent rite in the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration thereof, &amp; therfore he is only cenſured for his contempt or neglect of the churches authority in omitting it, but the ſufficiency of the ſacrament therfore, is neuer by authority for want therof once cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in queſtion. To argue therfore that it is vnlawfully added to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, becauſe it is called the ſigne of the croſſe in baptiſme, in the title of the 30. Canon, is a groſſe <hi>Paralogiſme,</hi> for the words of the Canon expreſly ſeuer it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baptiſm, in ſhewing how the child by the book is perfectly baptized before it be vſed; &amp; though the whole tract wherin
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2585:25"/>the forme of baptiſme is preſcribed, is called the form of adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Baptiſme, yet who knowes not that it is ſo, not for that euery thing therin, is to be reckoned as part of the eſſentiall forme of the ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miniſtring therof, but for that the chiefe part therof ſets downe that, &amp; the reſt appertains but to the circumſtances, &amp; to the comly &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent outward accidentall &amp; changeable manner of adminiſtring of it.</p>
               <p n="4">4 But ſay ſome, yet it cannot be but vnlawfull in the vſe, for that being but an humane needleſſe tradition, it is placed ſo near bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and is vrged as it is. But as long as it is ſo ſeuered from it, as it is, &amp; is vrged &amp; vſed with the cautions before mentioned, and ſo no way made either ſimply neceſſary, or any way, any part or point of Gods immediate and proper worſhip, and ſeruice, it is not, nor cannot be any forbid addition thereuto: <hi>Deuteronomie.</hi> 12. or elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, or any vaine condemned tradition, in or by the ſcriptures any where, as is premiſed in the fift principle agreed on at the firſt. But they reply confidently as it is vrged, that it is made a parte of Gods ſeruice and worſhip, and therefore that it is no better then a verie Idoll, and a forbidden likeneſſe of ſome thing in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond commandement condemned, and therefore by no meanes to bee yeelded vnto; yet as confident as they are herein this ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent of theirs, wee vtterly and wholy deny, for neither make wee it, as the ſimilitude of any thing to bee worſhipped with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diuine worſhippe, inward or outward, either in it ſelfe, or in that whereof it is made a likeneſſe: the <hi>Papists</hi> doe both, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as they vſe it, it is with them in their concept a part of Gods di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine worſhippe, and a groſſe Idoll they make of it, but in all theſe reſpects, we condemne them: and doubtleſſe they themſelues, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they ſo eſteeme of it, as it is vſed in their manner, &amp; with their intent &amp; mind, yet as it is made &amp; vſed by vs, there is none of any iudgment &amp; learning amongſt them, that anything regard it, and ſo much the ſtranger it is, that any of our owne religion quite contrary to our publike proteſtation ſhould beare vs, themſelues or any other in hand, that wee lodge any peece of Gods worſhip in it, or make any Idoll of it. Sure I am our harts, our words, and deeds, cleare vs both before God and man hereof: and that ſo being our beſt armour to beare of the blow, that by this weapon they would giue vs, is to thinke &amp; ſay with S. <hi>Paule.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. As touching our ſelue we paſſe very little to be iudged of you or of mans iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But ſeing they are ſo confident of the truth of this their antecedent,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2585:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:2585:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2585:27"/>let vs ſee what they bring to prooue it withall: the effect and ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of all their proofe is firſt, that wee vſe it in the worſhippe or ſeruice of God, therin that the Iewes worſhiped &amp; ſerued God, with diuine wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip in the obſeruing of their ceremonies preſcribed by God, by the miniſtery of <hi>Moſes,</hi> alſo for that therby in the publike worſhippe of God religious dueties are taught, and laſtly for that it is an outward forme deuiſed by man to ſome vſe of religion: in that it teacheth him vpon whom it is conferred, ſome religious dutie, by the ſignification therof. To all this, firſt I briefly anſwere, that neither any of theſe, nor all theſe togither, prooue the antecedent before denied, then my reaſon thereof is this, things may be vſed in the worſhip or ſeruice of God, either as neceſſary, eſſentiall, and ſubſtantiall parts therof only, which are part of Gods worſhip indeed, or but as circumſtances, or only as humane or eccleſiaſticall orders appointed but for ſeemely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; comlineſſe about the ſame, of which ſort this of ours is: and the <hi>Iewes</hi> obſeruing their rites &amp; ceremonies ſo preſcribed with right vnderſtanding, and with ſound hearts to God, therin might &amp; did immediatly ſerue and worſhip God, becauſe they therfore had the expreſſe warrant and commandement of God in particular, and yet not wee in ours, becauſe we want that, hauing only the general rule that he left vs for matters of this kind; and euery thing that any way teacheth religious dueties in the publike worſhip of God, is not ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore part of his ſeruice and worſhip, but that only is ſo indeed, that is of his own immediate ordinance, to that end, &amp; when accordingly it is rightly vſed; of which nature we hold not this rite to bee and as for the laſt which is to proue it to be againſt the ſecond commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; ſo an idoll, it proueth it not ſo to be in this, for though it be an outward forme of ſome thing deuiſed by ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet that is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to proue it to be an idoll condemned in that commandement, for that it ſerues to ſome vſe of religion, or for that alſo by our intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; meditation therof, it is giuen by the miniſter and people as a token betwixt them and the child, of the chriſtian hope and expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that they haue it will anſwere that which therewith all is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For as we haue heard the loue feaſts and kiſſe vſed, as they were with the ſupper, and to that ende they were alſo, were all this, and yet were neither condemned by the ſecond commandement, not yet Idolls. And who can deny but that the altar, built by the a tribes and a halfe mentioned <hi>Ioſua.</hi> 22. was an outward form deuiſed by them, &amp; to a religious vſe, namely to ſhew an other day to their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2585:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>children, that they belonged to the ſame God that the other Tribes did, and that therfore in reſpect of that end, vſe and ſignification, it was allowed by their brethren, when they vnderſtood thereof, how angry ſoeuer they were againſt them for it, before they vnderſtood it, and ſo for all that, not condemned to be againſt the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement or an idoll? That altar in their intention and meditation, when they made it, was to be an admonitory ſigne vnto their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of that religious leſſon in their hope and expectation, and therin there caſe and ours in this are like, but herein yet there is ſome diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that their inention and meaning therin was ſecret to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and therfore their building thereof, ſo ſubiect as it was, to offend the reſt, and ours is plainly with all expreſſed and ſet downe in our book of euery bodie to be ſeene, and therfore the better to preuent all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or other conſtruction of our meaning thereby: but indeede neither they, nor we hold; that the altar, or our ſigne of the Croſſe of themſelues; or any otherwiſe; then in our intention, ſignifie any ſuch thing at all. And yet this puts me in remembrance of another diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt that of thicks and this of ours, that that was viſible and permanent, as the ſubſtantiall croſſes vſed in poperie alſo are, whereas ours is but as an action tranſient, and by and by ceaſed and gone, and therefore neither ſo ſubiect to further abuſe, nor yet to giue offence, as either that of theirs, or theſe of the Papiſts, which are vſed without any expreſſe notification with all, of the ende and vſe thereof, much more of anie lawfull and warrantable mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they haue therein, and therefore the more doubtleſſe offenſiue. Yet if wee ſhould thereunto annexe the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion imagined, why ſhould that bee vnlawfull in our publicke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, when as the writers of the admonition thinke, that they lawfully may preferre ſitting in the receipt of the Lords Supper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any other geſture, for that it beſt ſignifies reſt thorough Chriſt from ſinne, and the rites of <hi>Moſes;</hi> yea that more is, read wee not <hi>Ioſhua</hi> 24. that hee hauing pitched a ſtone vnder an Oake, told the people that that ſhould be a witneſſe againſt them, if they at any time after forſooke that God, whom they then had choſen to ſerue? But yet for further and more full anſwere to theſe prooffes of theirs, we are to vnderſtand that Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or ſeruice, is taken eyther properly, as it is immediately tendered and done to himſelfe, for that he hath ſo commaunded it: Or it is taken in a large and generall ſenſe, for whatſoeuer
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2585:28"/>is done ſo with warrant from any rules of his word, as that the doer may doe it in faith, without which in nothing he doeth he can pleaſe God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. as it ſeemeth to be taken. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.17. where the Apoſtle ſaith, whatſoeuer ye ſhall doe in word or in deed, doe all in the name of the Lord Ieſus. In which ſenſe, ſeruants doing at the commaundement of their maiſters according to the fleſh, any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile worke not forbidden by God, doing it willingly and cheerfully as they ought, for that God hath commaunded ſeruants to obey their Maiſters in ſuch things, the Apoſtle ſaith, they therein ſerue the Lord and not man. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.7. And therefore ſo alſo when ſubiects obey the lawful ordinances and lawes of their Princes and Superiours, be they ciuill or eccleſiaſticall, becauſe God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded obedience and ſubiection to ſuch, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and 1. <hi>Pet</hi> 2. as we haue heard, and <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.17. and their commaundements haue warrant from generall rules left them in the word, though there they be not particularly ſpecified, they may euen therein in this ſenſe be ſaid to ſerue God himſelfe. But yet then any man may ſee, that there is great difference betwixt this kinde of ſeruing of him and the other, for the other, is ſo his proper and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ſeruice, as that men ſinne, if they yeald him it not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his owne onely commaunding it and requiring it at their handes. Whereas this growes to be but an inferiour kind of ſeruice of his, though rightly done verie accetable alſo, by the meanes of the lawfull commaund of the ſuperiour, whom hee hath commaunded to bee obeyed.</p>
               <p>And therefore the late Reuerend Archbiſhoppe in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid booke. Page 269. writing and ſpeaking there of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded rites &amp; ceremonies amongſt vs, and namely of the diſtinct apparrell appointed miniſters, ſaith, that men know we could be without them, &amp; that but for obedience ſake, we do not much eſteme them: which he neither could nor would haue ſaid, of any thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly and immediatly commaunded by God, as a point of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall or neceſſarie ſeruice or worſhip. Now then who is ſo ſimple but he may eaſily conceiue, that things of this latter kinde, may be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about religion and the ſeruice of God in the former ſenſe, and yet for all that, made no part nor peece eyther of religion or of the worſhip and ſeruice of God in that kinde; which as long as they are not, but onely keepe their owne inferiour ranke and place, that which they ſay of their ſo being vſed, makes nothing to proue their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2585:28"/>antecedent, or any vnlawfulneſſe in them. For the rules againſt all ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition by man to Gods ſeruice and worſhip, preſcribed by himſelfe in his written word, and againſt worſhipping and ſeruing of him by the precepts or traditions of men, are onely to be vnderſtood (as it is euident euen by that which we heard <hi>Paul</hi> ſay of ſeruants ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Lord Chriſt in doing their maiſters lawfull commaunds, in any thing that he hath not forbid) of his ſeruice and worſhip in the firſt ſenſe: and therefore they are no better then wreſted, when they are drawne againſt ſuch rites and ceremonies, and conformitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as we ſpake of.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Neyther is that any reaſon of force againſt them, that they are ſaid to be needleſſe and vnprofitable traditions of men, nor that they are made meere eccleſiaſticall, though they had ſome ſignification of ſome religious duety annexed vnto themſelues: for the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the publike ſtate of a Church, touching the needfulneſſe and profitableneſſe of ſuch things; is to bee preferred before the iudgment of priuate men. For they that bee in place of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and haue beene long exerciſed therein, beeing alſo Godly and learned, through their better acquaintance, with the myſteries of gouernment, muſt needs ſee and iudge better what is fit, and meete for order and comlineſſe, then priuate men can. And as for their beeing made mere eccleſiaſticall, by that which I ſaid before of the ſurpliſſe, partly appeares to be falſe, and reaſon I can ſee none (as I haue ſaid alſo) why the author of the booke againſt the croſſe ſhould account the vſe of it in the primitiue Church, beeing the ſame for which we vſe it, (namely to ſhew that we are not aſhamed to profeſſe faith in Chriſt crucified, &amp;c.) to haue bene then ciuill, and therefore lawfull, and ours to be meere Eccleſiaſticall, and therefore vtterly vnlawfull. If their reaſon be, becauſe we vſe it onely in the church &amp; that by the miniſter, &amp; they vſed it alſo elſewhere by any of them, ſurely that is a very weake one. For though mariage be, or were only to be ſolemnized in the church, and in the time of diuine ſeruice, and that onely by a miniſter, yet that would not proue it to be meere Eccleſiaſticall, and the like may be ſayd of the buriall of the dead: For notwitſtanding burials are in ſome ſort ciuill, humane, and politicke thinges, and therefore neither the vſing it onely in the Church; nor onely by the Miniſter, will prooue it ſo. And I wonder that any ſhould euer imagine, that an Eccleſiaſticall rite or ceremonie, ſhould therefore bee thought to bee
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2585:29"/>vnlawfull, becauſe by the end and vſe thereof it teacheth ſome good religious dutie. For none can be ignorant, that <hi>Paul</hi> ordered, that in the Church aſſemblies women ſhould be couered, and men vncoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and that, (as well <hi>Caluin</hi> notes) euen from ground ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in the words of the text there, thereby to ſignifie the ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the one to the other, and the ſuperioritie of the other ouer the other, which are good religious duties and leſſons. And a man would thinke they were ſo much the more commendable, and the more tending to edification, by how much the more they occaſioned men to learne thereby, and to remember good religious duties. But as I haue often ſaid we neyther maintaine nor defend ours, for any ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication they haue, neyther doe we hold they ſignifie of themſelues any ſuch religious dutie onely by the helpe of our meditation, by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of them, and by our intention in the vſe of this in particular, we retaine and vſe it, adding withall as we doe, in hope of the childe learning and practiſing that after, ſo the better alſo (for that we liue amongſt ſuch who haue abuſed it otherwiſe, and would faine ſo doe againe) to keepe and preſerue it from all ſuch abuſe, and in this auncient and lawfull vſe; yet all other arguments failing, many thinke, that becauſe it hath ſo ſuperſtitiouſly, yea idolatrouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beene abuſed of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> euen therefore as <hi>Ezechias</hi> for like abuſe of the braſen Serpent commendably defaced and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed that, though once commaunded to be ſet vp by God himſelf. <hi>Num.</hi> 21. So much more ſhould this, being but a mere humane ordinance haue beene abandoned, and that therefore it ought not thus to be vrged as it is, or ſo being, is yet not in any caſe for the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thereof by vs to be yealded vnto. Whereunto I anſwere, firſt that there is more in the concluſion then the antecedent or premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes will beare, for though the idolatrous abuſe thereof amongſt the Papiſts, by that example of <hi>Ezechias</hi> carry neuer ſuch ſhew of a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon, to haue moued our <hi>Ezechias</hi> accordingly rather to haue quite remoued it (as queſtionleſſe none will or can deny but vpon that conſideration and others, if it ſo had ſeemed good vnto his maieſty, he might) (for doubtleſſe Princes may as well vſe their authoritie to remoue ſuch, as to continue them) yet the ſame reaſon and conſiderations whatſoeuer elſe, are not therefore ſtreight of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient force, to binde vs rather to leaue miniſterie and all, then (he chuſing rather for other reaſons that ſeemed ſtronger vnto his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to retaine, &amp; thus to vrge it, which otherwiſe I am fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2585:29"/>he would not haue done) to yeeld our obedience in the vſing it accordingly. For it is generally held, that <hi>Ioab</hi> did lawfully at the laſt in obeying <hi>Dauids</hi> commaundement in numbring the people. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. hauing before in dutifull manner ſufficiently ſhewed the king his reaſons to diſwade him therfrom, howſoeuer <hi>Dauid</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding perſiſting in his purpoſe offended. And therefore euen <hi>Beza</hi> writing of theſe verie matters of ours that we haue in hand, ſaith that many things may be well obſerued, that are not ſo well commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, how much more therefore herein may we lawfully obey, ſeeing as yet there is not found any vnanſwerable reaſon, but that law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully we may alſo be commaunded as we are? And Maiſter <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> after he had ſaid all that hee could againſt the impoſing of theſe rites and ceremonies vpon vs, yet concludes in his ſecond part of his reply, Pag. 265. in theſe verie words, if the Prince vpon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the inconuenience of ſuch ceremonies, and humble ſuit for the releaſe of them, will looſe nothing of the cord of this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude, for my part, I ſee no better way for the miniſter of God, then with a vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>onition of the weak that they be not offended, &amp; prayer to God to ſtrengthen them thereunto, to keepe on the courſe of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the flocke committed vnto him. But indeed (welbeloued) now the queſtion is not that we haue in hand, what the ſtate ſhould haue done herein (though euen in that reſpect yet, we in dutie, as I haue ſaid all are bound to thinke and iudge, that for that they which are in authoritie haue done, and doe in this caſe, they haue ſufficient warrant and reaſons to ground, and iuſtifie their conſciences vpon, both before God and man, though ſundrie priuate men, not ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted as they with the neceſſarie rules of gouernment conceiue them not ſtraight) but the queſtion that we are now to ſeeke to be reſolued vpon onely is this, whether any of the things whereunto our conformitie vnder paine of depriuation is thus required as it is, be ſo intollerable for vnlawfulneſſe or inconueniency, as that rather then, we will be drawne to yeeld obedience thereunto, wee are by our perſiſting in refuſall thereof, to ſuffer that ſentence of depriuation or but of ſuſpention from our miniſtery to paſſe vpon vs. Touching therefore the reſt of this obiection, (and ſo that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to reſolue vs, that we may and ought rather by yeelding to the vſe of this, to hold on our miniſtery, and to keepe our places, then for abſolute refuſal ſo to do, to leeſe both,) Again, I would wiſh euery man to take the paines to read what the foreſaid Archbiſhop
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2585:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath ſet downe touching the lawfull retaining in the publicke ſeruice of God, things formerly vſed to idolatry, in his forenamed tract tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching apparell, beginning at Pag. 272, vnto 279. for there out of <hi>Aug.</hi> 154. <hi>Epiſtle ad publicolam,</hi> &amp; out of <hi>Caluin</hi> vpon the 23. of <hi>Exod. v.</hi> 24. <hi>Peter Martirs Epist.</hi> to <hi>Hooper. Bucers</hi> to <hi>Iohn Alaſco,</hi> and out of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his to <hi>Cranmer,</hi> as alſo out of <hi>Bullinger</hi> and <hi>Gualters Epiſt.</hi> he ſhall find in all theſe mens iudgements that things both wickedly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, and alſo groſly abuſed, may yet be ſo purged of that abuſe, as that they may be vſed to good Eccleſiaſticall vſes. Yea who knows not that <hi>Gedeon</hi> was commanded to take his fathers bullocke which he had dedicated to <hi>Baal,</hi> &amp; the wood which he had likewiſe appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his ſeruice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> therwith to offer and burnt a ſacrifice to the Lord? <hi>Iud.</hi> 6.25. that the veſſels of the temple abuſe, by <hi>Belthaſar, Dan.</hi> 5.3. were reſtored by <hi>Cyrus Ezra.</hi> 1.7. and after againe without ſcruple vſed in the Temple about Gods ſeruice, by the people of Iſrael after their captiuity, and that ſundrie things profaine before abuſed by the idolatrous inhabitants of <hi>Hiericho,</hi> were yet reſerued, &amp; conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Gods owne liking and allowance to the vſe of the tabernacle and ſanctuary. <hi>Ioſua.</hi> 6.23. Whereby, what exceptions ſoeuer other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they make againſt theſe examples as vnlike to the things with vs in queſtion, thus much yet is got, that the groſſe abuſing of a thing to to idolatry, makes it not alwaies after ſo polluted, as that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore ſimply, it can neuer be purged of that abuſe, &amp; ſo vſed againe about Gods ſeruice to a lawfull and good end and vſe. But to vrge them with examples neerer &amp; liker to our rites in queſtion: Bells in popery haue been &amp; yet be (witnes <hi>Durand</hi> writing of the vſe of them, <hi>de rat. diuin. offic. Fol</hi> 7.) as much abuſed as any of theſe, and yet we remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the abuſe, lawfully I hope retaine them to a good vſe, to call our people together to praiers and ſermmons. Againe the commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints departed, vſed to good and holy ends onely at the firſt in the primitiue Church (as to the praiſing of God for them, and to the better incouraging of others to imitate them) grew in time groſly to be abuſed, in adoring &amp; praying vnto them: and yet in the vniuerſities in their Colledges, and at Saint <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Oxenford</hi> as alſo at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe, and elſe where, the abuſe being remooued, the is a kind of commemoration of ſome departed vſed, and I think none will ſay vnlawfully. They cannot denie both theſe were firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp by humane ordinance, that the vſe of them is Eccleſiaſticall, and that neither of them, are ſimply neceſſarie, and yet I truſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2585:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>they will not ſay, that the Church with vs doth amiſſe in retayning them as ſhe doth to a good vſe, notwithſtanding their foreſaid abuſe by and in the Church of Rome. And kneeling who knoweth not hath beene a geſture and yet is, moſt groſly abuſed in and of that ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue; in ſaying their prayers, and doing their idolatrous deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to their ſtocks and ſtones, and yet who is there that will or may diſalow it as an vnfit &amp; vncomly geſture to be vſed in our religious &amp; dutifull ſeruice of God I grant for kneeling we haue warrant by the commended examples of the godly in the ſcripture, yet thence it followes not that it is ſimply alwaies a neceſſarie geſture in praying, which is ſufficient in this, for that point. But to preſſe them yet more neerely in this caſe, howſoeuer they may ſay, that ſome ſigning with the ſigne of the croſſe and ſome making thereof hath beene, and yet is ſuperſtitiouſly and idolatrouſly abuſed of Papiſtes, how can they ſay in particular that euer this of ours hath ſo beene, or is. They knowe and wee know, that wee in the vſe thereof haue and doe baniſh all their ſuperſtitiouſneſſe and idolatrie in the vſe of it. As therefore wee vſe it there neuer was nor is abuſe in it: neither haue or doe they abuſe the ſame that wee vſe <hi>Numero &amp; indiuiduo eodem:</hi> but the like onely in <hi>Genere aut ſpecie:</hi> which makes no more to the condemnation of ours, then the abuſe of ſome particular cattell, to the ſacrificing of them to idols or diuels, could or did make vnlawfull the ſacrifycing of any other in the time of the olde Teſtament like thereunto to the Lord, or as I ſaid before, to debarre the <hi>Corinthians</hi> from eating without ſcruple of all like mutton or meat, to that which had beene f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red to Idolls. And as for the vrged example of <hi>Ezechias</hi> in demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, for the groſſe abuſe therof, of the braſen ſerpent, who ſeeth not that it reacheth no further but to the encouraging by that example of others of like authority, vpon like occaſion, to do the like, to and with the very particular things ſo abuſed, and yet not to deale in like manner with all things that after ſhall bee like the other made and vſed onely to a lawfull and good ende? And after the vſe of that particuler braſen ſerpent was ended, for the which GOD commaunded it to bee ſet vp, as wee read. <hi>Num.</hi> 21.8. the retaining of it ſo long after, euen without any warrant from God, and therfore there beeing no vſe thereof, neither by diuine ordinance, nor by the churches, when it was ſo abuſed, it was the beſt ſo to deface it.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2585:31"/>And yet theſe things conſidered, that bindes not our King ſtraight of neceſſity to aboliſh this, which he found here before impoſed by the lawfull authority of a famous Church, to a lawfull end, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> howſoeuer other abuſed the like. But why may wee not, to ſome ſuch good ends as wee may imagine, then ſay ſome, aſwell retaine the vſe of ſome materiall croſſes, and other images in our churches, as this? I anſwere that beſides that there are many other reaſons, why that ſhould not be allowed, though this thus bee, there are two euident reaſons taken euen from the nature of this, and the manner of the vſe thereof, that put ſuch a difference betweene this as it is vſed and them, that no way the tolleration of them followes vpon the allowance of this. For firſt as I ſaid before, this is paſt and gone as ſoone as it is made, when as thoſe ſtand and abide ſtill, and this hath the vſe and end expreſs, and that lawfull with the making of it, and ſo haue not the other theirs, neither is their vſe lawfull. And therefore this is, ſo freed from the danger of ſuperſtition and idolatry infinitly better then thoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> Containing anſwers to obiections that concerne ſome men ſpecially, touching theſe ceremonies or rites.</head>
               <p>THus now their maine and chiefe obiections anſwered, touching the vnlawfulnes of the vrged vſe of our ceremonies, becauſe as I vnderſtand there are ſome, who though they bee brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that being in nature end vſe, no otherwiſe then they are with vs, they may of ſome be yeelded lawfully vnto, yet for their parts in reſpect of ſome particular circumſtances ariſing from their own perſons and places, hold it ſtill ſo vnconuenient for them ſo to doe, that they thinke they were better to ſuffer depriuation for refuſing to yeeld conformity, herein ſomething further I muſt adde, for the anſwering of the obiections of ſuch: wherfore indeed I muſt needs confeſſe, that it is moſt true, that the ſame Apoſtle that ſaid ſpeaking of outward indifferent things, that all things were lawfull for him, ads ſtraight that all things were not yet expedient for him, all things edify not, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.23. And therfore queſtionles wel may it be, that ſome that are perſwaded of the lawfulnes of others yelding, yet may doubt of the expediency therof, both in them and in themſelues. But we muſt withal remember (good brethren) that when <hi>Paule</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:2585:31"/>ſo ſpoke, hee ſpake of things indifferent left at liberty, and not as then for their vſe one onely way limitted by the lawfull order of the Church, as now our caſe in this is, for then as wee heard in the fourth generall rule ſet downe in the beginning, the ſame Apoſtle vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. <hi>Act.</hi> 16. &amp; 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. the obſeruation of the Churches orders in ſuch things. For the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in reſpect of their outward vſe, ſuch things haue much altred their nature: for before wheras charity was our rule to direct vs, how, where, and when to vſe our libertie therin, now the publike order of the Church, is to be our director in that reſpect, &amp; both we and others in charity and loue to maintaine peace, &amp; good order in the Church, are to conforme our ſelues quietly to her ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances therein.</p>
               <p n="1">1 But thou wilt ſay perhaps thou haſt ſo long diſuſed them, &amp; by ſpeaking againſt them, made them ſo odious vnto thy people, as that it cannot be but much to thy diſcredit, in that place eſpecially, &amp; to the no ſmall offence of thy people, for thee to yeeld now vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though to keepe thy place and miniſtry, which otherwiſe thou haſt ſmall hope to doe. I graunt this may be, and is the caſe of ſome, and where it is ſo, I cannot deny, but it is the harder with ſuch, by much, but yet I cannot think but in time, by vſing good meanes, if not by thy ſelfe, yet by others, theſe inconueniences, as great as they ſeeme to be, may be remoued. For firſt touching the diſuſing of them, or at leaſt of moſt of them, it was and hath beene very common and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynarie a long time. But in moſt places, not for that the parties that ſo diſuſed them, euer thought it vnlawfull to vſe them, eſpecially when they ſhould be vrged as they are now, vnder ſuch a penalty, for I am ſure ſome that haue diſuſed ſome of them as long well nigh as any, yet haue alwaies both priuately and publikely, when by their text they had iuſt occaſion ſo to do, and otherwiſe alſo ſhewed plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that that was their iudgment of them: and haply alſo would long agoe haue vſed the ſurpliſſe, if they could haue had any fit, or any at all to vſe; And therfore in deed only forbore the vſe of them, becauſe they ſaw without danger, &amp; without any publike offence they might ſo doe. In theſe therefore their former diſuſage of them, beeing but in his ſort, it can be no iuſt cauſe of diſcredit, now to vſe them: for not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, then &amp; now, their iudgment ſeemes to be one and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame of them, namely that they thought and thinke them ſuch things, both for nature and vſe, as that they could and can be content to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare them, when and as long, as the ſtate will quietly permit them so
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2585:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:2585:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:2585:33"/>to doe, and they can be content againe to vſe them rather then any way they would ſcandalize that, or ſhew any contempt of lawfull au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. If any yet will condemne ſuch of inconſtancy or leuity, or that they do ſo of worldlineſſe to ſaue their liuings, they do them the more wrong, and themſelues directly in their ſo raſh iudging, offend againſt the nature of true chriſtian charity, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. and againſt the rules that flatly condemne all ſuch iudging one another in &amp; for things of this kind, as we heard in the beginning of this treatiſe. Such therfore are by good inſtruction, priuatly and publikly to preſerue their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from theſe faults, but if that will not ſerue againſt all ſuch raſh cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, they are with the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. comfort themſelues with the teſtimonie of a good conſcience, that witneſſes with them before God, that that which they do, they do firſt in faith, that ſo lawfully they may do; and then that euen for the good of their flocks, and for the beſt diſcharge of their conſcience before God (as they think in that reſpect) they do as they do herein. And therfore to draw them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> raſh iudging, it were to be wiſhed, that they knew and would imitate the modeſtie of <hi>Iuſtinus Martir</hi> in his conference with <hi>Tripho,</hi> and of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> in his epiſtles to <hi>Quirinum</hi> and to <hi>Iubaiam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> where they may find, that the one wiſhed that Chriſtians might not be condemned in his time, for the bare vſing then ſome of the ceremonies of <hi>Moſes;</hi> &amp; that the other perſwades that none ſhould iudge another, or ſhunne communion one with another, for ther diuerſity of iudgements about the thing then in controuerſie, touching the baptizing againe or no of them that before had bin baptized of heretikes, which counſell as he gaue, he himſelfe tooke; inſomuch that <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> though therein, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting from him in his third booke againſt the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends his moderation, &amp; chriſtian courage in that point, &amp;c. Truly for my owne part, I muſt &amp; may with a ſafe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience before the Lord ſay &amp; proteſt, that I find my ſelf in conſcience ſo bound to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my flock, &amp; to fulfil my miniſterie therin, in feeding of it ſtil with knowledge &amp; vnderſtanding, that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but ſay with the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>Wo is to me if I preach not ſtil the goſpel,</hi> ſuch a neceſſity I find laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me ſo to do &amp; therfore I could neuer perſwade my ſelf (as I ſayd before) that if for any or all theſe things, I ſhold willingly ſuffer my ſelf to be put therfro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it wold euer ſerue me at the laſt day, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhal appear before the iudge of quick &amp; dead, to yeeld a reaſon &amp; an account why I ſo did, then to make anſwer that I could not be ſuffred ſo to do any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, vnles I wold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>form my ſelf herunto. And doubtles (my good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) conſidering you haue the ſame outward calling of the church that I haue: &amp; moſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2585:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>of you as good, if not better gifts, &amp; the Lord hath ſealed vnto you his approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your miniſtry, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fruits &amp; effects therof amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt his peple, why ſhold you not al be of the ſame mind with me if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with me, yet with Maiſter <hi>Cartwright,</hi> who as you haue heard would not haue you to forgoe your miniſtery, for refuſing to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable in theſe, notwithſtanding the offence of weak brethren, for where offences cannot be redeemed (ſaith he in that foreſaid place) otherwiſe then by leauing that vndon which the Lord himſelfe hath not left free vnto vs, but caſt a yoke of neceſſary ſeruice vppon vs (meaning therby our continuance in our miniſtry to preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell) there the caſe is otherwiſe, then that we ſhould for the not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of weake brethren, ſuffer our ſelues to be put from that. In deed, when (as he ſaith a little before) the not offending of priuate men is laid but in the ſcales with any thing that God hath left free vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, as is the choiſe of meats, and drinks then it will wey that down, but in no caſe as he there adds, it will in the ſcales ſo counterway the preaching of the Goſpell (which is ſo neceſſary for him that is called therunto, as that wo is his if he do it not) as that for the ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that, he ſhould let go ſo neceſſarie a duty. But if neither of our words nor opinions be of ſufficient waight, to draw all others to our mindes, yet I would think our reaſons ſhould.</p>
               <p n="2">2 As for that which is vrged in the ſecond place, namely that thou haſt preacht againſt them &amp;c, though as I ſaid that make thy caſe in yeelding harder, yet (good brother) both you &amp; your people know I hope, that it is no newes to heare famous men, to haue their ſecond cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (witneſſe but S. <hi>Aug.</hi> bookes of retractations in matters of a higher nature then theſe, and for which yet there is better &amp; more cleare light in the word) wiſer &amp; better then their firſt. And alwaies it hath beene counted a glorious thing to yeeld vnto the truth, thogh men haue oppugned it neuer ſo long before. And what ſhould any man ſo ſtand vpon his owne priuate credit, as in compariſon thereof to forget the maintenance of the credit of ſo gratious and chriſtian a King, and the publike credit of ſo famous an eſtate of a Church as this of ours is, that vrg vs hereunto? we deceiue our ſelues, if we think we offend men ſtraight in the ſenſe that it is forbid, when they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at that we doe, &amp; therfore prate &amp; talke their pleaſures of vs: but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only we ſo offend Gods children &amp; others indeed, when we do or ſay any thing wherby iuſtly in truth we occaſion the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either to fall into an error, or into any ſin, neither of which we do in this caſe, in obeying for the good of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Gods church the lawful ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the ſame</p>
               <p n="3">3 O that euery one would as forcibly bend his wits to take a ſuruey
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2585:34"/>aſwell of the inconueniences of their refuſall hereof, as it ſeemes they haue done of the contrarie. For then quickly they would and ſhould find (in my opinion) that the inconueniences this way are farre the greater: For doubtleſſe whiles they pretend conſcience, as they do, for their ſo doing, and ſtand vpon ſo many reaſons for that their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall, as though the things whereunto they are vrged were in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpects contrarie to Gods word, do they not thereby as farre as the credit of their perſons, and thoſe their reaſons ſtretch, diſcredit both his Highneſſe, and all the ſtate of this Church, that ioyne with him in the vrging hereof, as vrgers of ſo many things againſt the word of God, to the weakning of them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſequently ſo much, in their reducing to conformitie of religion, and the open practiſe thereof with vs, both <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Brownist?</hi> for ſo many reaſons they haue by this meanes put into their heads and hands, why they ſhould hold out as Recuſants ſtill. And though I muſt needs confeſſe their cauſe be ìnfinitly worſe then this of theſe men, yet by this their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample doubtleſſe, they take the more encouragement to plead their blind and fond conſcience, for the iuſtifying of their ſaid ſtubbornnes and peuiſhneſſe, and alſo to thinke that they may be yet aſwell borne withall in their diſobedience in greater matters (which as they thinke more deeply concerne their ſaluation or damnation) as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, in theſe things of leſſer mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And ſay they in words neuer ſo much, that they yeeld his Maieſtie his iuſt and full title of ſupremacie in all cauſes, and uer all perſons as well Eccleſiaſticall as Ciuill, yet as long as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, as they do in things of this kind, to yeeld him obedience, hardly can they perſwade his Highneſſe (ſaith the libeller <hi>T. W.</hi> in his late augmented and printed libell againſt vs, that in earneſt they doe meane ſo indeed. For in matters that God hath expreſly, or by good conſequent from his word commanded, firſt himſelfe (ſay they) they would and ſhould obey though hee ſayd nothing, and if hee ſhould commaund contrarie to that his word, then anſwer would and might be made, that they were rather to obey God then him, and therfore in ſuch matters as this, which are neither commanded nor forbid by him, are they to ſhew they yeeld it, or wherein elſe can they? And by perſeuering in this refuſall, and ſo occaſioning thereby the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of their ordinarie to paſſe againſt them to their depriuation, alas, to what inconueniences (beſides the weakning of our ſelues and our whole cauſe) do they expoſe themſelues, their wiues and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and their flockes, whereunto they are ſo ſtrictly bound as they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2585:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>are, by ſo many bonds, naturall, ciuill, and Eccleſiaſtical? Surely, ſurely (deare brethren in this yron and hard world, men had neede be ſure that they ſuffer for an apparent righteous cauſe indeede, to beare them out cheerefully to endure the manifolde vnkindneſſes thereof. O what a griefe can it not chuſe but be, for many to ſee as it is much to be feared, it will come to paſſe by one meanes or other vpon this occaſion, they leauing their places, that ſuch ſhall creepe into their roomes, as not onely ſhall want the skill and will that they had to doe good in their flocks, but alſo that ſhall euen in their ſightes, if not pull downe themſelues, yet ſuffer by the common ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary that to be ruinated that they with great labour before had built. But put caſe Law ſhould not be executed ſo ſeuerely, yet who ſeeth not, whiles men openly by their refuſall of this conformitie lay themſelues open to the danger therof, that thereby they ſo wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken themſelues in their places, that they ſhall no ſooner go about to bridle by other lawes, any lewd perſons in their charge, but that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſhall prouoke them to vrge the execution of this law againſt them. It may be the mouths of ſome <hi>Papiſts</hi> &amp; fooliſh proteſtants alſo will be opened againſt them that yeeld, &amp; ſurely we ſe, they will not be ſtopt againſt them that refuſe. Many will be offended at thy yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thou ſaiſt, but more and they that are more worthy to be reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, will be offended at thy refuſall; by thy yeelding thou ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens thy ſelf, thy Prince, &amp; the whole ſtate ſo much, by thy vnity with thy brethren that do againſt their common enemie, and thine, to all your reioycing, by thy continuance in thy refuſall, thou weakens all theſe, to the ioy of our common aduerſaries.</p>
               <p n="4">4 To conclude therefore this point, the beſt aduiſe and councell further that I can giue is, that as heretofore thou haſt ſought to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the reaſons together thou couldeſt, to induce thy ſelfe ſtill refuſe ſo much thy owne harme, and perill, and the Churches, ſo thou wouldeſt henceforth ſtudy as ſeriouſly to ſatisfie the ſame, and ſeeke out as carefully, reaſons to perſwade thy ſelfe that with a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience thou both mayeſt and oughſt to yeeld. For this I muſt needs tell thee, that thou but deceiueſt thy ſelfe, and ſeekeſt alſo to beguile others, as long as thou pretendeſt that thou refuſeſt only of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or tenderneſſe of conſcience, and yet wittingly and willingly thou holdeſt on the former courſe, and doeſt not follow this aduice. Forecaſt therefore in time, as well what is or may be ſayd to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thy conſcience in the lawfull vſe of theſe things, as euer thou
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2585:35"/>haſt, what tendeth to hold it in weakneſſe ſtill and therfore not to dare to vſe them, and earneſtly with thy ſelfe aſwell forethink of the ſcruples and troubles, that thou maiſt haue in thy conſcience, after that by thy ſtanding to long in this refuſall, depriuation bee pronounced vppon thee, for the inconueniences that many waies may grow thereby, as euer thou haſt thought of thoſe that may come by thy yeelding; leaſt when it is too late, thou then cry, had I wiſt; Chriſt yeelded of his right to pay tribute to the officers of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Caeſar,</hi> leaſt he ſhould offend them. <hi>Math.</hi> 17.27. And ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Paule,</hi> though he could truly ſay he was free from all men. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.19, yet withall, euen there, he glorieth in it, not as in an infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of his, but as a commendable courſe of his, wherin hee was to bee imitated of others, that he made him ſelfe ſeruant vnto all, in ſuch outwarde things that he might ſo win the more, in conforming him ſelfe both to <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> weak and ſtrong (as there he ſets downe at large) that ſo by all meanes, of all ſorts he might ſaue ſome, yea thus he did, when there was no poſitiue law of the Church, to binde him ſo to doe, how much rather would hee haue ſo done, if there had beene any ſuch to haue bound him thereunto, vnder pain of ceaſing elſe from preaching of the Goſpell, which to do he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth then ſuch a neceſſity was laid vpon him, that woe was vnto him if hee preacht it not? None of all the Apoſtles more feruent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and frequently taught and vrged the doctrine of chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in ſuch things then hee, and namely from the rites and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of <hi>Moyſes</hi> law, Chriſt beeing come, and hauing put an end therto; and yet wee ſee euen hee, many yeares after Chriſts aſcenſion comming to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> there at the perſawſion of <hi>Iames</hi> and the brethren, to maintaine the peace of the Church, and ſo to winne an opportunity to do the more good amongſt them, yeelded according to the ceremoniall law of <hi>Moiſes,</hi> to bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified the next day with foure men that had made a vow, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the temple with them, declaring the daies of the purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, vntill that an offering ſhould bee offered for euery one of them. <hi>Act.</hi> 21.23. And to the ſame end hee yeelded to the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of <hi>Timothie</hi> before that <hi>Act.</hi> 16.3. And yet he could not, nor was not ignorant what a ſuperſticious opinion many of the Iewes then had of thoſe things, &amp; what a ſhew of a dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent the retaining of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vſe, ſo long after the coming of Chriſt might ſeem to haue. Howbeit as long as he knew in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience how
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2585:35"/>rightly to vſe them, and he knew that <hi>Iames</hi> and the brethren vrged him to yeeld to the vſe of them, but to a good and lawfull end, he thought it his duty to that end to yeeld, as you haue heard. Wherein though the ſucceſſe anſwered not their good meaning therein, yet that is no ſufficient argument to condemne his ſo doing, as vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, for wee know that moſt lawfull and commendable actions through the frowardneſſe of the vngodly haue often as hard euents as that had; and we haue heard, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. how he glories in his ſo doing, and layes his example therein foorth at large to be imitated of others. Indeed when theſe things, and namely circumciſion was vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the falſe Apoſtles, as neceſſarie to ſaluation, and as a thing to merit by, and to tender vnto God any part of his proper and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediat worſhip, then the ſame Apoſtle is moſt ſtoute in the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall thereof, and therefore in that caſe by no meanes, as he writes <hi>Galathians</hi> 2.3.4. would he yeeld that <hi>Titus</hi> ſhould be circumciſed, and hee moſt confidently aſſures the <hi>Galathians,</hi> that whoſoeuer (meaning with that opinion thereof) ſhould be circumciſed, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.2. Chriſt ſhould profit them nothing at all. Otherwiſe yet when it was vſed but as an indifferent thing, without any ſuch ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious opinions tied thereunto, euen in the ſame Epiſtle twice, hee ſayd thereof, that neither circumciſion, nor vncircumciſion was anie thing, but a new creature, or faith that wrought by loue, Chapter 5.6. and 6.15. for as he ſayd in another place, the kingdome of God is not meate nor drinke, but righteouſneſſe, peace, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt, Romans 14.17. And (God be thanked for it) vnleſſe we would wilfully offer the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> manifeſt wrong, we cannot ſay that any ſuch ſuperſtitious opinions are tied by the ordinance or meaning thereof, to any of the rites and ceremonies that it preſcribes vs: but that they are impoſed no otherwiſe then ſuch things lawfully may bee, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would thinke that this example of Saint <hi>Paule</hi> giues vs a plaine light how to carrie our ſelues therein, and accordingly to ſay, the wearing or not wearing of a Surpliſſe, the making or not making the ſigne of the Croſſe, is not any thing. For the beſt and moſt honourable defender thereof that hath beene, and whoſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings thereof for his learning and place, may worthily be taken for the true meaning of our Church therein: hath of the Surpliſſe ſaid in plaine words, Pa. 258. of his foreſaid book, that he thought none that would communicate with vs in the vſe of the Sacraments, though either the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2585:36"/>better or the worſe thereof for the externall habit of the miniſter, and of the other as much (as we haue heard before.) Theſe things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore duely and without partiall or preiudicate opinion weyed and pondered, I hope will be ſufficient to perſwade that lawfully, &amp; with a good conſcience we are rather to conforme our ſelues to the order of our Church in theſe ceremonies, then for refuſing ſo to do, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre the ſentence of depriuation of miniſtery and all. Hauing therfore thus ſayd what I thought fit, and I hoped might ſerue the turne for this, let vs now proceed to the conſideration of the other exceptions, that are made againſt conformitie required, taken from the things that by order miniſters are enioyned, by the booke to read or vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> Touching the practiſe of the orders in the booke of reading of the Scriptures Canonicall.</head>
               <p>THough by a rubricke in the tract of the Communion, we be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to read <hi>Homilies,</hi> yet ſeeing that concernes onely ſuch as cannot or will not then preach: and none ſuch (for any thing that I heare) refuſe to yeeld the vrged conformitie, we may (whiles we are in hand only with this point) omit ſaying any thing of them, reſeruing that which we haue to ſay thereof, vntill we come to the other point, touching ſubſcription, within the compaſſe whereof the allowance of the reading of them indeed comes, not onely by meanes of that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke, but alſo by vertue of the 35 article in the book of articles. The things therefore that now only we haue to conſider, are the excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that the refuſers of conformitie make againſt the order that the booke appoints, firſt for the reading of the Scriptures Canonicall or Apocrypha, and then againſt other things ſet downe in the ſame to be read, in the formall vſe and practiſe thereof, in all which I will ſtriue by how much I haue bene longer then I had thought I ſhould, in the former, by ſo much to be the briefer. In the order appointed by the booke touching the reading of the Canonicall Scripture, three things are miſliked, namely that thereby a great part thereof is not appointed to be read at all, that ſome portions therof are appointed to be read at ſuch times as they are, as namely the <hi>Epistles</hi> and <hi>Goſpels</hi> the firſt day and Sonday of Lent, the Epiſtle on <hi>Innocents</hi> day, and the Epiſtles on Eaſter eue and <hi>Michaels</hi> day, &amp; laſtly that the portions of ſcripture in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted into the booke, and the Pſalter annexed thereunto, are ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2585:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>thereby to be read as they are, wherein yet there are many knowne faults that by no meanes can ſtand with the ſame Scriptures in the originall tongues wherein they were firſt written. The firſt, whereof is prooued to be a great fault, for that it is a kinde or taking from the word, and forbid, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 22. and a depriuing the people of one good meanes the better to enable them to ſearch them: and ſo is the ſecond ſaid to be, for that by the preciſe appointing them at thoſe times, the people are occaſioned to miſtake and to miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, and likewiſe is the third, for that ſo there is falſe witneſſe borne both againſt the ſcriptures, and the ſpirit of God the authour thereof, as to haue ſaid and meant that there, which they neuer did. But to the firſt of theſe, for any thing that I can gather out of the 14 Canon (for by the ſtatute made at the firſt, <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. to eſtabliſh the booke, aſwell all addition, detraction, or alteration thereof, in the vſe and practiſe of it was forbid as it is now by that Canon) it may as well now as before, and indeed both before and now truely and iuſtly bee ſaid that no ſuch inconuenience neede ariſe by that order, for that no miniſter eyther by the booke, or by any other ordinance of our Church, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> forbid, ouer and aboue thoſe that are appointed (being allowed to be a Preacher) to read any or all of thoſe that are not, at ſuch times as he ſhall thinke good, with expoſition thereof, and ſure I am, I myſelfe haue ſo done, and in ful perſwaſion that therin I haue done nothing againſt order therin taken eyther before or now. For doubt leſſe any man may iuſtly think that by our Churches order they were onley ſo left out as they are, in that they were not thought ſo lightſome and eaſie to be vnderſtood as the other, that are appointed to be read, being but barely read without expoſition and interpretation: and in the meane time none that can, are forbid to read, and ſtudie them priuately: But if they were by the Kalender aſwell appointed as the other orderly to bee read, yet in that in pariſh Churches the people com not together, but vpon few daies in the weeke, they might miſſe the hearing of moſt of them aſwell then as now. And as for the ſecond, the inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence imagined to ariſe therby, euery miniſter that makes ſcruple at conformity, being a Preacher as commonly and generally he is, that likewiſe he in reading of thoſe Scriptures at thoſe ſet times by ſoundly interpreting them, and preaching thereupon, which the booke no where nor any other Canon forbids him, may preuent. And touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the laſt I hope ſhortly all occaſion of that obiection will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2585:37"/>when the new tranſlation by his Maieſties moſt Chriſtian and Princely order in hand, ſhall be finiſhed, and authoriſed as the onely authenticall tranſlation to be vſed in our Churches: and in the meane time I am perſwaded that no Biſhop in this land, will denie any miniſter (that can and will in peace and quietneſſe vſe that his liberty) to read all the foreſaid Scriptures, in the booke according to the great Bible by order alreadie from themſelues appointed to be in Churches, that we may read the Chapters out of it: for though we may find that the Booke appointes Epiſtles &amp; Goſpels, Chapters and Pſalmes to be read, yet no where ſhall we finde there eyther that they are ſaid to be any part of the Booke, (and therefore they were left out in the latine tranſlation thereof) or that it ties or bindes vs to any one certaine tranſlation for the ſame. But if it expreſſly did, may we iuſtly thinke that it is contrarie to the word, to read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to the common people, in a tranſlation that hath ſuch faults, as the originalls thereof rightly vnderſtood ſometimes will not beare? Doubtleſſe then I feare (in faith and aſſurance in our conſciences that wee doe alwaies well therein) we ſhall neuer allow them to read, or to haue read vnto them the Scriptures in any tranſlation at all: for when can we be certaine that any tranſlation is free from all ſuch faults? vnleſſe therefore with the Papiſts we would debarre them from hauing and hearing the Scriptures at all in the vulgar tongues, we muſt be contented that they read and haue them read vnto them in tranſlations that (happily when we haue all done) may haue ſome ſuch faults. And this is it, that both they and we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues withall in this caſe, firſt that the faultes be ſuch, which though they ſtand not full with the originall, yet they import not any errour againſt any neceſſarie truth elſewhere taught in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, of which kind (for any thing that I can remember) amongſt all the faults noted in the foreſaid inſerted Scriptures, in the booke there is not one: and then that thoſe faults are not ſo defended by our Church to be no faults, but that alwaies it hath beene permitted the godly learned miniſters in preaching of any of the ſaid Scriptures, in a wiſe and diſcreet manner, notwithſtanding, to acquaint the people with the ſenſe moſt agreeable with the original: yea we ſee moſt of the ſame faults corrected and amended alreadie in the foreſaid great Bible, commonly called the Biſhops Bible: and now againe, that that whole tranſlation and others are to be examined and ſo all faults that haue paſt in any hertofore (as far as the learning and diligence of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2585:37"/>man can reach vnto) are to be reformed, all which duely conſidered I hope may ſerue to anſwere theſe obiections.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> Touching the reading of the Apocrypha.</head>
               <p>NOw the next is touching the bookes appointing the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> to be read as it doth, wherein many faults are found alſo, as that they are appointed publikely to be read at all, that they are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be read as Chapters of the holy Scripture of the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and as more edifying then the Canonicall omitted to giue roome for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that often there is a ſpeciall choyſe of them, for certaine ſolemne feaſt daies or holy daies. All which obiections (as I ſayd before) the Deane the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> now L. Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> (no man then or there finding any fault with that his anſwer, in the conference before his Maieſtie) ſhewed was needleſſe, becauſe by the preface ſet before the ſecond volume of homilies (which is by order of our Church allowed &amp; authorized aſwell as the booke, and indeed publiſhed ſince the bookes firſt authoriſing in the yeare 1563. and therefore euen by that circumſtance more likely and fit to ſerue in this point to explane the meaning of the booke,) the miniſter is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to wey and to read his Chapters priuatly before he come to read them publickly, and thereupon, if in his diſcretion he thinke it fitter and more to edification, to read a chapter of the new for any that is appointed of the old, then ſo to do. And indeed this being euen ſo (as any man may ſee it is in that place) in that thereby he is ſo left to his diſcretion to change any chapter appointed to be read of the old, and therefore thereby ſome times may ſo do with a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall chapter, what reaſon hath any man to thinke, but that hee may ſo do alſo with the <hi>Apocrypha?</hi> or who can truly ſay that euer yet any miniſter was troubled for his quietly and peaceably taking and vſing his liberty herein? you heard alſo before, what the ſame reuerend man truly reported to haue been ſaid by his Maieſtie in the foreſaide conference, touching the omitting the reading of any apocrypha chapter, that iuſtly might be charged with any fault, croſſing the canonicall, <hi>Page.</hi> 63. of his report there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſince in print. Further, certaine it is that Doctor <hi>Abbots</hi> Deane of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inchester,</hi> one called alſo to the foreſaid conference
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2585:38"/>and then vice chauncellor of <hi>Oxenford,</hi> in his anſwere of late publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed againſt Doctor <hi>Hill. Page.</hi> 317: vrgeth againe the direction of the ſaid preface, to the ſecond booke of <hi>Homilies,</hi> publiſhed by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie 1563, whereas the booke was authoriſed ſome foure yeares before, to proue that the miniſter by warrant from thence, may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in ſtead of any of the <hi>Apocryphall</hi> Chapters appointed to be read on ſundaies and holy dayes, and therefore much more as hee ſaith vpon the working dayes, as he in his wiſedome and iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſhall think fit, vſing prudence and diſcretion in that behalfe, read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther canonicall leſſons, and ſo likewiſe others in print, haue anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this obiection ſince (as it ſhould ſeeme with the good liking and allowance of them that be in authority, which being ſo all the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of this obiection, are euen thereby quite cut of, as alſo all the hard conſequents &amp; imputations by reaſon therof impoſed vpon the booke, or the order thereof, ſo farr as conformity is vſe and practiſe therunto reach, are vtterly remoued, eſpecially ſeeing alſo in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the booke, it is ſaid that nothing is therby appointed to bee read, out eyther the pure word of god, or that which is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereupon, and the late <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> as plainly refuſes to defend any thing allowed thereby, to be read, not grounded vpon the word of God: <hi>Page.</hi> 720. of his foreſaid booke. But ſuppoſe the worſt, nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that it be not, or were not ſo, or if it had beene ſo, that now yet by better view of the Callender, for the order in this reſpect in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and by the canons, it were taken away, as ſome alleadge (though loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereinto, and as ſeriouſly conſidering therof as I can, I find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to lead any man iuſtly to think, that in that regard the caſe is any thing altered, or otherwiſe then it was before) yet though by the booke we be tyed neuer ſo ſtrictly to read them, yet we are not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by bound to iuſtifie them to be faultleſſe, neither do we, for likewiſe by the ſaid booke, by a certaine rubrick in the treatiſe of the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, wee allow ſermons to be made, and if we read not a homily, wee ſhould preach, &amp; yet we therby do not iuſtifie all ſermons made according to that order, alwaies to bee without all faults, but ſurely moſt, if not all the ſuppoſed faults againſt them, that by the book are appointed to be read, by fauourable conſtruction, would bee much leſſened, if not quite remoued. And in that by the very expreſſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our booke, wee are both before, &amp; after we read them, to note out of what booke euery chapter thereby appointed to be read, is taken, and in the ſixt article of the booke of articles publiſhed firſt &amp;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2585:38"/>concluded on, in conuocation. 1562, which was three yeares after the booke was firſt authoriſed, all the Apocrypha bookes are appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently ſeuered from the canonicall, &amp; there further it is ſaid, that as <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erom</hi> faith, the Church doth read them for example, of life &amp; inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of manners, yet it doth not apply them to eſtabliſh therby any doctrine, it is moſt euident, howſoeuer they are appointed to be read and ſome canonicall omitted, and on ſome ſolemne feaſt daies, and holy daies, and as chapters of the holy ſcriptures, or of the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, that yet by none of theſe, or all theſe together may wee, or can wee gather, without doing the Church of England manifeſt wrong, that euer it was or is her meaning to equall them, much leſſe to make them in dignity or in edifiing ſuperiour to any of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, but rather indeed all theſe notwithſtanding, her mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and deſire is, that euerie one ſhould know that they are but <hi>Apocrypha</hi> chapters, and therefore farre inferiour to any of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conicall, eſpecially wee hauing acquainted our people as we ſhould which bee canonicall bookes, and which bee apocrypha, teaching them euen by their names to know and diſcerne them. In common charity therefore wee are bound whenſoeuer either in the booke or in the Homilies, they are ſaid either to be Chapters of the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament or holy Scripture, to conceiue (whereas holy ſcriptures, or old Teſtament, are taken either according to the vulgar and common ſpeech, for all that commonly is wont to bee bound to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither in Bibles with the holy ſcriptures of the old teſtament, or more properly and ſtrictly, for thoſe onely bookes therof, that we are ſure were written by ſuch direction of the holy ſpirit, that preſerued the writers thereof, from all erring therein, which therefore onely wee count and call canonicall) in ſo ſpeaking of them, that the ſaid books ſpeake, and therefore are to be vnderſtood ſo to do, onely in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſenſe. And when therein there is compariſon made betwixt chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters of the old teſtament of leſſe, and more edifying, we can not, for the foreſaid manifeſt difference acknowledged to be by our Church betwixt all the canonicall bookes of the old Teſtament, and all the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> euen in that reſpect, vnderſtand it to be betwixt any cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall appointed to be read or not read, and the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> ſet down to be read, but only betwixt the canonicall appointed thereby to be read, and thoſe that are not. And looking into the Kallender for proper leſſons for ſundaies and holy daies, in that therby I find none but canonicall appointed for the ſundaies, and <hi>Apocrypha</hi> often for
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2585:39"/>Saints daies, I alwaies haue taken it, that euen thereby our church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es meaning was, plainly to giue vs all to vnderſtand, that as ſhee in her regard and eſtimation preferres the Lords daie, before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy daies, ſo ſhe would haue vs euen by this order to ſee, that ſo ſhe preferred the canonicall, before the Apocrypha, in worth, credit and dignity: but ſuppoſe the compariſon ſhold by the booke be meant of certaine chapters of the Apocrypha; it is ſo, for that the ſame are wholy conſonant with the canonicall, and are more now to our edification, then the canonicall, either for their hardneſſe, or for that now they doe not ſo much concerne vs. theſe things there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore wayed indifferently, and with mindes rather ſeeking to be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, where iuſtly they may, then needleſly ſtill to keepe ſtones, and blocks in their way to ſtumble at, I truſt the force of this obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is ſo remoued alſo, that henceforth it will ſtay none that duly conſidereth hereof, from peacably yeelding, this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, to conforme themſelues to the vſe and practiſe of the booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 11.</hi> Concerning the interrogatories in Baptiſme.</head>
               <p>THe next thing of any moment, that I find troubles and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders men from yeelding to conformity, is the order of the booke for the interrogations and anſweres in the tract of baptiſme, wherat I the leſſe muſt needs maruail, for that I find by the 23. <hi>Epiſtle</hi> of S. <hi>Au:</hi> that one <hi>Boniface</hi> a learned Biſhop in his time, was alſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled therwith: but then I muſt needs ſay againe, that I find in the ſaid <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> that it firſt appears, that they were euen then in vſe in baptiſing of Infants, in effect as they are now, and that there the ſaid S. <hi>Aug</hi> ſets himſelfe earneſtly in the beſt manner that he could, to defend the vſe of them, againſt all the obiections of the ſaid <hi>Boniface;</hi> yea further certaine it is, let any man read <hi>Dioniſius</hi> eccleſiaſticall <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erarchy. Cap.</hi> 7. &amp; he ſhall there find, that in that Authors time (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer &amp; whatſoeuer he was) they were alſo in vſe, and likewiſe of ſome miſliked, and that therfore he to defend them, expounded then the promiſes there, that the godfathers make, as alſo our late <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop</hi> doth, defending the ſame <hi>Page.</hi> 611. as made onely to ſignifie that they will vndertake to doe aſmuch as ſhall lye in them, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the child liuing to yeares of diſcretion, it ſhall performe that which they promiſe and vow in the name thereof, which therefore in the firſt entrance into our Catechiſme; euery one is taught to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2585:39"/>that thereby he taketh himſelfe bound to do, and therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly that he will. And ſurely hereupon it is alſo that in the new addition to the Catechiſme alſo it is ſayd, that the child performes faith and repentance, in that they promiſed them both in the name therof, ſo ſpeaking for that ſo they are both vowd and profeſſed in the name thereof, and not as ſome hardly take it, as though now therein, it were the meaning of our booke, to teach either that both theſe are actually in euery child that is baptized, or that one may beleeue and repent by another, but only ſo to ſhew that their good hope was, in ſo promiſing in the name thereof, that in time it ſhould and would. To this effect S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in the latter end of his 105. Epiſtle, hauing an eye to the like vſe in his time in anſwering for the child, moſt plainly writes, that truly the child ſo anſwers by their mouths, and beleeues by their hearts and mouths that ſo confeſſe for it; as it is there new borne, by the miniſterie of the baptizer. See him alſo, to this purpoſe: <hi>de verbis Apost. ſer.</hi> 10. And indeed who ſo only conſiders the words of the booke, not only in the queſtions and anſwers themſelues, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as they are ſet downe in priuate baptiſme, but alſo in the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, precedent, and conſequent, in the tract of publike baptiſme, as alſo what is ſet downe concerning the ſame in the entrance into the old part of the Catechiſme, ſhall be enforced to ſee, that the ſaid que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions are propoſed to the infants, and that the anſwers are made only by the godfathers and godmothers thereunto in their names, for &amp; of the hope, which they in chriſtian charity haue of them (which teacheth them to hope alwayes the beſt, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7. of ſuch as are ſo borne in the Church, &amp; deſcended, &amp; come of Chriſtian parents, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14) becauſe they are not able then ſo to anſwer for themſelues. The reaſon and ground of which cuſtome is, that in the adminiſtration of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament the Church alwayes hath thought, there is to paſſe a mutuall ſtipulation &amp; couenant betwixt God &amp; euery partie to be baptized; and therfore ſeeing children born or deſcended of parents, wherof but one is a chriſtian, ſo far herby are ſanctified, as that they are admittable to, and capable of baptiſme, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. &amp; yet not able either to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelues thereunto, or expreſly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to make the ſame, they that in the name of the parents &amp; congregation preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therunto, ſhould in this ſort and maner, as our booke appoints it, do it in their names; thereby not only ſhewing what they hope they after will do, but ſo binding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues alſo to be what means to them they can, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come to age &amp; to diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they ſhal perform al which they
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2585:40"/>promiſed for them, or in their names. Which as his Maieſtie ſaid in the foreſayd conference, when queſtion was about theſe, ought the leſſe to ſeeme ſtrange vnto vs, for that it is an vſuall thing for gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians to orphans and children, to aunſwere and to promiſe ſundry things in the names of their ſayd pupils and wards, and that yet the foreſayd pupils and wards, are after to thinke themſelues bound as well to performe the ſame, as if they had their owne ſelues being of yeares of diſcretion ſo anſwered and promiſed. Whereof alſo another experience his Highneſſe gaue vs in his owne ſelfe, and that when he was crowned king of <hi>Scotland,</hi> being then but an infant, yet then his nobles anſwered in his name, as he himſelfe would and ſhould haue done, if he had then bene a man, and therefore whereof he had euer ſince bene and would be hereafter as carefull to performe the ſame, as if he had himſelfe made the ſayd anſwers. It may be at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this forme was preſcribed to be vſed, onely as ſome thinke, to ſuch as when they were baptized were of diſcretion and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, thus to anſwer for themſelues, and yet very likely is it alſo (that ſo the rather it might appeare that the Church would haue all men to vnderſtand that the baptiſme of ſuch and of infants alſo was one and ſelfe ſame baptiſme, and that they therein aſwell as the other entred into couenant with the Lord) that it was thought fit and neceſſarie, that the ſame anſwer, ſhould be made by ſome of the congregation alwayes in their names, that the other made themſelues. Wherefore to conclude this point, in my opinion, well and iuſtly hath againe our late <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> Pag. 602. of his anſwere to Maiſter <hi>Cartwright</hi> concerning this obiection ſayd, why ſhould it not be as lawfull for the Church of <hi>England</hi> by publike authoritie to appoint godfathers and godmothers, thus to anſwer in the name of the child, as for the writers of the admonition, to allow vpon their priuate fancies, that parents or ſome in their roomes in caſe of their neceſſarie abſence, ſhould in the childs name, make confeſſion of the Chriſtian faith and deſire to be baptized therein? Thus therefore in the name of the child they profeſſing and deſiring, what is it but in the true meaning of the booke in Chriſtian charitie, and hope ſo to do, for that they are perſwaded, that if the child were of age, it would euen ſo do, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe &amp; deſire, &amp; therfore that they in the mean time do ſo in the name therof, in full expectation, that when it ſhall, it will account that by them it ſelfe ſo did, that ſo the Couenant betwixt God, and it may in this Sacrament ſtand ratified therein. And yet in ſome ſence
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2585:40"/>according to Chriſts ſaying, <hi>Math.</hi> 18. it might well bee defended, that ſuch little ones beleeue in him, as habitually they are reaſonable, not actually.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 12.</hi> Anſwering diuerſe obiections againſt the booke touching bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and other things there ordained</head>
               <p>ANd ſeeing by Chriſts baptiſme, and his ordaining of this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, water was alloted to be the outward part therein, why may we not according to the booke, both ſay and thinke that therby the water of the flood <hi>Iordan,</hi> wherin he and others were baptiſed, and all other water, was indeed ſanctified (meaning as the outward element in a ſacrament by the inſtitution therof, was, and is thereby ſanctified for that vſe) to the myſticall waſhing away of ſin! As for that which is further obiected againſt that which is ſet downe, in the foreſaid parte of the Catechiſme, touching two ſacraments, only ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally neceſſary to ſaluation, the meaning onely is, that there are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 2 ſuch, taking a ſacrament properly, as thereafter it is defyned, and that they two are neceſſary ſo to ſaluation, as by no means without danger therof, they may be contemned or neglected, and that for all chriſtians, firſt or laſt, yong or old, and then what iuſt exception can there be made at all againſt that? So alſo by the order that is now take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the booke, that the lawfull miniſter only ſhall priuately baptiſe the child, the old obiection againſt the conditional baptiſing of it after in the caſe mentioned in the booke, is ſufficiently taken away, for now that will neuer neede to be put in vſe. And as for the ring vſed in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, the words with my bodie I the worſhip, or the reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blance that it is ſaid there to haue of the ſpirituall marriage betwixt Chriſt, and his church; I finde not that any ſeeme greatly to ſtand at any or at all of theſe. And if they ſhould, ſurely they could not therin finde any iuſt cauſe; for the ring is but giuen &amp; taken as a ciuill token betwixt the parties that are maried, of the promiſe and couenant that therein they make one to the other: and the word worſhip there vſed, doth but import that worſhip or honor that growes vnto the woman by marriage, in that thereby man is ſo made her head that ſhe hath in the phraſe and ſenſe of the Apoſtle, thereby alſo ſuch a right of, ouer and in his bodie, that thenceforth it is not his owne, as it was before, which whiles by marying of her, he intitles her vnto, very truly hee
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2585:41"/>may ſay in that ſenſe, that with his bodie he doth her worſhip, and finding the holy ghoſt, ſo oft hath taken delight vnder the ſhadow of marriage betwixt man and woman, to ſet forth vnto vs the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all marriage betwixt Chriſt and his Church, the ſpeech in the booke beeing to bee vnderſtood no otherwiſe, but as hauing reference onely thereunto) as indeed iuſtly it cannot) no iuſt fault can be found thereat. Now as for all the reſt of the obiections alledged againſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe conformity in the practiſe of the booke, from certaine words &amp; phraſes in ſundry prayers and parts thereof, which ſeeme hardly and harſhly to be ſet downe, yea ſo as without ſome alteration they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well be ſo vſed, to helpe vs in that, we are to call to mind againe his Maieſties pleaſure (as I noted in the beginning of this treatiſe) moſt gratiouſly deliuered vs in the concluſion of the conference, that hee would haue vs to take euery thing in the beſt ſenſe we could, for in that ſenſe only he would haue vs to vnderſtand that he vrged them to be vſed and yeelded vnto: for in this caſe, we but ſo doing, there is nothing ſo hardly ſet downe, but that taking it and explaining it as the very booke meanes it, and as the publikly profeſſed and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed doctrine of our Church doth lead vs, the offence thereat will be remoued.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Then ſecondly, howſoeuer ſome now (ſo the better to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance their refuſall to yeeld this conformity (though in ſome ſort they haue ſeemed better to like thereof heretofore) perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp; would alſo perſwade others, that now they are more ſtrictly bound to follow in euery thing the preciſe letter of the Booke then before, by the new Canons, and the declared meaning therein of the Church in that reſpect, we are to vnderſtand that both contrarie to his Maieſties foreſaid declared pleaſure in that point, and contrarie indeed both to the meaning of the booke and thoſe Canons, it is ſo conceiued: for if that were ſo, that now vpon no circumſtance or due conſideration the preciſe letter thereof might be altered at any time, then we ſhould neyther burie, baptize, nor viſite any but males, and though there be but one to be baptiſed, we ſhould yet alwaies vſe the plurall number in ſpeaking thereof, for ſo onely runs the letter of our booke: yea (that more is) if conformitie now vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged bound vs to ſuch a preciſe and ſtrict following the very letter of our booke in euery thing, then thereby we ſhould be bound to breed the Biſhops and the whole ſtate, more trouble by our exact ſo doing then they breed any by the vrging of it. For by the laſt rubricke in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2585:41"/>marriage, euery married couple ſhould receiue the Communion that day, and by an other, euen the laſt alſo in the tract of confirmation, it is flatly ſet downe, that none are to be admitted vnto the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, vntill ſuch time as they can ſay that Cathechiſme, and bee confirmed, for all wiſe men will and may eaſily conceiue, that if our conformity bound vs ſo ſtrictly to the letter of the book, that by force of theſe two Canons, no Papiſts or Browniſts that refuſe vtterly to communicate with vs, nor any elſe that cannot both ſay the whole Catechiſme, and were not confirmed alſo, might by any miniſter of this Church lawfully be married, what inconueniences ſoeuer other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe grew thereof, and likewiſe that all vnconfirmed, old and yong, man and woman, noble and ignoble, ſhould be held from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, vntill they could all ſay the Catechiſme, and were alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; there being therefore ſo few in compariſon of the reſt that are thus qualified, what a ſtirre would this breede? Miniſters in moſt places ſhould haue far leſſe to doe, then they haue in marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and in miniſtring of the Communion, and the Biſhops would be driuen to ſpend all their time and liuing in confirming of the vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, or the whole land would mightily be diſquieted in running and ſeeking vnto them for no ſmall ſpace. The makers therefore of the Statute <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. Firſt to authoriſe the ſeruice Booke, though thereby as ſtrict order is taken for the vniforme practiſe thereof, as euer was by any Canons ſince, without any alteration thereof, yet moſt wiſely foreſeeing, as well the miſchiefe and inconuenience that might growe in time vpon ſome circumſtances in following too to preciſely the letter thereof, hath onely made penall the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tranſgreſsing the order thereof, and obſtinate ſtanding therein And therefore alſo in the ſecond Article, whereunto ſubſcription is made touching the vſe and practiſe of the Booke, he that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto ſubſcribeth, promiſeth onely to vſe the forme in the ſaid Booke preſcribed in publicke prayer and adminiſtration of the Sacraments and none other. Whereby it ſhould ſeeme to mee, that the edge and force both of the ſtatute law and Canon, is againſt Papiſts and Sectaries, that will vſe new formes or rites quite differing from this Booke, or but little or none of this, and not againſt ſuch as are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to vſe the whole form &amp; ſubſtance of this without any alteration thereof at all, but vpon due circumſtances, &amp; iuſt conſideration, reaſon and occaſion, and that in peace and ſilence alſo anſwering yet alwaies by that their alteration or explanation, the true end and ſenſe therof,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2585:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>as much as any way conueniently may be, and therefore we may be ſure that ſuch alteration onely of ſome occurrents therein, is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and allowable. As for example, when reading the Collectes appointed to bee read on Chriſtmaſſe daye, or Whitſonday, certaine daies follwing, the miniſter quietly and in good diſcretion, chuſes rather to ſay, as about this time, then as the verie letter is, this day, becauſe he knowes that Chriſt was borne but of one day, and the holy Ghoſt likewiſe in that extraordinarie manner came downe but vpon one: or when in the receit of the communion by himſelfe, or in his owne perſon, he chaunges the words appointed to to be uſed in the deliuerie or receipt thereof; namely the words, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for thee, into theſe words giuen for mee: what Biſhop or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie in the land can or will diſlike him for ſo doing? Likewiſe, in the foreſaid caſes, doubtleſſe the meaning of thoſe rubrickes onely is, that they ſhall communicate that day if there be a Communion then, &amp; they be fit, &amp; that none are to be held to be fit to be admitted thereunto, but they that are confirmed or which for knowledge, age and diſcretion might well haue beene. And ſo though the booke pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing a common rule and order for the burying of all ſuch as in ſuch a Chriſtian Church as this is, ſhall die (in Chriſtian charity and hope that all would die like Chriſtians) appoints the miniſter to ſay in committing his body to the earth, that he doth ſo, in ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hope of reſurrection to eternall life: and therefore after alſo to pray, that they together with that their brother may haue their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect conſummation and bliſſe in Gods eternall and euerlaſting king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: yet now without any breach of that order, by the other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, Perſons dying excommunicated, <hi>Maiore excommunicatione,</hi> for ſome grieuous and notorious crime, when no man is able to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie of their repentance, the miniſter is not to burie at all, much leſſe in the preciſe forme, and with thoſe words. And otherwiſe it is well knowne, that murderers of themſelues, and ſundrie other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious offenders, dying in and for thoſe their ſuch crimes, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are not by that order, or by lawe, at all bound to bury: and therefore not in that very manner. Wherefore then, as the very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon giuen in the Canon in the foreſaid caſe ſhewes, when both the miniſter and moſt of the pariſh knoweth (as the caſe in my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge both hath beene, and therefore may be againe) that one comes to be buried, that liued and dyed moſt profanely, more like a verie Atheiſt, and a groſſe infidell, then like any Chriſtian at all:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2585:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>who doth not ſee, that the diſcreet miniſter (yet therein nothing croſſing eyther the meaning of the booke, or the intent of the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſers thereof) may in wiſedome and diſcretion, in ſuch ſort vſe, and alter thoſe words: as that neither he burie his bodie in ſure and certaine hope of the reſurrection thereof to eternall life, as the body of one that died like a Chriſtian indeed, nor that he be inforced to ſay, that he and the reſt there preſent, may haue their conſummation with him in Gods euerlaſting bliſſe &amp; kingdome? For we may be ſure that it was neither the meaning either of the book or of the authoriſers therof, firſt or laſt, in thoſe ſet and preciſe words and tearmes, to bind the miniſters to bury any but ſuch whom with a good conſcience they ſo might. And yet who knoweth not that fit it is, that for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of good order, the rule ſhould be ſo generally ſee downe, becauſe it is not fit (many amongſt ſuch a multitude of miniſters as be in this kingdome, lacking due diſcretion) to leaue all or any in ſuch a caſe ſimply at their owne liberty? And yet againe, who is ſo ſimple but he vnderſtands, that hardly can any rule in ſuch matters, be ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſet downe, but that euer the equity therof, &amp; the true meaning of the preſcribers therof, will &amp; may admit of ſome inſtances to the contrary. Howbei Gods mercy being ſo infinite as it is, and we in Chriſtian chariritie being bound but as we are, to hope and to iudge the beſt of all that die amongſt vs, doubtles in this reſpect, the inſtances wil be but few, and very rare: and yet euen then to preuent all inconue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niences that might grow by the raſhnes &amp; indiſcretion of ſome mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, I would wiſh none to take liberty of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to alter this form, but by allowance of authority, vpon due information of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar occaſion firſt obtaind: which when there is or ſhall be iuſt cauſe, I am fully perſwaded, would eaſily be obtaind; and I wiſh it ſhould. For it cannot ſtand with the rule, wherby the Church is bound in all her orders to haue eſpeciall care that they tend to edification alwaies; to tye her miniſters in the buriall of the dead, to equall ſuch, in and by ſuch words, with her beſt and liuelieſt members. As for that which is miſliked in the booke, touching priuate abſolution, in the tract of viſiting the ſicke, in my opinion there is no iuſt cauſe thereof: for doubtleſſe in the caſe there mentioned, ſuch priuate abſolution is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary and comfortable: and the meaning thereof is no more, but that they ſo repenting and beleeuing as is there ſpecified in the booke, we, as the miniſters of God aſſure them, that he doth abſolue them of their ſinnes ſo repented of. And indeed there is no
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2585:43"/>difference in the true ſenſe and meaning, betweene this and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall abſolution, or pronouncing of the ſins of the penitent to be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, with good allowance vſed after the generall confeſſion of ſins in the beginning of morning and euening praier: but that there it is pronounced generally to all there preſent that are truly penitent, and beleeue in Chriſt according to the Goſpell: and here particularly but to the ſicke party, likewiſe ſo profeſsing both faith and repentance. And why may we not in the Collect of Trinitie ſonday pray as there the booke appoints to be deliuered from all aduerſitie; as well as in the Lords prayer to be deliuered from all euill? For the Church and her members (at the leaſt ſome particular Churches) ſometime may haue reſt therefrom; but if not, and ſhe were ſure thereof alſo, why may ſhe not yet ſo pray, to ſhew her deſire that ſhe might; as Chriſt did, that the cup might paſſe from him, which he knew ſhould not? Theſe things duly conſidered, I remember nothing of any moment in the booke, to ſtay any man from yeelding to conformity in the vſe and practiſe therof. For, as for the few ſuppoſed incommodious phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in ſome other praiers, they will and may be eaſily remooued, but by taking them in the beſt and faireſt ſenſe, moſt ſtanding with the ſubſtance of ſound doctrine otherwiſe publikly profeſſed, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed in this Church, which vntil euident cauſe be giuen me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, euery one in duty is bound to do. For, what reaſon hath any man to think, but that our profeſſed &amp; authoriſed doctrine, and our praiers and practiſe agree? Our Church therfore diſalowing praier for the dead as it doth, and requiring alwaies ſtedfaſt faith in our praiers, we may be ſure therby, we are only in the Letany ſo taught to pray that God would not remember the ſinnes of our forefathers, as therfore to take vengeance of vs: and in the two collects, the fift after the offertory, &amp; the ſecond after Trinity, to feare, and to diſtruſt, only in reſpect of our ſelues, but not in reſpect of Gods mercy in Chriſt at all. Wherfore, hauing now thus ſaid, what I hope may be ſufficient to moue my good brethren for the Churches peace &amp; good, and alſo for their owne, and to preuent greater inconueniences, to ſtand forth no longer in their refuſal to conforme themſelues in their practiſe to the orders of our Church, required at their hands: let vs paſſe on to that which yet ſeemeth to be wanting, to perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo, if and when need ſhalbe; in the ſame reſpects, rather to yeeld to the vrged form of ſubſcription, then either therfore to ſhun to enter into the miniſtry, when otherwiſe they are fit and might, or for the refuſal therof, to be debarred of the vſe of their gifts therin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:2585:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 13.</hi> Touching the yeelding to the now vrged ſubſcription: and anſwering cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine obiections againſt the ſame.</head>
               <p>BEing therefore now come to the queſtion about this ſubſcription howſoeuer heretofore it was doubted whether it had any expreſſ law or canon to warrant it or no, now wee are put out of doubte thereof by theſe laſt cannons, and namely by the 36, in that wee ſee and know them all to be ſo authoriſed by his Maieſtie as they are, who hath full and ſufficient authority by his highneſſe tytle &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue confirmed vnto him by expreſſe law otherwiſe, ſo to doe. And therefore we cannot be now ignorant, but that our reuerend fathers the Biſhops, haue thereby authority, to vrge ſuch miniſters thereunto, as bee vnder their iuriſdictions, at ſuch times, and in ſuch caſes, and vpon ſuch occaſions, and in ſuch manner, as are expreſſed in the ſaid canons, and alſo vnder the penalties to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers, then ſpecified in the ſame. Wherefore as I ſaid of the former ſo I muſt needs ſay of this, ſo farre as there is nothing within the compaſſe therof, either in the owne nature, or as it is meant by the order of our Church, and the gouernors thereof, contrary either to ſound faith or good manners, taught in Gods word, conſcience (in reſpect of them and this their authority which they haue now by law or canon, though not in regard of the bare nature of euery thing within the reach of the ſame) without all queſtion doth bind vs, for the Churches good, and our owne, to yeeld thereunto. And this is certaine, the firſt Article touching his Maieſties iuſt Title and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie therin ſet downe, &amp; the laſt touching the booke of Articles (ſo far forth as they concern faith &amp; the ſacraments) all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion &amp; profeſſion that hold communion with vs, haue alwaies ſince ſubſcription hath beene firſt required, beene willing and ready to yeeld the ſame, acknowledging, as by the lawes of the realme, ſo alſo by the lawes of God, for the plaine and manifeſt truth therin contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that they were bound in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience alſo, euen for the matter ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo to do. The queſtion therfore concerning this point lies in this, whether the reſt contained in theſe thre articles mentioned in that 36 canon, &amp; in the form there ſet down, may be yeelded vnto with a ſafe &amp; good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, wheru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to firſt I ſay, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paring the Articles wher vnto now ſubſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is required, with the 3 that formerly were wont
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2585:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be vrged, touching either the whole, or the reſt, now only in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, I find no great difference; ſome words are added in the firſt ſomewhat more fully to expreſſe his Maieſties title and ſupremacy, wherof therefore I think euery one likes ſo much the better, and as for the ſecond, it is word for word, the ſame it was, and that requires that by our ſubſcription therunto, we only aduouch, that thoſe twoe bookes therein named (the booke of common prayer, and the booke of ordering Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons) containe nothing contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the word of God, and in the laſt, as I finde theſe words added; (now to make it plaine how many articles the ſaid booke of Articles containes) <hi>being in number</hi> 39 <hi>beſides the ratification,</hi> ſo I obſerue for the word beleeueth, vſed before touching all the Articles therein contained, as it there is expreſly ſet downe, a ſofter word put, namely acknowledgeth, ſo that herein euen in the conſtruction of thoſe that moſt miſlike and write againſt the former, it is moſt cleare, that this now vrged is in reſpect of the matter therof, the very ſame, if not better and eaſier, then it was before, eſpecially conſidering alſo the things amended &amp; explaned in the booke of common prayer of late, as was noted in the beginning.</p>
               <p n="2">2 If any ſay yet, now it is worſe then it was, in reſpect of the forme, becauſe now is added <hi>ex animo,</hi> where it was before but <hi>volens,</hi> that is ſuch a difference, whereupon it will not follow that it is one iot worſe then it was before: for who can indeed ſay or write that he doth a thing <hi>volens,</hi> and yet not <hi>ex animo?</hi> it alſo appearing by that which I haue ſaid already of the former point, that our Church by theſe laſt canons, hath in nothing made the ſenſe of any thing hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then it was before, it muſt neees follow that now to refuſe thus to ſubſcribe, for any that haue ſubſcribed before, is rather an argument of inconſtancy in them then otherwiſe. And this is well knowne, and doubtles the Biſhop (I am perſwaded, by publike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord vnder our hands (can proue, that very few or none of vs, that haue entred into the miniſtry, or haue beene inſtituted or admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them to any liuing ſince the thirteenth yeare of her Maieſties raigne that laſt was, but wee haue both for the one, and the other, how oft ſo euer that hath beene in the latter reſpect ſo oft ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed vnto; the conſideration whereof, one would thinke might bee ſome motiue vnto vs, the leſſe to ſticke at it now againe, if neede ſo require.</p>
               <p n="3">3 This alſo in my opinion may bee an other of ſome force the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2585:44"/>rather to draw vs thereunto, that we plainely ſee in the ſecond article, the reuerend fathers and our brethren that firſt with them agreed in Conuocation, that this forme (to breed vnitie and vniformitie, as they hoped) of ſubſcription ſhould be vrged, thereby only concluded that we ſhould aduouch nothing to bee contained in thoſe two bookes mentioned in the ſecond article, and about which indeed all the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, as I haue ſayd, in this caſe, contrarie to the word of God. Which (as I, and many others haue heard ſome of the chiefe that then were) proteſt, they did of purpoſe therby to eaſe the conſciences of the ſubſcribers, as much as might be: for that as they knew ſundry things within the compaſſe of the ſaid bookes to be <hi>prater verbum &amp; diuerſa à verbo</hi> (which was lawfull enough in things of that nature that they were) ſo they knew alſo, that it was far les to ſay accordingly that they contained nothing contrarie to the word, then that all things contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therein were agreeable to the word, as they require we ſhould ſay touching the booke of Articles, containing the moſt ſubſtantiall grounds and points of the doctrine of faith and the Sacrament, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the third article is: vnleſſe therfore in their ſenſe, we can ſhew ſome things that thoſe bookes containe contrary to the word, we ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt the forme of ſubſcription thereby required.</p>
               <p n="4">4 To ſay or thinke that the booke of Common prayer containes ſome thing contrarie to the word of God, either becauſe it appoints the Canonicall Scriptures but to be read as it doth, or the Apocrypha chapters mentioned in the Kalenders, I hope by that which I haue ſaid before, at large of both thoſe points, it wil or may appear, that therfore it is not ſo. For therby I haue ſhewed that in good conſtruction, (and but yet in ſuch as may well ſtand with any thing ſet downe in those kookes) in both thoſe reſpects, it containes nothing but that which a man may lawfully accordingly practiſe &amp; conforme himſelfe vnto, &amp; therfore nothing contrary to the word: and the like alſo I hope I may aſſume of all the reſt contained therin, in the foreſaid diſcourſe cleared of the obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s made againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> touching co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formity: &amp; that therfore now againe, I ſhall not need to trouble the reader with any further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſall therof. For as I ſaid in the beginning, ſo far as one may lawfully &amp; with a good conſcience go in his practiſe &amp; vſe, he may alſo go in this forme of ſubſcribing therunto: and this is certaine alſo, that that which the authoriſed book containes not, nor binds vs to practiſe (ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within the compaſſe of theſe things we ſhold practiſe, if the books meaning were indeed to bind vs thereuno) that, we need not thinke,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2585:45"/>that it containes at all, thus farre to be iuſtified by ſubſcription: Let vs heare therfore what further particularly can be obiected againſt this ſubſcription, either out of the book of comon prayer, or out of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Some thing further I find to this end obiected, out of the tracts of the communion &amp;, baptiſm, &amp; ſomething out of that of confirmation.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Out of the tract of the communion for the ſicke that there in a certaine caſe, the communion is allowed to be adminiſtred to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, as namely when he is ſicke of a contagious diſeaſe, and none can be got to communicate with him, and that it is there in the treatiſe of the publike communion alſo permitted vnto ſome of the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants to make the generall confeſſion of ſinnes in his owne name, and of all the reſt, as it is there ſet downe; both which are held to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the word, For that the miniſter by the inſtitution is to ſay, eate ye and drinke yee all of this, which he cannot ſay to one alone, and that ſo to make confeſſion of ſinnes is held to be, by the word properly and onely belonging to the miniſter. Neither of theſe I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in the former diſcourſe, becauſe though they bee both in the communion booke, yet they are neither of them there ſo ſet downe, as that neceſſarily either of them need euer come into practiſe, and very ſeldome or neuer haue they, or are like to do: for in the former it is expreſly ſet downe, that in that caſe onely vpon ſpeciall requeſt of the diſeaſed, the miniſter may alone communicate with him, it ſaith not that either he muſt or ought; and therfore we may be ſure, for feare of his owne perill, he will chuſe rather not ſo to do, then ſo to adminiſter it, eſpecially ſeeing the preface to the communion for the ſicke, and a rubricke after therein, ſeeme rather to wiſh that to be neuer miniſtred without a conuenient companie, and that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by oft communicating, and by good inſtruction, ſhall be brought to that vnderſtanding, that they ſhould neuer need to deſire it ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniently to be adminiſtred, and the 67 Canon now binds not the miniſter to go ſo much as to viſit the ſick, in caſe his diſeaſe be known, or but probably ſuſpected to be infectious: and the other is alſo ſo permitted to one of the receiuers (in the rubricke before the ſayd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion) as that the ſaid confeſſion is to be made either by one of them, or by one of the miniſters, or by the prieſt himſelfe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (being ſo ſet downe) that alwayes it ſhall lie in the miniſters or prieſts choiſe, whether any of the other lay communicants ſhal ſay it or no, they haue, wil, &amp; may, by the book ſo preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience, that it ſhall need neuer (more then it hath done) come to be ſo vſed,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2585:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>And thus alſo indeed we ſee euen by the ſame reaſons that neither of theſe are ſo contained in the booke, as that they need to trouble any in the ſubſcribing thereunto. And therefore as the latter is not once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, either by the writers of the admonition, or by <hi>M. Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> as worthy once to be obiected againſt the booke, ſo the other though it be obiected by both, is neither acknowledged nor once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, by the late <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> in his anſwer vnto them (as you may ſee Pag. 528. &amp; 229. of his booke) as at all contained or mentioned in the ſeruice booke; yea Pag. 525. (belike for the reaſons aforeſaid) he ſaith flatly that there is no receiuing of one alone alowed in the booke. But ſuppoſe the worſt; if it ſhould be held to be contrarie to the word, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to miniſter it in a priuat houſe, or that the miniſter in any caſe ſhould miniſter it to one alone, we muſt then condemne all antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, euen in <hi>Iustin Martyrs, Tertullians,</hi> and <hi>Cyprians</hi> times, in whoſe times Maiſter <hi>Cartwright</hi> is inforced to confeſſe it was miniſtred in priuate houſes, in the foreſaid page 525. &amp; in <hi>Serapians</hi> time, who had it ſent him lying ſick on his death bed, to be receiued alone, as we read in <hi>Euſebius Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 43. And though there be but two, the miniſter and the ſick, yet in reference to them two, it may be ſaid take ye, eat yee, and wee know that Chriſt hath promiſed that when two or three are gathered togeather in his name, hee will bee in the middeſt of them. <hi>Math.</hi> 18. And wee know that <hi>Bucer</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> allowed our communion booke, euen in reſpect of the communion therein preſcribed for the ſick, in their iudgments that they gaue thereof, and likewiſe that <hi>Muſculus: de coena Domini</hi> confeſſes that it is retained in diuerſe reformed Churches, yea neither <hi>Beza</hi> nor <hi>Caluin,</hi> but in ſome caſe they allowed it, and <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> as it is written in his life, denied it not the ſicke, but in this caſe we need none of theſe helps, becauſe this thing in queſtion is ſo mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the communion booke as rather yet it is diſalowed thereby then allowed, &amp; cannot iuſtly be ſaid to be contained therein, and is ſo ſhut out againe (as we haue heard) both by the drift of the ſame, &amp; by the foreſaid Canons explayning the meaning of the book touching the miniſters duty in viſiting of the ſicke. And further of the other neede not be ſaid, for it is ſo there permitted, as with all, ſtreight (as we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue heard) the vſe of that permiſsion is preuented. And yet if it ſhold be vrged as plainly yet permitted there, I think wel may it be <hi>Prater verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> but hardly wil it be proued any more to be contrary to the word, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the former, for wher hath the word ſo appropriated
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2585:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>this to the miniſter, and denyed it vnto others, that it ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to permit it to another.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Further yet, in that (in a rubricke next the creed in that tract) it is ſaid, if there be no ſermon, ſhall follow one of me homilies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſet forth or to be ſet forth by common authority, eſpecially the 35 article in the booke of Articles, adiudging both the former booke of Homilies ſet forth in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixts time, and the ſecond booke, the ſeuerall tytles wherof are there ſet downe, to be read in the Churches, by the miniſters diligently &amp; diſtinctly, as containing what doctrine is meete &amp; neceſſary for theſe times, ariſe other obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which they haue againſt this ſubſcription: for ſay they in theſe already extant, ſome faults there are in certaine of them, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand with the word, and further what may be in the reſt, that ſhall bee ſee forth, wee cannot tell, and therfore hard it is to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe; howſoeuer when that booke and rubrick was authoriſed firſt <hi>Eliza.</hi> I there were ſome to be ſet out, yet ſince they that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended then, haue long agoe beene publiſhed, &amp; ſo therefore in that reſpect as I ſaid in the beginnig, this obiection is void. Touching thoſe that then were extant, notwithſtanding the obiected faults againſt ſome of them, very true it is, that there is much wholſome &amp; need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doctrine contained in them, &amp; moſt of them they can not nor do touch with any faults at all, and thoſe which they obiect againſt any of them, are not of any ſuch mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but either with a fauourable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they may be made none at all, or elſe (as they knowe) they are ſuch as about which amongſt the godly learned both of ancient time, &amp; now alſo, there is &amp; hath been great queſtion whether they be to be counted any faults at all or no: and the ſame may as iuſtly bee ſaid of all that ſince haue beene authoriſed. But touching thoſe that by authority then ſhould after be ſet out, why ought not men then in charity, aſwell haue hoped that they in authority would haue a care, that they ſhould containe nothing contrary to the word, as it ſeemeth they did of Sermons to be made? In that therefore they made no exception euer yet againſt the Booke in that reſpect, though then their Sermons be allowed to be made, by preachers euery where, which yet then they could not tell whether they would bee faultleſſe or no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> But in very deed, though ſubſcribing to the Booke of Common Prayer, and Articles, we thus ſubſcribe to the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them to be read, yet in that by the preface before the ſecond Booke of Homilies (which interprets the meaning of both theſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2585:46"/>bookes, herein) it appeares the miniſter is not tied to read them all, but directed there only out of them all, prudently to chuſe out ſuch as be moſt fit for the time and for the inſtruction of the people, our late <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> in his foreſaid booke, Pag. 715. and the next, had iuſt cauſe and ground to write (as he hath) fully to remoue this obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: if any homily (ſaith he) ſhall be appointed hereafter, wherein you miſlike any thing, you need not to read it, for the book appoints you not to read this or that homily, but ſome one which you ſhall like beſt, and if you be diſpoſed to preach, you need read none at all; and touching thoſe which are to be ſet out, if you feare any ſuch thing as you pretend, I thinke, ſaith he, in that caſe a modeſt proteſtation would not be refuſed. Yea as we haue heard before, Pag. 720. he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth in plaine and expreſſe words to defend any thing as appointed by the booke to be read, which is not grounded vpon the word of God. But in very deed I cannot ſee how iuſtly and truely the bookes can be ſaid, to containe all which they appoint or allow in any ſort to be read: ſuch direction for the reading of them, they may well be ſayd to containe, but yet not therfore the things themſelues. Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer in this caſe, in my conſcience, there is great difference betwixt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bound only by the booke to read the Scriptures in a tranſlation that hath faults, the Apocrapha that hath faults, or homilies that hath faults, &amp; the iuſtifying of them to be faultleſſe: and plain it is (ſuppoſe in this that we were ſtrictly thereby tied to read all theſe) that yet no where, by the bookes, or otherwiſe, are we charged, either by practiſe or ſubſcription, to aduouch that all or any of theſe containe no faults, or that ſo doing, to auer that they are no faults: and therfore this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection need trouble vs as litle as any.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 14.</hi> Anſwering more obiections againſt ſubſcription to the book of comon prayer.</head>
               <p>NOw touching baptiſme &amp; the tract thereof, in that priuate bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is ſo vrged as it is therby, and by the 69. Canon, eſpecially ſeeing both it and the other ſacrament are ſaid in the Catechiſme to be neceſſarie to ſaluation, ſome thereupon gather that now it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be the meaning of the booke, and of our church alſo, to hold baptiſm ſo neceſſary to ſaluation, as that none can now be ſaued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. But ſurely herein they wrong in my iudgement both the books and the meaning of our church. For hereby doubtleſſe they do not mean to tie God ſo to this ordinary meanes, as that he neither can nor
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2585:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>will exraordinarily ſaue any without it, though neuer ſo much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by death, before according to Gods ordinance they may haue it. For then the booke neuer ſhould haue beene ſo explained in that point as now it is, that none but a lawfull miniſter ſhould baptiſe the chld in what danger ſoeuer it be. But onely hereby would the ſtate take order as much as might be, (which was very neceſſary) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent all contempt or neglect thereof, if it could in time be had, for as the one extreame is to be auoided, ſo doubtles was and is the other: and ſo for any thing our Church hath done in this point, the ancient doctrine that alwaies hath in this caſe bene held and receiued of and in the Churches of Chriſt, ſince the firſt inſtitution of the ſacraments, namely not the want therof ſimply, but the contempt or neglect therof to be damnable, is held here ſtill, and therfore this of baptiſme is to be counted ſo neceſſary to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as that by all means when &amp; wher (as is aforeſaid) it may be had it is moſt carefully &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to be ſought for.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Now whereas I heare that ſome ſtumble at that, that the child dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after baptiſme before yet it can be confirmed, it is ſaid in the book (immediatly before the Catechiſme, in a rubricke there) that ſuch a child hath all things neceſſary by the word of God to ſaluation, and is vndoubtedly ſaued, gathering thereupon that the meaning of our Church therin is abſolutely and ſimply ſo to tie ſaluation to baptiſme that whoſoeuer once is outwardly baptiſed, cannot be ſaued: ſurely this is as hard a collection &amp; conſtruction of this as may be For firſt it is euident that there the ſpeach is of baptiſed children onely dying before they be confirmed and that of purpoſe it is there ſo ſet down, to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of chriſtian parents in that caſe, &amp; plainly to teach vs all, howſoeuer our Church thinks it fit to retain the vſe of confirmation in ſundry good reſpects, yet (it holds it not to be of the ſame nature with the ſacraments of baptiſm &amp; the Lords Supper, nor ſo neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. And what reaſon is there to the contrary, but that we may and ought in Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charity, ſo hope &amp; perſwade our ſelues of al chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> children ſo baptiſed, dying in their childhood, as that book ſpeaketh?</p>
               <p n="3">3 For all this ſome yet draw an argument to ſtay them from thus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing as is required, for that by the booke as they alleage, ſo much is attributed to confirmation, that it is therby made as a third ſacrament contrary to the 25 article of the book of articles, alſo ſubſcribed vnto, for that ſay they, the Biſhops impoſition of his hands, is in the tract of confirmation expreſly termed a ſigne, wherby they certify them whom they confirme of Gods gratious fauour and goodnes towads them, whereas the article ſaith that neyther confirmation nor any of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2585:47"/>foure by the Papiſts held to be ſacraments, can be ſacraments iin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, becauſe they haue not any viſible ſigne or ceremony ordayned of God. But the contrariety that ſeemeth herein to be, betwixt theſe bookes, is eaſily to be remoued. For though the communion booke make impoſition of hands a ſigne drawne from the example of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, yet it deriues it not from Gods ordinance and inſtitution, as the outward ſignes in Sacraments are, and ſo that notwithanding, the words of the article may well enough ſtand therwith, which only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies it to haue any viſible ſigne ordained by God. Againe, there is great ods betwixt materiall and ſubſtantial ſignes, ſuch as water, bread, and wine are in the ſacraments &amp; this bare action of impoſition of hands: &amp; ſacraments properly taken are not only ſigns of ſome ſpiritual grace but of ſauing grace in Chriſt Ieſus: &amp; they are means alſo to offer, to deliuer, &amp; to ſeale the deliuery of the ſame, to the right receiuers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: all which this is not hereby made. But I maruell what reaſon men haue, to allow of impoſition of hands, as a laudable rite and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, euen drawne alſo from the Apoſtles example, in the ordination of miniſters, thereby as it were by that ſolemne ceremony and prayer withall, to ſet them apart from all others, for the worke of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, and yet ſo much to miſlike of this here: they thinke not that it makes ordination a ſacrament, why ſhould they thinke then that it makes ſo confirmation? it is vſed here with prayer, wherunto eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the booke attributeth their confirmation, appointing the other but withall to be vſed as there by externally to certifie them, that to them particularly that ſtrength is wiſhed. <hi>Hierom,</hi> I am ſure, againſt the Luciferians, acknowledges that it was in vſe in churches in his time and before, and that only to be miniſtred by Biſhops as it is with vs, <hi>propter honorem ſacerdotii, non legis neceſſitatem.</hi> And <hi>Bucer</hi> vpon the fourth to the <hi>Eph.</hi> ſo allowes it, and ſo many other learned writers both ancient, and of theſe times, as you may ſee at large, <hi>Inſt. Cal. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4. &amp; no reaſon it is why they ſhold not, becauſe now with this impoſiion of hands, extraordinary gifts of the ſpirit are not giuen; for thoſe were but to follow therupon for a time, and ſufficient it is now that further ſtrength doth folow. And it is vſed &amp; hath bin thus, by the biſhops &amp; not by the miniſters, not as ſom hardly therupon gather ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to intimate, as though it were a higher thing then either baptiſme or the ſupper, which they vſe to miniſter, but onely for order and in good pollicy, thereby the better to draw both miniſters and godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and godmothers the more carefully to ſee children ſo catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as that being cald by the Biſhops to this, they may therewith their owne mouthes profeſſe and promiſe that which others before
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2585:48"/>did for them. And verily being vſed to this end, in the good Pollicy of the Church, it would be a notable good meanes hereof, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue long wiſht a more carefull and an vniuerſall vſe therof, &amp; lament the neglect therof, for euen from thence the great negligence that hath beene both in miniſters to Catechiſe, &amp; in the people in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to haue their youth duly inſtructed, hath very much proceeded, &amp; I hope the contrary good fruits in that behalfe, will grow by the wiſe and orderly reuiuing thereof.</p>
               <p>What more of any moment, not formerly anſwered is now allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out of the communion booke to ſtay men from ſubſcription, I remember not, ſaue that ſome ſay the vrging of all preſcribed therby now to be read without leauing out any part therof in reſpect of a ſermon, or in any other regard (as it appeares Canon 14) ſhuts out preaching much. But my experience teacheth me the contrary, for though I read fully all that is appointed, and haue long vſed ſo to do, yet I praiſe God, beeing vpon the point now of 60 yeares of age, yet I finde both ſtrength and time conuenient, euery <hi>Sabbath,</hi> both fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone and afternoone to do both. And they that finde not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of ſtrength ſo to doe, they are not by any law forbid to get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Curats and helpers, which may eaſe them, commonly if not of all, yet of a great part of the burden of the tone; and if their liuing bee ſo ſmall, and they are not able to haue that helpe, otherwiſe beeing conformeable, and doing what they can, their weakneſſe or ſickly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, will eaſily with their ordinaries excuſe them. Sure any man may be, that reads the booke and the canons, there to find that the booke often directeth vs to pray that all miniſters may be diligent preachers of the word, and that by the canons better order is taken, for often &amp; diligent preaching of the word, then euer heretofore hath beene, and therefore this may goe amongſt other too hard collections and conſtructions of our Churches meaning well enough, and therfore need not in truth ſtay any man from ſubſcribing. I am not ignorant that yet many things more in this booke are obiected, but becauſe I know onely a charitable conſtruction will eaſily remooue them, I paſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer wiſhing euery man therby, as he may &amp; is bound, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie him ſelfe therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 15.</hi> Anſwering certaine obiections, out of the booke of Ordination</head>
               <p>THus then we are come at the laſt to the other booke of ordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Biſhops, Prieſts, &amp; Deacons, againſt which (as it is in vſe with vs now &amp; long hath been) I muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe I ſee or find nothing euer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2585:48"/>of any moment to this purpoſe, but I finde the ſame ſo fully anſwered by our late moſt reuerend Archbiſhop in his foreſaid book againſt <hi>Cartwright,</hi> ſo oft before named, &amp; ſince by the right reuerend and learned now Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> in his booke written long ſince of the perpetuall gouernment of Chriſts Church, as that I cannot but maruaile (eſpecially ſeeing I could neuer ſee the latter of theſe books by any, once euer yet attempted to be anſwered) that any for all this ſhould ſet a foot againe, any old obiections (and new I finde none of any moment) againſt the ſaid booke, whereunto there they haue beene and are, and that alſo long ago, ſo throughly anſwerd. And therefore for this point (Chriſtian Reader) both to ſpare thy fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther labour and mine, thereunto I referre thee. Onely this in the meane time I ſay for my owne part, that there I finde all that hath beene ſaid of any waight againſt the ſaid booke (in my iudgement) ſo ſatisfied, that in reſpect thereof onely, whoſoeuer refuſeth to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, he doth ſo without any iuſt cauſe at all. For concerning the diſtinction of degrees by that booke (for the better ordering of the Church in her eccleſiaſticall policy) allowed to be amongſt vs the miniſters of the Goſpell, I muſt needs ſay and proteſt, though as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and diligently as I could, I haue read and conſidered all that hath beene written to or from, with or againſt, of that queſtion for theſe thirtie yeares and more, and alſo of purpoſe for the ſame, haue ſearched all antient writers, and all monuments of antiquity, that I could come by, yet I could neuer find any thing of any ſound mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or force brought againſt the ſame: yea (that more is) beſides hatred to popery, &amp; too great an admiration of ſome other Churches I neuer by all this could finde, that the impugners thereof, and the ſeekers in the ſteed thereof to bring in a gouernment of the Church by a parity of Miniſters and their Presbiteries, haue indeed and truth any thing of ſound moment, or of any waight at all to iuſtifie or to countenance their ſo doing. In ſo much that before the late reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Geneua,</hi> for all the fore ſaid points, and ſearch that I haue vſed for this point, I could thereby yet neuer finde, any one Church of Chriſt, ſo big as that of <hi>Geneua</hi> and the appurtenances thereof, any where, or at any time for the ſpace of one ten yeares poſſeſt of that their kinde of gouernment: whereas of the contrarie, through the whole courſe of the Scriptures euer ſince <hi>Moſes,</hi> and through all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical ſtories and monuments of antiquitie. I obſerue it hath bin the lords pleaſure in his good prouidence, alwaies to haue his church
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2585:49"/>ſince it had but outward viſibility in one nation, perpetually gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by diſtinct degrees of miniſters, proportionable to this of ours, for through the old Teſtament from <hi>Moſes</hi> to Chriſt, it had by Gods ordinance an high prieſt, Prieſts and Leuites to that end: and Chriſt enlarging the bounds therof, we find by the playne teſtimony of the new teſtament, he left for the orderly gouernment therof, vntill his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comming. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. ſome <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſome <hi>Prophets,</hi> ſome <hi>Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> &amp; ſome <hi>Paſtors</hi> &amp; <hi>Teachers</hi> In that therfore in that golden age of the Apoſtles, when the gifts of the ſpirit, both vpon the ordinary Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, &amp; chriſtian people, were as they were often extraordinary, we yet find when particular Churches were furniſhed &amp; ſetled with all their ordinary neceſſary officers, they ſtood need beſides the helpe they then had of <hi>Synods,</hi> the ouerſight of euangeliſts &amp; the viſitation againe, and againe, both by their letters &amp; perſonall preſence, of the apoſtles, whiles they liued; what reaſon can any man haue to thinke, that in the times ſince, far worſe then thoſe, the churches of Chriſt ſhould not likewiſe need ſome in the roome of thoſe, to haue a ſuperintendency ouer the particular miniſters, to viſit, and to keepe them in order from time to time? And therfore doubtleſſe the <hi>Apoſtles Prophets</hi> &amp; <hi>Euangeliſts,</hi> in that which they had extraordinaly, ceaſing euer ſince we find, by the teſtimony of eccleſiaſticall ſtories, by light &amp; warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from theſe former proportions, &amp; experience for the better ordering therof in peace and vnitie, the church of Chriſt poſſeſt of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, miniſters &amp; Deacons. All which neither could nor would haue beene ſo, if this other fancyed forme of Church gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t had been ſo eſſentiall thereunto, &amp; this of ours ſo bad &amp; vnfit for the ſame, as the admirers of that other would beare the world in hand, both this and the other hath been &amp; is, for who can or wil be perſwaded that God being of that powre that he is, &amp; louing his church as he doth, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he could or would ſuffer her for 15 or 16 hundred yeares to be deſtituted &amp; bereued of her proper and eſſentiall outward forme of church gouernment, or that he would haue continued &amp; bleſſed the other, as he hath both in the ancient churches &amp; ſince, if it had beene or were ſo diſpleaſing vnto him, &amp; antichriſtian, as they now charge it to be?</p>
               <p n="2">2 As for the preaching by deacons &amp; miniſtring baptiſme by ſuch, who can read the ſtory of the <hi>Acts,</hi> touching the Deacon <hi>Phillip</hi> and what after is ſtoried there in both reſpects, as done lawfully by him, though we read there only of his calling to the office of a deacon, or what to like purpoſe, as the foreſaid two learned fathers haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2585:49"/>out of the monuments of true antiquity, ſuch haue don in the primitiue Church, but he will ſee he hath cauſe to ceaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obiecting that as a fault againſt that booke, in that our Deacons are ſaid to bee called to their office according to apoſtolike example.</p>
               <p n="3">3 And as for the name Prieſt, it anſwering with vs as it doth in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our office, the word presbyter, &amp; not the other <hi>Sacerdos,</hi> what iuſt offence can any take thereat?</p>
               <p n="4">4 And as long as we find Apoſtles directing and commaunding E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts, as <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Timo.</hi> and <hi>Tytus,</hi> witneſſe the epiſtles he wrote to them, &amp; they therby directed to ouerſee, &amp; direct paſtors, as therin &amp; by the ſtorie of the <hi>Acts,</hi> it appeares they did, &amp; paſtors charged to attend &amp; feed their flocks, though we find not the preciſe names of Archbiſhops, Metropolitans or primats at the firſt, what ſhould wee therfore ſtriue? Strife about words, as long as wee find the matter and ſubſtance that in truth implyeth as much, becomes not the Church of God: but the eccleſiaſticall ſtories, and the records of the ancient councells make it moſt manifeſt to them that read them, that it was not long after the age of the apoſtles, ere theſe very names were taken vp and for order ſake giuen to the Biſhops ouer other.</p>
               <p n="5">5 And as for that ſaying, receiue the holy Ghoſt, it beeing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood either of the holy Ghoſt it ſelfe, or of the gifts thereof, fit for the miniſtry, as ſome take it, it doubtleſſe is vſed and meant as a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that ſo they may, not as a ſpeech of one hauing power &amp; authority to giue it, as when Chriſt vſed it, but taking it as very wel, alſo it may for the calling to the miniſtry wherof the holy Ghoſt is the author, they as the ordinary means wherby he calleth them thereunto, may ſay ſo: wherfore to grow to an end, I verily think no one thing more, either hath bred, or yet doth nouriſh more the eccleſiaſticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies of ours about rites and ceremonies, and the outward pollicy of our Church, as either not reading, or negligent ſtudying of ſound antiquity: &amp; therfore I would wiſh, &amp; do with all my heart, that all my good brethren of the in miniſtry, as far as their ability will ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would get them the writings of the ancient fathers, &amp; eſpecially the eccleſiaſticall ſtories of <hi>Euſebius</hi> &amp; his fellows: &amp; the tomes of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient councels, &amp; then next after the ſtudy of the ſacred ſcripture, that they would diligently read &amp; conſider of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For doubtles euen ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they would learn much to direct them how to cary themſelues in their places, &amp; in all occurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that otherwiſe for lack of ſo good pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to much troble many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; are ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſe alſo why they are more troubleſome vnto others, for ſuch matters the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwiſe they
<pb facs="tcp:2585:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>would be, if they were throughly acquainted with the ancient practiſe of Chriſts Church in ſuch caſes. There they ſhould finde it in <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt.</hi> 86. to <hi>Caſulan.</hi> &amp; 118. to <hi>Ianuari: Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. <hi>Zozom. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. &amp; in <hi>Greg. ad Leandrum:</hi> and that one Church is not bound in her outward rites &amp; faſhions to anothers and therfore that no one Church is preiudiced by anothers different faſhions in ſuch things: yea, that <hi>nihil officit in eadem fide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirantium Eccleſiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſuetudo diuerſa:</hi> yea that rather that ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they holding notwithſtanding vnity of faith, they are the more commendable: for the bonds of the Churches vnitie were alwaies held to be one God, one faith, one baptiſme, and not one rite, or one ceremony, and therefore there alſo ſhall they finde, how peacably &amp; godly the learned in ſuch times conformed themſelues to the orders and faſhions alwaies of the Church wherin they liued in ſuch things; and ſo neither gaue offence to any nor tooke any, and how, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent faſhions or opinions in ſuch things notwithſtanding, they thought it vnfit to breake vnity with others. And to this end I wold euery one would but read the ſaid 86. &amp; 118 epiſtles of S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and his next alſo, the 119, for there they ſhould find, both excellent councell, and examples to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Alas how can any ioyne with the browniſts in holding rhis kinde of gouernment by <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> and Biſhops to be antichriſtian and that of theirs to be Chriſts Churche, perpetuall &amp; eſſentiall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, but he muſt needs ioyne with them in their practiſe, rent, &amp; ſeparation from vs?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Or the premiſes conſidered, what ſound reaſon hath any man to thinke though one of late an enemie thereunto hath vrged it in print that the holding of this gouernment of ours to haue warrant from the ſcriptures, ſhould impeach the Kings ſupremacy as though that theſe degrees of miniſters, in this ſort allowed by the booke of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of them, could not both ſtand together; wheras indeed therby, it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed &amp; ſtrengthened as <hi>Solomons</hi> was, in that though the high Prieſthood, was expreſly from God, he yet rightly depoſed <hi>Abiather</hi> and placed <hi>Sadok</hi> in his roome. 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 3.35. For though in reſpect of that which they haue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prínces, they may be ſaid to be theirs, &amp; of humane conſtitution: yet in reſpect of their miniſtry &amp; ſpiritual iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the church, they wel may be ſaid to be of Gods own ordinance.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Wherfore (to grow towards an end) remember we (my good brethren) this one thing more, that it ſtandeth this our ſtate and Church much vpon, hauing made ſo many ſeuere lawes as it hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2585:50"/>
                  <hi>Papiſts, Schiſmaticks, Barowiſts or Browniſts</hi> (cal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as you wil) &amp; hauing alſo ſo executed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as they haue, &amp; minding as it ſemeth ſo to do ſtil (and we ſee it is moſt neceſſary for the peace of the church they ſhould) let none of vs, that ſhould ioyne with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therin, &amp; alſo euery way ſtrengthen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what we could (they ſo multiplying as they do both on the right hand, &amp; left) by any means weaken eyther our' ſelues, or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, againſt them: which once againe I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but put you in mind we do, ſo long as eyther for conformity, or this ſubſcribing, (by our refuſal ſtil hereof) we not only make diſtraction, rent &amp; breach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelues, but alſo ſtrengthen them with ſo many arguments as we ſtand vpon, wilfully to perſiſt in their ſuperſtitious refuſal or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſancy, on the one ſide, &amp; in their like peuiſh ſhu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning of ioining in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> again with vs of the other. And therby as much doubtles as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the weight of thoſe reaſons comes to, or the credit of their perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is that ſtand therupon, are they &amp; will they, be emboldened to think &amp; ſay, in the opinion of ſo many of our own religion and fellowſhip that they haue had wrong, and ſhall haue ſtill, in being puniſhed as they haue beene, are, or ſhall be for refuſing to ioyne with vs in vſe of that ſeruice, and for ſubmitting themſelues to that forme of Eccleſiaſtical gouernment, which is in ſo many reſpects, contrary to the word. O therfore, it were to be wiſhed (good brethren) in this caſe, that you would ſeriouſly remember that the Lord requires of all his, <hi>Zac,</hi> 8.19 that they ſhould loue truth and peace, ioyning them both together, &amp; therfore that the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. had no ſooner wild vs to be ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſpirit, but he addeth ſtreight, ſeruing the lord, &amp; ver. 18. vrging vs al as much as is poſſible to haue pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> with al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For doubtles they are very much deceiued, that vnder pretence of zeale, think they may without offence diſturbe the Churches peace. For who knoweth not that it is as dangerous erring on the right hand, as on the left, and that Chriſt iuſtly checked the ſons of thunder. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.55. though their wiſh of fire againſt the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> came from a fiery zeale, and loue towards himſelfe? Surely euen the lamentable experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we haue had already by the original &amp; growth of the ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſchiſme wherin to many of our brethren haue deſperately run of late years, &amp; wherin ſtil wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and obſtinately they continue (being as all men muſt needs ſee from no other ground &amp; occaſion, but from the too much vrging and amplifying vnder the ſhew &amp; likenes of zeale of the ſame things that now ſtill in this caſe of refuſall of conformity and ſubſcription are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued) I would thinke ſhould haue ſounded ſuch a loud retreat in all our eats from euer medling any more therewith, for feare of the like inconuenience to our ſelues, that ere this wee ſhould haue
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2585:51"/>beene ſufficiently warned from running any more this courſe: for hardly can any be of the iudgment of the one, but he muſt like of the practiſe of the other. But <hi>Nunquam ſera eſt ad bones mores via.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let not <hi>ſtudium partium,</hi> or any preiudicate opinion touching loue of our own priuat credit, or to much deſire too pleaſe a few priuat men make any of vs ſo to forget our duty, either to God, our church, or our ſelues, and thoſe that depend vpon vs, as for a few weake obiections (a thouſand times ſo anſwered, that as <hi>Augustine</hi> ſpeaketh, Epiſt. 118 might ſatisfie, though not a contentious perſon, yet any modeſt and peaceable minded man) to run our ſelues and ours any longer vpon theſe ſo dangerous rocks, ſo much to our owne harme, &amp; ſo much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the reioycing and ſtrengthening of our common aduerſaries. And yet this I haue not writ, or any thing therein, eyther to condemn any that of weakneſſe and tenderneſſe of conſcience indeed, (all this that I haue ſaid notwithſtanding) cannot in faith doe otherwiſe (for I haue learned of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. (as I ſaid in the beginning) that whatſoeuer is not done of faith is ſinne, or any way to ſtay or to withold them that be in authority, eyther from ſhewing what fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour they will or may to ſuch (elſe alſo being peaceable and fruitfull men) or when it ſhal ſeem good vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is regard of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to remoue, or better to ſmoth the controuerted changable things, they moſt take offence at, but onely in the meane time, whileſt things ſtand as they do, hereby to perwade my good brethren in the beſt manner I could, how with a good conſcience theſe things may be yeelded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, for the peace of the Church without any iuſt offence, therby either giuen or taken, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that for their not ſo yeelding they ſhold ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelues to be kept from entring the miniſtery, or to be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thereof againe, or but to be but ſuſpended from the execution thereof, by the ſentence of the Biſhoppes. But in the meane time, whiles we can grow all to be thus minded, &amp; to be at vnity amongſt our ſelues, in theſe things, let no man thinke that therfore he hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny iuſt cauſe giuen him, to call into queſtion the truth of our religion otherwiſe, or the Papiſt at all therefore to inſult ouer vs. For none of any reading of the monuments of antiquitie can be ignorant, that in the primitiue Church, and in the beſt times thereof ſince the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, &amp; that for a long time together, there hath beene amongſt the ancient Chriſtians, otherwiſe very ſound, and at vnitie in the trueth, and ſubſtance of religion amongſt themſelues, as great diuerſities of opinons, and as hot contentions as in theſe reſpects theſe of ours
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2585:51"/>be about Eccleſiaſticall rites and ceremonies. And all the world may know but by the confeſſed differences of opinions by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelues, in his bookes of controuerſies in matters of far higher nature: that the Papiſts of all men haue leaſt vnitie euen in the chiefe grounds of their religion: and it is as famouſly knowne, that here in England whiles they bare the ſway: for all their great brag of vnitie otherwiſe, that in their church ſeruice there was great diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: ſome following the vſe of Sarum; ſome Herford vſe, ſome the vſe of Bangor; ſome of Yorke, and ſome of Lincolne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 16.</hi> Containing the concluſion and exhortation to vnitie.</head>
               <p>YEt to conclude (good brethren) ſeeing in euery particular natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall church, vniformitie in ſuch things, is very requiſit and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, for the better maintenance of peace and loue therein: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of loue and compaſſion to our common mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which as I haue ſayd, is troubled with ſo dangerous enemies, both on her right hand and left, and ſo to bury and extinguiſh for euer the odious name of Puritants, &amp; to put an end to all ſhew of Schiſme, diſtraction, and diuiſion amongſt our ſelues, to the no ſmall ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our ſelues, to our reioycing againſt our common aduerſaries, and ſo to the great weakning and vndoubted griefe of our enemies, let vs, all of vs for euer hereafter, giue ouer contending any more thus amongſt our ſelues, about theſe our mothers outward faſhions, trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings, and deckings, and let vs both ſpeedily and vnfainedly, euery one of vs, reunite our ſelues together in vnitie of iudgement, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of practiſe, as by theſe her outward orders, is by her authority required at our hands, that ſo we may bend all our forces as dutifull children together to the preſeruation of the life and ſtrength of our ſayd mother, which we cannot but ſee otherwiſe to be in great perill and danger, ſo the better that ſhe may ſtrongly encounter, ouercome, and ſubdue all, both her aduerſaries and ours. For <hi>Neſtor</hi> perſwading <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and <hi>Achilles</hi> to concord, ſaid, that otherwiſe <hi>Priamus</hi> would laugh them both to ſcorne. And wiſely ſayd <hi>Metius Suffetius</hi> to <hi>Tullus Hoſtilius</hi> king of the Romans, when the Albans and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were readie to ioyne battell the one with the other, vnderſtand, O king, that the <hi>Hetrurians,</hi> a mightie people, enuie vs both, &amp; only whiles we ſpoile one another, they exſpect that ſo we both being
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2585:52"/>once ſpent, may in the end both become a pray and ſpoile to them; And aduiſedly alſo therupon, to end that controuerſie, wheras the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans choſe 3 <hi>Horatians,</hi> and the <hi>Albans</hi> 3 <hi>Curiatians</hi> to fight a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, though therein the <hi>Curiatians</hi> had quickly ſlaine two of the <hi>Hora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> and alſo ſore wounded the third, yet we read in that ſtory, that he flying in pollicie, and ſo ſingling the 3 <hi>Curiatians</hi> being then all aliue, in the end, ſo, one after another, killed them all, which he could neuer haue done, if they had all held together: &amp; ſo the <hi>Romans</hi> by the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion agreed on in that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bat, conquered the <hi>Albans;</hi> whereby we may plainly as in a glaſſe ſee, that though two parts of three of our Romiſh enemies, ſeeme to vs already ſlaine, &amp; the third part alſo much woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, yet if by any means, that one can ſingle &amp; ſeuer vs, he wil hope in the end to conquer vs all. For whiles <hi>Athens</hi> &amp; <hi>Lacedemon</hi> iarred, both became a pray to the enemie, while <hi>Hanniball</hi> and <hi>Hanno</hi> enuied one another <hi>Carthage</hi> came to confuſion; &amp; whiles the two brethren <hi>Ethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocles</hi> and <hi>Polynices</hi> contended for the kingdome of <hi>Thebes,</hi> they both loſt themſelues and their kingdom. Likewiſe whiles <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> and <hi>Hircanus</hi> two brethren ſtroue for the kingdome of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a bootie to the <hi>Romans.</hi> And when <hi>Amon</hi> and <hi>Moab,</hi> and they of Mount Seir fell out amongſt themſelues, and ſo ſlue one another, we know how the holy ſtory ſheweth, their huge army thereby eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a rich ſpoile to <hi>Iehoſophat,</hi> 2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 20. whereas of the contrary we read there, that the amitie of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> was the very cauſe of <hi>Lots</hi> reſcue, and of all his friends and neighbours, out of the hands of fiue kings that had taken them all priſoners and captiues, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. And who knoweth not that by concord ſmall things increaſe, &amp; that by the contrary very great things come to nothing? and that a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold cord is not eaſily broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but yet, that vntwiſted it eaſily fals a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſo though a ſheafe of arrowes bound faſt together will not quickly be burſt, that yet looſed they are quickly knapt a ſunder? Iuſtly therfore did <hi>Sparta</hi> count the concord that was in that city, the ſtrongeſt and beſt wals that it could haue, and otherwiſe where that was wanting, that the ſtrongeſt wals that any city could haue, were but as wals of paper. Learne we therefore (deare brethren) in time to ſing with the <hi>Pſalmist, O how good and pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in vnity. Pſ.</hi> 133. &amp; therfore according both to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, &amp; the Apoſtles, let vs as much as is poſſible, &amp; in vs lieth, ſeeke peace with all men, and enſue it, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 34. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. And therfore alſo conſider we one another, as we are wiſht, <hi>He.</hi> 10. to prouoke one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2585:52"/>only to loue &amp; to good works not forſaking the fellowſhip that we haue amongſt our ſelues as ſome do, and learne as we haue bene taught of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Ro.</hi> 14.13. eſpecially of things of this kind, neither to be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded at or with one another, or to iudge one another, but rather to ſay with <hi>Abraham</hi> euery one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let there be no ſtrife betwixt vs, for we are brethren, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 13. ſo yeelding rather with him of our own right, as he then and there did to his inferiour <hi>Loth,</hi> if neede bee to redeeme and purchaſe our owne peace and the churches, ſo long eſpecially as we may ſo doe without breach of holines, as in this caſe of ours, I hope, I haue ſhewed we may. For if there be enuie, ſtrife, and diuiſion amongſt vs ſtill, &amp; that for things of no greater moment, <hi>Paul</hi> doth tell vs plainly, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. that we are carnall and walke as men. God therefore giue vs all once grace, ſo to make it appeare, that we haue mutuall conſolation in Chriſt, Comfort of loue, and fellowſhip of the ſpirit, Compaſſion and mercie, that we may fulfill his ioy in being of one accord and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.2. not doing any thing of vainglory or of contention, but in meekneſſe of mind, euery one eſteeming another better then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. and in following the things that concerne peace, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with one may edifie another, <hi>Ro.</hi> 14.19. and ſo ſtriuing in giuing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor who can giue moſt and firſt, <hi>Ro.</hi> 12.10. Now then ſaying with the Pſalmiſt 122. <hi>Vnto all, pray for the peace of Hieruſalem, Let them proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that loue her, peace be with in her wals, and proſperity within her pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces.</hi> I humbly beſeech the Lord to direct vs all herein, and in all our other actions to his owne glory and to our own euerlaſting comfort, and ſo I hartily bid thee farewell in the ſame Lord. 1606. <hi>February.</hi> 1.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Thine in the Lord vnfainedly,</hi> Thomas Sparke.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped, thus corrected.</head>
            <p>PAge. 1. for commended, read commaunded. Epiſt. dedic. line. 4. for bound. r. bould. Epiſt. to the Rea p. 3. l. 1. r. ſtronger for ſtrong. &amp; 18. for quieter. r. quiet. lier. &amp;. l. 22. for Biſhops, r. Biſhop. p. 8. l. 4. for ſhew. r. ſhewed, &amp;. l. 10. for point. r. courſe. p 7. l. 4. for. 3. r. 13. p. 9. l. 31. for act. 1. art p 18. for alſo. r. all ſo. p. 20. l. 35. for it. r. it, it &amp; any for many. p. 21. l 31. for ſome ey: r. ſome, ey. p. 22. l. 30. for follows r. allowes. &amp; for then. r. them. p. 23. l. 14. for reuerence. r. reference. p. 24. l. 35. after baptiſed put. p 25. l. 15. for as. r. is. p. 26. l. 1. for this. r. his. &amp; l. 27. for third r. thirty. p. 29. l. 5. for conference. r. reference. p. 34 l. 3. for. therin. r. then. p. 35 l. 10. for mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> r. intention. p. 40. for. there. r. the. l. 34. p. 42. l. 3. put out. &amp;. 46. l. 1. r. put out as. p. 51. l. 19. r. put out, any man. p. 63. <hi>l.</hi> 20. for howbei. r. howbeit. p. 69. <hi>l.</hi> 36. put out we p. 70. <hi>l.</hi> 2. put out. that. l. 34. for their. r. and there.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
